<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<allaboutnature>
		<enfj>
			<title>ENFJ - The "Mentor"</title>
			<overview>ENFJs are externally focused, introspective, altruistic, positive and have excellent people skills. They place utmost importance on helping others grow. They are warm and have a natural desire to be supportive and encouraging. Being charissmatic and posessing excellent language skills, they do well in leadership roles. ENFJs strive to enhance the lives of their human brethren. </overview>
			<temper>NF Temperament - The "Visionaries" NFs are introspective, intuitive and highly idealistic. They are subjective, compassionate "feeler" people that desire to contribute goodness and meaning to the lives of others. They are effective at doing this through their nurturing, insightful and encouraging nature. NFs despise conflict. They will do everything they can to make sure their loved ones get along with each other and are happy. NFs are imaginitive, creatively inclined and passionate about their choice causes. </temper>
			<population>•Total: 3% •Male: 1.5% •Female: 4.5%</population>
			<people>
							Real ENFJ People 
				•	Abraham Maslow - psychologist
				•	Andy Griffith - actor
				•	Ben Affleck - actor
				•	Ben Stiller - actor, comedian
				•	Bob Saget - actor
				•	Brenda Vaccaro - actress
				•	Craig T. Nelson - actor (Coach)
				•	Dennis Hopper - actor
				•	Diane Sawyer - television journalist
				•	Dick Van Dyke - actor
				•	Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. - minister, civil rights activist
				•	Elizabeth Dole - senator
				•	Francois Mitterand - French President
				•	James Garner - actor
				•	John Wooden - basketball player, coach	 	•	Johnny Depp - actor
				•	King David - King of Israel
				•	Kirstie Alley - actress
				•	Lauren Graham - actress
				•	Margaret Mead - cultural anthropologist
				•	Matthew McConaughey - actor
				•	Mikhail Gorbachev - last leader of Soviet Union
				•	Pete Sampras - tennis champion
				•	Peyton Manning - NFL quarterback
				•	Ralph Nader - attorney, political activist
				•	Randy Quaid - actor
				•	Ross Perot - businessman
				•	Tommy Lee Jones - actor
				•	William Aramony - United Way president
				•	William Cullen Bryant - poet


				Fictional ENFJs (Characters) 
				•	Faye Valentine - Cowboy Bebop	 	•	Jules Winnfield - Pulp Fiction

			</people>
			<career>
			ENFJ Career Matches

			ENFJs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Mentor/Visionary personality. 
			•	Accountant/Auditor
			•	Artist
			•	Administrator
			•	Actor
			•	Administrative Assistant
			•	Banker/Economist
			•	Consultant
			•	Computer Specialist
			•	Career Counselor
			•	Church Worker
			•	Diplomat
			•	Designer
			•	Events Coordinator
			•	Editor
			•	Engineer
			•	Facilitator
			•	Human Resources	 	•	Homemaker
			•	Librarian
			•	Musician
			•	Nurse
			•	Occupational Therapist
			•	Psychiatrist
			•	Psychologist/Counselor
			•	Project Manager
			•	Politician
			•	Social Worker
			•	Senior Manager
			•	Scientist
			•	Sales Representative
			•	Trainer
			•	Teacher/Professor
			•	Technical Specialist
			•	Writer
			</career>
			<brief>ENFJs are lively and enthusiastic facilitators who apply warmth and vision to helping people and meeting their needs. They are aware of people's aspirations and develop plans of action to make those aspirations into reality. They like organization and closure. They are at their best facilitating situations that require interpersonal sensitivity. ENFJs are tolerant and appreciative of others, seeking involvement with them in life's tasks. They are able communicators who are liberal in showing appreciation for others.</brief>
			<living>ENFJ children want life to be friendly, harmonious, and lively. They are responsible children because they like to please others and meet their needs. In doing for others, they usually find satisfaction for themselves. They are upset by conflict or disharmony. They are pleasant, exuberant and talkative. 
			ENFJ teenagers are constantly on the go, participating in many, many things. They enjoy a wide variety of activities, not only for that variety but also for the action and opportunity to be with others. They love being involved with friends, clubs, and any activities that let them be with others. ENFJs are often voted most congenial or nicest person in their class. Additionally, they may serve as leaders in their school activities. As students, they are able to focus on the interpersonal spirit or nature of the school and to speak eloquently to others about the school's best values. ENFJs are likable because they notice what is good about people.
			As young adults, ENFJs set goals early on, both in the personal and professional realms. They follow through diligently and usually attain what they seek. Often the goals they set have to do with making society a better place for people. ENFJs may sometimes feel pulled between financial gain and spiritual gain. 
			Many ENFJs take their religious and community values seriously and want others to do the same. Loyalty, commitment, and responsibility are important values to ENFJs, even as children. They often settle into organizations that have a values orientation, or they will find a spot in an organization that is centered on values or people's need. ENFJs make responsible spouses, employees, and community members. Because most ENFJs enjoy public speaking and seem to have a way with words, they are often asked to present the position of the groups to which they belong.
			Some ENFJs report that at mid-life they seek situations for themselves where it is possible for them to turn inward. This often takes a structured form such as meditation, journaling, or in some cases even career changes.
			In retirement, they are likely to want to settle geographically in an area where they have close personal relationships and/or close personal ties to a specific organization. The relationships and values that are imprtant to the ENFJ become even more so in their retirement. Many ENFJs participate in voluntary service work in retirement. 
			</living>
			<learning>ENFJs learn best in structured situations in which they are able to talk bout the lesson and interact with their peers. Because they want their teachers to be pleased with them, they attempt to be model students. They are willing to do what is required in order to become personally recognized by their teachers. Because they take criticism personally, they can either be wounded by it or be willing to redouble their efforts in order to change the criticism. ENFJs enjoy classes that have subject matter relating to people, their needs, their aspirations, and their characterizations. Many ENFJs choose the liberal arts because it gives them an opportunity to more fully explore humanity.
			ENFJs are good students when the subject matter relates to their strong relationship values and people orientation, and when the teacher is warm and personal. They apply the necessary effort and energy to complete the tasks that they start. ENFJs also like some independent learning and projects.
			</learning>
			<working>ENFJs focused on the organization's ideals and operate within those ideals. They focus on how organizations should treat people and communicate these values to others. They enjoy leading and facilitating teams, and like to bring matters to mutually beneficial conclusions. 
			ENFJs prefer a work setting that contains individuals focused on changing things for the betterment of others. They like an environment that is people oriented, supportive, and organized. They do their best when there is a spirit of harmony, with encouragement given for self-expression. And they like their work to be settled and orderly, but not so much so that it is dull, quiet, unchanging, or unchallenging.
			The ENFJ organizing style is to plan around the particular value or ideal and to supply the necessary energy toward its achievement or implementation. In the accomplishment of the goal, ENFJs will look at the people available and will assign tasks based on who needs the experience, the exposure, or the development. To a lesser degree, they will assign the task based on who needs the experience, the exposure, or the development. To a lesser degree, they will assign the task based purely on competency, because ENFJs feel it is more important to help others grow and develop new skills. If others have a particular deadline that needs to be met, the ENFJ will work to meet that deadline so that the other person will be happy.
			ENFJs prefer occupations that reflect their ideals and that promote harmonious relationships with others. They tend to be attracted to occupation with a service orientation. They generally follow policies and procedures as long as those procedures are compatible with people's needs. They prefer things to be organized and decided rather than haphazard. 
			Some occupations seem to be more attractive to ENFJs: actor, clergy, consultant, counselor and therapist, designer, home economist, musician, religious worker, teacher, writer, and other occupations that allow them to be of service to others.
			</working>
							<leading>The ENFJ puts relationships and responsibilities before personal leisure. Their time can be imposed upon easily; however, they need to guard against excessive responsiveness to avoid reaching overload.
				They particularly enjoy reading novels and seeing movies in order to see how the characters play out the life issues and questions presented in the story; it gives them an opportunity to see how others live and get along. They enjoy discussing their reading and may join book groups in order to do that. They like going to movies and plays with others and like to comment on the plot characterization. They are close observers of others' behavior.
				Many ENFJs join religious or community-oriented groups whose focus is to work for better understanding between people. ENFJs like discussion and an opportunity to talk about values and philosophical topics. Many do not like activities in which there is a great deal of competition or in which someone or something could be hurt. 
				</leading>
							<loving>For the ENFJ, love means flowers, poetry, candlelight dinners --- in other words, romance with a capital R. When they first fall in love, they fall in love with an ideal perspective of what the relationship will be, and they fall deeply, head over heels. ENFJs value commitment and loyalty, and look for it from their partner. They typically enjoy activities with their partners that allow them to discuss the relationship and focus on what each person truly believes. When commitments are broken, ENFJs become upset because they see the breakup as a personal reflection on them and because they have idealized the relationship. Since they are willing to put the time and effort into the relationship, they expect it will continue on as it was from the very start. Relationships have their ups and downs; the downs, however, are particularly hard on the ENFJ, who does not manage disharmony well.
				When scorned, ENFJs may be resentful, spiteful, and deeply hurt. Because they are acutely aware of emotional matters they take the breakup of a relationship especially hard. They are willing to discuss the ending of the relationship with only a few others because they feel a sense of blame and shame for the relationship not working out.
				ENFJ's are outstanding leaders of groups, both task groups and growth groups. They have the charming characteristic of seeming to take for granted that they will be followed, never doubting that people will want to do what they suggest. And, more often than not, people do, because this type has unusual charisma. ENFJ's place a high value on cooperation from others and are most willing to cooperate themselves. 
				Found in only 5 percent of the general population, ENFJ's place people as being of highest importance and priority. As a result, ENFJ's may find themselves feeling responsible for the feelings of others to an extent which places a burden on the relationship. An ENFJ communicates caring, concern, and a willingness to become involved. Thus people turn to ENFJ's for nurture and support, which an ENFJ is usually able to deliver. At times, however, these kinds of demands can overwhelm ENFJ's, who find at this point that they lack the skills to dissociate. ENFJ's do not seem able to turn away from these demands even when they become unreasonable. Or, if forced to let go of the burden through sheer unavailability of time or energy, ENFJ's experience a guilt all out of proportion to the realities of the commitment made to the relationship. 
				ENFJ's are especially vulnerable to idealizing interpersonal relationships, raising these relationships to a plane which seldom can sustain the realities of human nature. Because of this tendency to raise interpersonal relations to the ideal, ENFJ's may unwittingly overpower their friends, who believe that they cannot possibly live up to an ENFJ's perception of them. The fact is, ENFJ's are extraordinarily tolerant of others, seldom critical, and always trustworthy. 
				ENFJ's take communication for granted and believe that they are understood and that their communications are accepted. Just as they themselves are accepting, so do they assume that others are the same. When ENFJ's find that their position or beliefs were not comprehended or accepted, they are surprised, puzzled, and sometimes hurt. Fortunately, this does not happen with high frequency, as ENFJ's have a remarkable fluency with language, especially in speech; they are particularly adept when communicating face-to-face as opposed to communicating in writing. They are influential, therefore, in groups, having no hesitation about speaking out, no matter how large or small the group may be. 
				ENFJ's have an unusual ability to relate to others with empathy, taking into themselves the characteristics, emotions, and beliefs of others. This can pose a danger for ENFJ's because they can unconsciously over-identify with others and pick up their burdens as if they were their own. In the process, ENFJ's may risk their own sense of identity. They have a natural ability to mimic because of this highly developed ability to empathize by introjection. They are likely to be very concerned about the problems of those close to them, but they also may get as deeply involved in the problems of those not so close and may find themselves over-extended emotionally. 
				ENFJ's would do well to follow their hunches, for their intuition tends to be well developed. Decisions made purely on the basis of logic may not be so sound, and checking with a person who has a strong T preference might be at times advisable for the ENFJ. In the framework of values, however, the ENFJ is on certain ground. Generally, they know what they prefer and can read other people with outstanding accuracy. Seldom is an ENFJ wrong about the motivations or intent of another, hidden or not. 
				</loving>
							<careerdetail>This longing for the perfect carries over into the careers of ENFJ's, who experience some degree of restlessness whatever their jobs. And, as with ENFP's, ENFJ's have a wide range of occupations which offer success. Being verbally adept, ENFJ's contribute to an unusual level when dealing with people, particularly face-to-face; the media, the ministry, and the stage and screen are populated with successful ENFJ's. They make superior therapists, charismatic teachers, excellent executives, and personalized salespersons. Areas that would not permit utilization of the interactional talents of ENFJ's for example, accounting, should be avoided; otherwise, almost any people-to-people occupation where personal, sustained contact is involved capitalizes on the personality of an ENFJ. 
				ENFJ'S like to have things settled and organized. They prefer to plan both work and social engagements ahead and tend to be absolutely reliable in honoring these commitments. ENFJ's are very much at home in complex situations which require the juggling of much data. At the same time, they can handle people with charm and concern. ENFJ's are usually popular wherever they are. Their ability to be comfortable either leading or following makes them easy to have around, whatever the situation. A well-developed ENFJ group leader can provide, almost endlessly, activities for groups to engage in with almost no preplanning and can find adequate roles for members of the group to play. In some, this can amount to genius which other types find hard to emulate. In this ability to organize without planning there is a certain similarity to an ESFJ, but the latter acts more as a master of ceremonies than as a leader of groups. The ESFJ is more of a recreational leader, who insures that each member has fun at a party and that the right things are expressed at social occasions, especially institutional social occasions such as weddings, funerals parties, and the like. ENFJ's, just like the ESFJ's, value harmonious human relations above all else; but ENFJ's are not so easily crushed by indifference as are ESFJ's and are more independent of other's valuations. 
				</careerdetail>
							<home>ENFJ's are socially adept and make excellent companions and mates. They also are deeply devoted to their children, yet tend not to be domineering to either the children or mate. In fact, the ENFJ is so even-tempered that he or she can be victimized by a mate who might have become more and more demanding. 
				ENFJ mates always try to please and feel personally responsible when home life does not go smoothly. They are tireless in their efforts to see that it does, providing generously from available income, time, and energy. This dedication often exists, however, side by side with an ENFJ's dream of the perfect relationship-a characteristic of all NF's, but one which is particularly strong in an ENFJ. Thus an ENFJ has that longing for the ideal that results in a vague dissatisfaction with whatever is in the way of relationships, mating as well as friendships. 
				</home>
							<midlife>At midlife, ENFJ's might want to expand their capabilities toward introverted activities such as reading, gardening, painting. They also may want to increase their sensitivity to classical music, subtleties of fine foods and beverages, beginning to develop ever-increasing discriminations of fineness among fine things. Already likely to be a gourmet, an ENFJ might become a connoisseur art collector, for example, or an expert of medieval tapestries. Also, the development further of intellectual capabilities might interest ENFJ's at midlife, perhaps taking the direction of formal study. ENFJ's have the ability to appreciate both people and nature, and more time spent in travel might be gratifying, particularly if this was used as an opportunity to collect works of art. </midlife>
							<mates>Who can complement this growth-catalyst? The opposite on the S side is ISTP, the "artisan." It is not difficult to see how the teacher inherent in the ENFJ would want to "bring out" the craftsman in the ISTP. The artisan, however, has another side to his nature that pops up occasionally and in some cases is a life theme: adventure and exploration. The ISTP can, so to speak, be wayward, take off for parts unknown. It is difficult to imagine a similar desire on the part of the ENFJ to bring out adventuresomeness. 
				The ENFJ, on the intuitive side, finds the INTP attractive. Now here is a splendid target for our catalyst, for beneath the cool, collected, detached, and doubting exterior lies an architect of buildings, machines, tools, operations, tactics, languages, mathematics, or whatever can be designed. If, that is, this latently capable designer can be "activated" or "brought out".


				ENFJs put a lot of effort and enthusiasm into their relationships. To some extent, the ENFJ defines themself by the closeness and authenticity of their personal relationships, and are therefore highly invested in the business of relationships. They have very good people skills, and are affectionate and considerate. They are warmly affirming and nurturing. The excel at bringing out the best in others, and warmly supporting them. They want responding affirmation from their relationships, although they have a problem asking for it. When a situation calls for it, the ENFJ will become very sharp and critical. After having made their point, they will return to their natural, warm selves. They may have a tendency to "smother" their loved ones, but are generally highly valued for their genuine warmth and caring natures. 
				</mates>
							<strengths>Most ENFJs will exhibit the following strengths with regards to relationship issues: 
				•	Good verbal communication skills 
				•	Very perceptive about people's thoughts and motives 
				•	Motivational, inspirational; bring out the best in others 
				•	Warmly affectionate and affirming 
				•	Fun to be with - lively sense of humor, dramatic, energetic, optimistic 
				•	Good money skills 
				•	Able to "move on" after a love relationship has failed (although they blame themselves) 
				•	Loyal and committed - they want lifelong relationships 
				•	Strive for "win-win" situations 
				•	Driven to meet other's needs 
				</strengths>
							<weakness>Most ENFJs will exhibit the following weaknesses with regards to relationships issues: 
				•	Tendency to be smothering and over-protective 
				•	Tendency to be controling and/or manipulative 
				•	Don't pay enough attention to their own needs 
				•	Tend to be critical of opinions and attitudes which don't match their own 
				•	Sometimes unaware of social appropriateness or protocol 
				•	Extremely sensitive to conflict, with a tendency to sweep things under the rug as an avoidance tactic 
				•	Tendency to blame themselves when things go wrong, and not give themselves credit when things go right 
				•	Their sharply defined value systems make them unbending in some areas 
				•	They may be so attuned to what is socially accepted or expected that they're unable to assess whether something is "right" or "wrong" outside of what their social circle expects. 
				</weakness>	
		</enfj>
	
	
	
	
		<enfp>
				<title>ENFP - The "Advocate"</title>
				<overview>ENFPs are introspective, values-oriented, inspiring, social and extremely expressive. They actively send their thoughts and ideas out into the world as a way to bring attention to what they feel to be important, which often has to do with ethics and current events. ENFPs are natural advocates, attracting people to themselves and their cause with excellent people skills, warmth, energy and positivity. ENFPs are described as creative, resourceful, assertive, spontaneous, life-loving, charismatic, passionate and experimental. </overview>
				<temper>NFs are introspective, intuitive and highly idealistic. They are subjective, compassionate "feeler" people that desire to contribute goodness and meaning to the lives of others. They are effective at doing this through their nurturing, insightful and encouraging nature. NFs despise conflict. They will do everything they can to make sure their loved ones get along with each other and are happy. NFs are imaginitive, creatively inclined and passionate about their choice causes.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 5.5%
				Male: 4.5%
				Female: 6.5% 
				</population>
				<people>
								Real ENFP People 
				•	Alicia Silverstone - actress (Clueless), fashion model
				•	Andy Kaufman - American entertainer
				•	Andy Rooney - television writer
				•	Bill Cosby - actor, comedian, activist
				•	Bill Moyers - journalist, commentator
				•	Bob Dylan - singer-songwriter, musician
				•	Bus ter Keaton - silent film comic actor
				•	Carol Burnett - comedian
				•	Charles Dickens - English novelist
				•	Dave Thomas - businessman (Wendy's), philanthropist
				•	Dr. Seuss (Theodor Seuss Geise) - writer, cartoonist
				•	Franz Joseph Haydn - composer
				•	James Dobson - evangelical psychologist
				•	Joseph Campbell - writer, orator
					•	King Jordan - deaf president of Gallaudet University
				•	Lewis Grizzard - humorist
				•	Martin Short - Canadian actor, comedian
				•	Paul Harvey - radio broadcaster
				•	Paul Robeson - actor, athlete, singer, writer, activist
				•	Phil Donahue - TV personality
				•	Regis Philbin - TV personality
				•	Robin Williams - actor
				•	Samuel Clemens (Mark Twain) - writer
				•	Sandra Bullock - actress
				•	Sinbad - actor, comedian
				•	Upton Sinclair - author, investigative journalist
				•	Will Rogers - Comedian


				Fictional ENFPs (Characters) 
				•	Ariel - The Little Mermaid
				•	Balki - Perfect Strangers
				•	Dr. Doug Ross - ER
					•	Lara Antipova - Doctor Zhivago
				•	Steve Urkel - Family Matters
				•	Will - The Fresh Prince of Bel-Air


				</people>
				<career>
								ENFPs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Advocate/Visionary personality. 
				•	Artist
				•	Art Director
				•	Actor
				•	Accountant/Auditor
				•	Banker/Economist
				•	Consultant
				•	Career Counselor
				•	Conference Planner
				•	Church Worker
				•	Diplomat
				•	Dietitian/Nutritionist
				•	Designer
				•	Entrepreneur
				•	Engineer
				•	Editor
				•	Human Resources
				•	Housing Director
				•	Homemaker
				•	Journalist
				•	Lawyer/Attorney
				•	Musician	 	•	Merchandise Planner
				•	Marketer
				•	Massage Therapist
				•	Nurse
				•	Newscaster
				•	Occupational Therapist
				•	Public Relations
				•	Psychologist/Counselor
				•	Painter
				•	Politician
				•	Project Manager
				•	Researcher
				•	Scientist
				•	Social Worker
				•	Speech Pathologist
				•	Social Scientist
				•	Senior Manager
				•	Trainer
				•	Teacher/Professor
				•	Technical Specialist
				•	Writer

				
				</career>
				<brief>ENFPs are initiators of change who are keenly perceptive of possibilities, and who energize and stimulate through their contagious enthusiasm. They prefer the start-up phase of a project or relationship, and are tireless in the pursuit of new-found interests. ENFPs are able to anticipate the needs of others and to offer them needed help and appreciation. They bring zest, joy, liveliness, and fun to all aspects of their lives. They are at their best in situations that are fluid and changing, and that allow them to express their creativity and use their charisma.</brief>
				<living>ENFP children are 'into everything.' Their natural curiosity results in children for whom questions were invented. They often spend long periods of time devising new and original --- but not necessarily practical --- languages, plays, and scenarios. Many ENFPs enjoy drawing, writing, playacting, and dreaming. They are often chosen as leaders because of their persuasive enthusiasm and their energy for new and different ways of developing things.
ENFP teenagers are agreeable, sociable, outgoing people who like to imagine themselves in the future. They spend many hours wondering and discussing with friends whom they will marry, where they will live, what their children will be like, and what work they will do. They leave no option or possibility unexplored and find it difficult to see themselves in any single job or career.
Because they see endless possibilities, to select one possibility appears to the ENFP to be too narrow a focus. They hate to be boxed into a career for life and therefore hesitate and resist making decisions. It is unwise for ENFPs to settle down too early, and they make the soundest choices when they delay career and marriage decisions until their middle to late twenties. Often when a decision is made, ENFPs will still leave a number of options open or change their minds as they encounter new information.
Even in their everyday activities, ENFPs often search for the new and the novel. If there is a logical route to work and ENFP has been driving that way continually, he or she will likely tire of it and look for other routes.
ENFPs are more likely than other types to change from one career to another, demonstrating their versatility in doing so. It is not uncommon to hear stories of ENFPs who have established themselves in a career and who, when faced with the daily routine of maintaining it, leave it to start another. 
Adult ENFPs maintain characteristics that might be considered youthful, such as enthusiasm, curiosity, and a zestful outlook on life. As a result, people often enjoy being with them. Many times they are young-in-spirit as they age, perhaps because of their temperament.
ENFPs look forward to retirement as a time that can bring freedom from the restrictions of the work world and ample opportunity to pursue their varied interests. However, if ENFPs become disabled or experience a lack of resources, such as money, they may become despondent because this restricts their ability to quest after new experiences. 
</living>
				<learning>ENFPs often learn best through a variety of means, such as observing, reading, and listening to and interacting with others. They enjoy the search for new ideas and possibilities, and will put in the time necessary to master subjects they find interesting. One strength is their enthusiasm for the process of discovery. They enjoy survey courses, comparative studies, and disciplines in which there is much to research and explore. They do not like classes that are too structured, that consist only of lectures, and that allow no room for their imagination. They may get caught up in the learning process and consequently need strict deadlines to bring a project to completion. 
ENFPs prefer a learning environment in which the teacher takes personal interest in them, in which there is an opportunity to talk about ideas with their peers, and in which there is a chance to ask questions and develop new ideas.
A motto that might describe the ENFP as a learner is "There's always another way or another answer."
</learning>
				<working>ENFPs often follow a nonlinear career track and nontraditional routes to obtaining knowledge, qualifications, and skills. When they are committed to what they do, they are enthusiastic to the point of preaching to the entire world about it. For an ENFP, work must be fun and must contribute to something larger than merely collecting a paycheck.
The preferred work setting for ENFPs contains imaginative people focused on human possibilities. ENFPs want a work environment that is both physically and mentally colorful. They prefer a participative and collegial atmosphere in which employees are included in the decision making. ENFPs are less productive where there is disharmony because they pay more attention to the relationships between people at work than they do to the tasks. Their ideal job would offer variety, novelty, challenge, and freedom from tight supervision; it would be idea oriented and imaginative, and would have lively, energetic people enjoying themselves and their tasks. 
Most ENFPs will say they are organized, but others might not see them that way. Their desire to be open to the moment tends to outweigh their need to be organized. Usually ENFP work space is arranged haphazardly, with work materials and personal momentos scattered about. In terms of the management of time, ENFPs find it particularly difficult to estimate accurately how long an activity will take. Because people's needs are more important than schedules, ENFPs are often late and characteristically full of apologies for their tardiness.
ENFPs prefer occupations that reflect their ideals and that promote harmonious relationships with others. They tend to be attracted to occupations with a service orientation. ENFPs usually find a place in their work life for creativity. They particularly enjoy people-oriented work in which they are able to combine things in new and different ways to benefit humanity. Flexibility and autonomy are important to ENFPs, who may bolt from organizations in which this is not attainable.
Common occupations picked by ENFPs include artist, clergy, consultant, counselor, entertainer, journalist, public relations worker, social scientist, social worker, teacher, and other occupations that allow ENFPs to use their creativity and insight.
</working>
				<leading>ENFPs are energetic and enthusiastic leaders who are likely to take charge when a new endeavor needs a visionary spokesperson. ENFPs are values-oriented people who become champions of causes and services relating to human needs and dreams. Their leadership style is one of soliciting and recognizing others' contributions and of evaluating the personal needs of their followers. ENFPs are often charismatic leaders who are able to help people see the possibilities beyond themselves and their current realities. They function as catalysts.
 </leading>
				<loving>For ENFPs, loving is an almost constant state. They are generally involved or in love with someone or something new. ENFPs may have originated the quotation "All the world loves a lover." When falling in love, they explore all the new possibilities in the relationship, and the new person is studied in every way. The ENFP tends to idealize his or her current relationship and will often say that their current one is "the best ever."
It might be argued that each type, when first in love, resembles a garden-variety ENFP, because ENFPs normally behave like people in love. Some of the cultural cliches about falling in love - such as "Falling in love with love," "Head over heels in love," "Love is blind," "All the world loves a lover," and "Throw caution to the wind" - seem to apply to the ENFP. This same boundless affection can be showered upon friends, co-workers, and others. People often feel unconditionally loved by ENFPs, but over time many of these relationships dissipate, as in "When I'm not near the ones I love, I love the ones I'm near."
ENFPs are delightful, enthusiastic partners who are young in spirit; there is rarely a dull moment with them. They readily note their partner's best aspects. They may overlook obvious details and facts about their partners that might cause other types to be more cautious. As relationships progress, ENFPs romanticise their partners and make strong efforts to rationalize any discrepancy between the reality and their "ideal."
When they are in love, they may either overcommit and ignore any unpleasant yet true facts; or they may undercommit, believing that there may be a better love "just around the corner." Therefore, ENFPs may be seen as fickle in their relationships as they search for the "right one."
When and if the flaws in the relationship become too obvious to ENFPs, they may admit defeat, feeling great pain because they have put so much energy into perfecting a particular relationship. When ENFPs are scorned, they overgeneralize about their partners' worst faults. Because ENFPs thrive on new possibilities, when they fall out of love, they rebound quickly.

For ENFPs nothing occurs which does not have some significance, and they have an uncanny sense of the motivations of others. This gives them a talent for seeing life as an exciting drama, pregnant with possibilities for both good and evil. This type is found in only about 5 percent of the general population, but they have great influence because of their extraordinary impact on others. ENFPs strive toward the authentic, even when acting spontaneously, and this is usually communicated nonverbally to others, who find this characteristic attractive. ENFPs, however, find their own efforts of authenticity and spontaneity always lacking, and tend to heap coals of fire on themselves, always berating themselves for being so conscious of self. 
ENFPs consider intense emotional experiences vital; when they have these, however, they are made uneasy by a sense of being there but with a part of themselves split off. They strive for congruency, but always see themselves in some danger of losing touch with their real feelings, which ENFPs possess in a wide range and variety. 
ENFPs exercise a continuous scanning of the external environment, and nothing out of the ordinary is likely to escape their attention. They are keen and penetrating observers and are capable of intense concentration on another individual while aware of what is going on about them. Their attention is never passive or casual, never wandering, but always directed. At times, ENFPs find themselves interpreting events in terms of another's "hidden motive," giving special meaning to words or actions. This interpretation tends to be negative and, more often than not, inaccurately negative. In the process, an ENFP may find that he or she has introduced an unnecessary, toxic element into the relationship. While ENFPs are brilliantly perceptive, they can make serious mistakes in judgment, which works to their discomfort. These mistakes derive from their tendency to focus on data which confirm their own biases. They may be absolutely correct in their perceptions but wrong in their conclusions. 
Because they tend to be hypersensitive and hyper-alert, they may suffer from muscle tension. They live in readiness for emergencies; because they have this facility, they assume this is true for others. They can become bored rather quickly with both situations and people, and resist repeating experiences. They enjoy the process of creating something-an idea or a project-but are not as interested in the follow-through. They are typically enthusiastic, and this is contagious. People get caught up and entranced by an ENFP. Yet this type is marked with a fierce independence, repudiating any kind of subordination, either in themselves or in others in relation to them. They do tend to attribute more power to authority figures than is there and give over to these figures an ability to "see through" them-which also is not apt to be there. While ENFPs resist the notion of others becoming dependent or having power over them, their charisma draws followers who wish to be shown the way. ENFPs constantly find themselves surrounded by others who look toward the ENFP for wisdom, inspiration, courage, leadership, and so on-an expectancy which, at times, weighs rather heavily on an ENFP. 
ENFPs are characteristically optimistic and are surprised when people or events do not turn out as anticipated. Often their confidence in the innate goodness of fate and human nature is a self-fulling prophecy

</loving>
				<careerdetail>ENFPs have a remarkable latitude in career choices and succeed in many fields. As workers, they are warmly enthusiastic, high-spirited, ingenious, imaginative, and can do almost anything that interests them. They can solve most problems, particularly those dealing with people. They are charming and at ease with colleagues; others enjoy their presence. ENFPs are outstanding in getting people together, and are good at initiating meetings and conferences, although not as talented at providing for the operational details of these events. They enjoy inventing new ways of doing things, and their projects tend to become a cause, quickly becoming personalized. They are imaginative themselves, but can have difficulty picking up on ideas and projects initiated by others. They must make these ideas and projects their own if ENFPs are to lend their energy and interest. Once people or projects become routine, ENFPs are likely to lose interest; what might be is always more fascinating than what is. ENFPs make extensive use of their intuitive powers. They usually have a wide range of personal and telephone contacts, expending energy in maintaining both career and personal relationships. 
ENFPs make excellent salespeople, advertising people, politicians, screen or play writers, and in general are attracted to the interpretative arts, particularly character acting. People to people work is essential for ENFPs, who need the feedback of interaction with others. ENFPs may find it difficult to work within the constraints of an institution, especially in following rules, regulations, and standard operating procedures. More frequently, institutional procedures and policies are targets to be challenged and bent by the will of an ENFP. Colleagues and superiors sometimes find themselves in the position of having to accommodate and salvage. At times, ENFPs demonstrate impatience with others; they may get into difficulty in an organization by siding with its detractors, who find in an ENFP a sympathetic ear and a natural rescuer. In occupational choice, ENFPs quickly become restless if the choice involves painstaking detail and follow-through over a period of time. Variety in day-to-day operations and interactions best suits the talents of ENFPs, who need quite a bit of latitude in which to exercise their adaptive ingenuity. 
</careerdetail>
				<home>As mates, ENFPs tend to be charming, gentle, sympathetic, and nonconformist. They are not likely to be interested in the less-inspired routines of daily maintenance and ever will be seeking new outlets for their inspirations. As parents, ENFPs are devoted although somewhat unpredictable in handling their children, shifting from a role of friend-in-need-rescuer to stern authority figure. They may not always be willing to enforce their impulsive pronouncements, but leave it to their mates to follow through. A mate of an ENFP can expect charming surprises: extravagant generosity punctuated by periods of frugality. Independent actions regarding money on the part of an ENFP's mate are not ordinarily welcomed, and the mate may find him or herself in an embarrassing situation of having to return purchases. ENFPs generally are the ones in charge of the home, and a conflict free home is desired, almost demanded. When he or she is in charge of economic resources, the ENFP's home may contain extravagant luxuries while necessities may be missing. They are not always interested in saving for the future and may be casual in giving consideration to such things as life insurance, savings accounts, and even a ready cash supply for mate and children. 
ENFPs are characteristic in their pursuit of the novel, their strong sense of the possible, and outstanding intuitive powers. At the same time, they have warmth and fun with people and generally are unusually skilled in handling people. Their extraverted role tends to be well developed, as is their capacity for the novel and the dramatic. 
</home>
				<midlife>At midlife ENFPs may need to give particular attention to their physical health, concentrating perhaps on developing resources to release muscular tensions. Body awareness and relaxation exercises may deserve investment of energies; work with various art media such as oils, clay, and building materials may be pleasurable. They need also to discipline themselves against beginning too many projects and making commitments to too many people. They should more fully enjoy relationships and opportunities that already exist, even at the expense of neglecting new ones. ENFPs certainly need to relax, to decrease the number of hours invested in work, and turn to recreational activities-travel, visual entertainment, and physically relaxing activities. </midlife>
				<mates>Here is the herald, the spirited bearer of tiding. But underneath this effervescent enthusiasm is a person fiercely dedicated to "meaning" in life and reminiscent of the INFP crusader. Only the ENFP neither crusades nor meditates, not for long anyway. The ENFP is into everything, frisky, not unlike a puppy, sniffing around to see what's new. ENFP has to be in on everything, can't bear to be left out of anything. That's why they make such splendid reporters, newscasters, and journalists. Mercury. Now who would enjoy this frisky, bubbly-yet serious-person? The Rock of Gibraltar, of course-ISTJ, the "trustee." ISTJ, who revels in "keeping the books in order," "balancing the budget," "securing and ensuring," "stabilizing and steadying," "honoring contracts," "keeping the ship on a steady course" and "shipshape," delights also in providing anchorage and safe harbor for the heraldic ENFP. 
Who else is attractive and attracted to our curious journalist? Strangely, the abstract scientist: INTJ. Lost in his abstract world of hypotheses, he finds anchorage in the person who knows what's going on in the real world! So ENFP can be an anchor or have an anchor, and who can tell which will be chosen.
</mates>
				<strengths>Most ENFPs will exhibit the following strengths with regards to relationships issues: 
•	Good communication skills 
•	Very perceptive about people's thought and motives 
•	Motivational, inspirational; bring out the best in others 
•	Warmly affectionate and affirming 
•	Fun to be with - lively sense of humor, dramatic, energetic, optimistic 
•	Strive for "win-win" situations 
•	Driven to meet other's needs 
•	Usually loyal and dedicated 
</strengths>
				<weakness>Most ENFPs will exhibit the following weaknesses with regards to relationship issues: 
•	Tendency to be smothering 
•	Their enthusiasm may lead them to be unrealistic 
•	Uninterested in dealing with "mundane" matters such as cleaning, paying bills, etc. 
•	Hold onto bad relationships long after they've turned bad 
•	Extreme dislike of conflict 
•	Extreme dislike of criticism 
•	Don't pay attention to their own needs 
•	Constant quest for the perfect relationship may make them change relationships frequently 
•	May become bored easily 
•	Have difficulty scolding or punishing others 
</weakness>	
			</enfp>
	
	
		<entj>
				<title>ENTJ - The "Chief"</title>
				<overview>ENTJs are strategic, organized and possess natural leadership qualities. They are master coordinators that can effectively give direction to groups. They are able to understand complicated organizational situations and quick to develop intelligent solutions. ENTJs are outspoken and will not hesitate to speak of their plans for improvement. They are decisive and value knowledge, efficiency and competence. </overview>
				<temper>NTs are introspective, logical and on a constant quest for knowledge. They are practical and unsentimental in their approach to problem solving. The actions of an NT are precise and follow a systematic course. Abstract, theoretical and technically adept, NTs are naturally inventive. They can also be described as being analytical, intellectual, inquisitive, independent and complex.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 3%
Male: 4.5%
Female: 1.5% 
</population>
				<people>
				Real ENTJ People 
•	Al Gore - former American Vice President
•	Benny Goodman - Jazz musician
•	Bill Gates - Microsoft Founder
•	Candace Bergen - actress (Murphy Brown)
•	Dave Letterman - TV show host, comedian
•	Edward Teller - theoretical physicist
•	Franklin D. Roosevelt - American President
•	Harrison Ford - actor (Indiana Jones)
 	•	Jim Carrey - actor, comedian
•	Margaret Thatcher - British Prime Minister
•	Newt Gingrich - Speaker of the House
•	Patrick Stewart - actor (Star Trek's "Cpt. Picard")
•	Richard Nixon - American President
•	Sigourney Weaver - actress
•	Steve Martin - actor, comedian
•	Whoopi Goldberg - actress, comedian


Fictional ENTJs (Characters) 
•	Beatrix Kiddo (The Bride) - Kill Bill Vol. I
•	Jordi LaForge - Star Trek: The Next Generation	 	•	Winston 'The Wolf' Wolfe - Pulp Fiction

				</people>
				<career>
				ENTJs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Chief/Intellectual personality. 
•	Business Administrator
•	Corporate Executive Officer
•	Computer Consultant
•	Entrepreneur
•	Judge
•	Lawyer/Attorney	 	•	Mortgage Banker
•	Manager
•	Politician
•	Scientist
•	Systems Analyst 
•	Teacher/Professor

				</career>
				<brief>ENTJs take charge quickly and deal directly with problems, especially in situations that involve confusion and inefficiency. They provide structure to the organizations to which they belong and design strategies to accomplish their personal and organizational goals. They are 'take charge' people who organise their own and others' external environments. They use their resources to find a way to meet the challenge. They are at their best in using their analytical and strategic thinking.</brief>
				<living>ENTJ children need to have goals for everything. These goals may be related to achievements such as swimming the fifty-yard freestyle on second faster than they did the previous year, getting a straight-A report card, or winning the school math contest. They seek power and control. They want to have an impact. Because of their desire to take charge, they are often leaders.
ENTJs enjoy an active and diverse lifestyle. They are likely to be in extracurricular activities and often function as the team captain, the president, or the leader. They pursue leadership roles very directly and have difficulty following others unless those individuals demonstrate more competence than they themselves have. Even then, it may be tough for the ENTJ to follow long.
ENTJs are likely to commit to a career goal early, often in their teen years. They determine their overall goals and objectives and what it will take to accomplish them. Whatever ENFJs do must make sense to them according to their logic or they have difficulty doing it.
In mature adulthood, ENTJs are often in leadership positions in their work organizations. They go after what they want with fusto. They set their sights high and work hard. Work and its related activities may become their lives. They may find retirement unsettling, boring, and difficult because it may bring with it a loss of the power that they had during their working years. Often they make arrangements so that they do not have to retire. 
</living>
				<learning>ENTJs see education as one of the major ways of getting ahead. They are willing to learn about the past and what is but always with the mind-set of how that information affects their future. They particularly enjoy critiquing and solving problems. They apply their logical systems view to the issues they deal with. They want to change things to fit their concept of what should be. They learn best through a variety of instructional methods, including lectures and group activities. Without variety and action in the classroom boredom sets in. 
ENTJs like to debate and view problems from all sides. They are comfortable critiquing and analyzing. and do not mind intellectual conflict in the classroom. They like challenge. They may have a general study plan laid out, with test dates and paper deadlines noted. They set up a schedule and work to attain the goal within that time.
</learning>
				<working>At work, ENTJs contribute a wealth of energy directed toward the goals and those of the organization. Their sense of identity is closely tied to how they carry out their responsibilities. They are curious about new ideas and theories, evaluating them in terms of their goals. They are very efficient, competitive, strategic, and task focused.
Occupations that require tough-mindedness, goal direction, and a global perspective tend to attract ENTJs. They use logic and analysis to form conclusions, to organize themselves and others, to give direction, and to take charge. Some occupations seem to be especially attractive to ENTJs: administrator, attorney, consultant, credit investigator, labor relations worker, manager, marketing personnel, mortgage banker, personnel professional, systems analyst, and other occupations that allow them to use their strategic sense.
</working>
				<leading>If one word were used to capture ENTJ's style, it would be commandant. The basic driving force and need of ENTJ's is to lead, and from an early age they can be observed taking over groups. This type is found in approximately 5 percent of the total population. ENTJ's have a strong urge to give structure wherever they are-to harness people to distant goals. Their empirical, objective, and extraverted thinking may be highly developed; if this is the case, they use classification, generalization, summarization, adduction of evidence, and demonstration with ease. They resemble ESTJ's in their tendency to establish plans for a task, enterprise, or organization, but ENTJ's search more for policy and goals than for regulations and procedures. An ENTJ's introverted thinking (analysis and conservation) may be less well developed than the extraverted thinking processes, and the ENTJ leader may turn to an ENTP or INTP to provide his kind of input. ENTJ's are similar to INTJ's except that the former places greater trust in empirical thought than in intuition; it is the ENTJ's own intuitive sense of coherence, however, that augments and supports their empirical thinking. </leading>
				<loving>For the ENTJ, love needs to fit into the overall picture and may become subservient to their larger goals. Love is always within the context of what the relationship is. One ENTJ stated, "I don't allow love to course freely through my body. God forbid that it should control me rather than I control it!" Love means a match between the ENTJ's needs and what the partner provides. The loved one is, in a sense, an extension of the ENTJ's vision, preferably acting in a supportive, not competing, role. ENTJs tend to make rigorous demands of love. While they may fall in love easily, they maintain that love only if the other person is willing to accept the ENTJ's directness and need for independence. 
Because attractiveness is a part of our culture and an initial standard for many relationships and because ENTJs like to do better than the standard, they particularly take note of the attractive people. The often wonder if they can 'win the heart' of the attractive other. It becomes almost a game for them. 
The partner of ENTJ can expect a hard-working and industrious provider who may use the fruits of his or her labor as an expression of love. They may not be as verbally communicative of their loving feelings as others types. 
ENTJs expect to have their needs met in relationships, while maintaining their independence. When the partner can no longer do that, it is logical for them to sever ties and to move on. However, when ENTJs are scorned by others, they may feel a passionate devastation and a strong sense of loss that is seldom shared with others. However, this sense of loss and gloom generally lasts only a short period before they are ready to move on.
</loving>
				<careerdetail>Although ENTJ's are tolerant of established procedures, they can abandon any procedure when it can be shown to be indifferent to the goal it seemingly serves. Inefficiency is especially rejected by ENTJ's, and repetition of error causes them to become impatient. For the ENTJ, there must always be a reason for doing anything, and people's feelings usually are not sufficient reason. When in charge of an organization, ENTJ's more than any other type desire (and generally have the ability) to visualize where the organization is going and seem able to communicate that vision to others. They are the natural organization builders, and they cannot not lead. They find themselves in command and sometimes are mystified as to how this happened. As administrators, ENTJ's organize their units into a smooth functioning system, planning in advance, keeping both short-term and long-range objectives well in mind. They seek and can see efficiency and effectiveness in personnel. They prefer decisions to be based on impersonal data, want to work from well thought-out plans, and like to use engineered operations-and they prefer that others follow suit. ENTJ's will support the policy of the organization and will expect others to do so. 
ENTJ's will usually rise to positions of responsibility and enjoy being executives. They are tireless in their devotion to their jobs and can easily block out other areas of life for the sake of work. They will be able to reduce inefficiency, ineffectiveness, and aimless confusion, being willing to dismiss employees who perpetuate such behaviors. ENTJ's tend to work in organizational structures of some sort, tend to be in charge administratively, and rise to top levels of responsibility, whether in the military, business, education, or government. 
</careerdetail>
				<home>ENTJ's take charge of the home. When an ENTJ is present, there will be little doubt as to who is in command. Because their work is so important to them, however, they can become increasingly absent, especially if male. Male or female, ENTJ's expect a great deal of their mates, who need to possess a strong personality of their own, a well-developed autonomy, many and varied interests, and a healthy self-esteem. A career wife, however, may not be appealing to an ENTJ male, who is apt to view his home and family as a part of his professional background, a resource, and adjunct to his own career development. 
As a parent, an ENTJ will be thoroughly in charge, and the children will know what is expected of them and will be expected to obey. When this does not occur, an ENTJ parent is not apt to make a scene; rather, there is more likely to be a low-key, firm issuance of reprimand and a taking-for-granted of immediate obedience. While both mating and parenting are roles of importance to the ENTJ's, they are to some degree preempted by the ENTJ's strong career interest. The romantic dream and the quest for the ideal mate is usually not a characteristic of this type. ENTJ's generally do, however, expect a home to be attractive, well-ordered, with meals served punctually and maintenance accomplished on schedule-all these in the service of the larger goal of creating a family system where children can be reared to be productive and healthy and establishing a devoted, harmonious relationship between man and woman. An ENTJ male might expect his mate to be active in civic and community affairs, to be socially sophisticated, and as well educated as he. The ENTJ female may find it difficult to select a mate who is not overwhelmed by her strong personality and will. 
</home>
				<midlife>At midlife the ENTJ's tendency to be somewhat unaware of the feelings of others, including those close, may be an area that could be given attention. But perhaps the most important midlife task of the ENTJ is to begin to allocate time and energy to pursuits which are not work-connected and to begin to develop a larger repertoire of play skills. Putting off vacations, travel, hobbies, and family should be avoided. </midlife>
				<mates>The ENTJ is a natural "fieldmarshal," that is, he's itching to get his hands on several "armies" so that he can marshal his forces and conduct the "war" as it should be conducted. If our ENTJ is in charge of any kind of enterprise, however small, his temperament dictates that he run it as he would his armies-with an eye to long-term strategies and their derivative tactics, logistics, and consequences. In startling contrast to this, the fieldmarshal is enamored by the "flower child," the bucolic artist ISFP, tranquilly ensconced next to Walden pond! Perhaps the ENTJ wishes a spouse who will share with him or her the quiet of the forest and field far from the madding crowd, thus separating home from work by a great, insulating distance. 
The ENTJ is attracted also to his opposite in the Appolonian camp: the monastic and questing INFP. What in the saintly or knightly (St. Joan of Arc, Sir Galahad) INFP calls the ENTJ fieldmarshal? First note the outward similarity of the INFP and the ISFP. Perhaps it is this, the underlying missionary outlook of the INFP. In a sense, both INFP and ISFP have great missionary zeal, the former enlisting the spouse in the quest, the latter in the tranquil respite of nature? 
</mates>
				<strengths>•	Genuinely interested in people's ideas and thoughts 
•	Enthusiastic and energetic 
•	Take their commitments very seriously 
•	Fair-minded and interested in doing the Right Thing 
•	Very good with money 
•	Extremely direct and straightforward 
•	Verbally fluent 
•	Enhance and encourage knowledge and self-growth in all aspects of life 
•	Able to leave relationships without looking back 
•	Able to turn conflict situations into positive lessons 
•	Able to take constructive criticism well 
•	Extremely high standards and expectations (both a strength and a weakness) 
•	Usually have strong affections and sentimental streaks 
•	Able to dole out discipline 
</strengths>
				<weakness>•	Their enthusiasm for verbal debates can make them appear argumentative 
•	Tendency to be challenging and confrontational 
•	Tend to get involved in "win-lose" conversations 
•	Tendency to have difficulty listening to others 
•	Tendency to be critical of opinions and attitudes which don't match their own 
•	Extremely high standards and expectations (both a strength and a weakness) 
•	Not naturally in tune with people's feelings and reactions 
•	May have difficulty expressing love and affection, sometimes seeming awkward or inappropriate 
•	Can be overpowering and intimidating to others 
•	Tendency to want to always be in charge, rather than sharing responsibilities 
•	Can be very harsh and intolerant about messiness or inefficiency 
•	Tendency to be controlling 
•	May be slow to give praise or to realize another's need for praise 
•	If unhappy or underdeveloped, they may be very impersonal, dictatorial, or abrasive 
•	Tendency to make hasty decisions 
•	Make explode with terrible tempers when under extreme stress 
</weakness>	
			</entj>
	
	
	
	
	
	
		<entp>
				<title>ENTP - The "Originator"</title>
				<overview>ENTPs are logical, innovative, curious and downright inventive. They see possibilities for improvement everywhere and possess the ability to understand complex concepts. ENTPs are introspective and carefree nonconformists. They often neglect the more common areas of life while pursuing new solutions. ENTPs can be good conversationalists and exciting company. </overview>
				<temper>NTs are introspective, logical and on a constant quest for knowledge. They are practical and unsentimental in their approach to problem solving. The actions of an NT are precise and follow a systematic course. Abstract, theoretical and technically adept, NTs are naturally inventive. They can also be described as being analytical, intellectual, inquisitive, independent and complex.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 3%
Male: 4.5%
Female: 1.5% 
</population>
				<people>
				Real ENTP People 
•	Alexander the Great - king, military commander
•	Alfred Hitchcock - filmmaker (The Birds)
•	Celine Dion - singer
•	David Spade - actor, comedian
•	George Carlin - comedian, actor, author
•	James A. Garfield - American President
•	John Adams - American President
•	John Candy - comedian, actor
•	Julia Child - chef, author, TV personality
•	Lewis Carroll - author (Alice in Wonderland)
•	Marilyn Vos Savant - author, lecturer, playwright
•	Matthew Perry - actor (Friends)
 	•	Nikola Tesla - inventor, physicist, engineer
•	Richard Feynman - physicist
•	Rodney Dangerfield - comedian, actor
•	Rutherford B. Hayes - American President
•	Sir Walter Raleigh - writer, poet, explorer
•	Suzanne Pleshette - actress
•	Theodore "Teddy" Roosevelt - American President
•	Thomas Edison - inventor
•	Tom Hanks - actor
•	Valerie Harper - actress
•	Walt Disney - filmmaker, entrepreneur
•	Weird Al Yankovic - musician (satire/parody)

Fictional ENTPs (Characters) 
•	Bugs Bunny - Looney Tunes
•	Cosmo Kramer - Seinfeld
•	Dr. Emmett 'Doc' Brown - Back to the Future
•	Ed - Cowboy Bebop
•	Mercutio - Romeo and Juliet
 	•	Polly Prince - Along Came Polly
•	Q - James Bond
•	Q - Star Trek: The Next Generation
•	Shirley Feeney - Laverne & Shirley
•	Wile E. Coyote - Road Runner (Looney Tunes)

				</people>
				<career>
				ENTPs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Originator/Intellectual personality. 
•	Actor
•	Artist
•	Consultant
•	Computer Programmer
•	Comedian
•	Computer Analyst
•	Designer
•	Engineer
•	Entrepreneur
•	Inventor
•	Journalist	 	•	Lawyer/Attorney
•	Musician
•	Marketer
•	Psychologist
•	Psychiatrist
•	Politician
•	Photographer
•	Systems Analyst 
•	Sales Representative
•	Scientist
•	Writer

				</career>
				<brief>ENTPs are known for their quest of the novel and complex. They have faith in their ability to improvise and to overcome any challenges that they face. They are highly independent, and value adaptability and innovation. They may be several steps ahead of others in encouraging and valuing change. They hate uninspired routine and resist hierarchical and bureaucratic structures that are not functional. They need freedom for action. </brief>
				<living>ENTPs are lively children who question established truths and norms, dream and scheme, and develop unusual ways of doing traditional childhood things. The ENTP child is oriented toward doing the unique, which may mean taking risks and outwitting parental, school, and societal authority. They enjoy creating projects and following interests that are unusual and different.
ENTP children enjoy inventing new toys, dances, and languages. Because they are outgoing in their personality style, they often engage other children in their projects and assign them particular roles to play. ENTPs rarely accept things just as they are. They like to test or explore to see new meanings and relationships. When things do not go as they want, they use their ingenuity and cleverness to bring people and situations around to their point of view. 
As young adults, when ENTPs choose a career for themselves, they tend to set flexible goals that allow them to incorporate new information and accommodate to new circumstances when they come along. It is hard for ENTPs not to be able to explore the road not taken. Their byword is keep your options open. Sometimes this flexibility can look like indecision to outsiders.
As adults, ENTPs take advantage of opportunities. Because of their ability to see relationships and connections between seemingly unrelated things, they are able to realize the potential in many things. When they see and opportunity that others have missed, they set action-oriented strategies that allow them the greatest flexibility to achieve the results they want. The worst job for them is working for someone who demands considerable rule following or tries too often to tell or order, rather than make suggestions to the ENTP. Throughout their careers, ENTPs want their work to be enjoyable, with interesting possibilities for applications. Additionally, having their work widely acclaimed and accepted as a unique contribution would be highly gratifying for ENTPs. They also weave in vacations whenever possible and want a flexible work schedule.
</living>
				<learning>Learning and Working
ENTPs are relentless learners. When the subject matter interests them, they are able to find meaning in whatever they are studying. Knowledge is important to them, but they may not feel the need to show this to their teachers and therefore may be somewhat lackadaisical about assignments and tests. 
ENTPs use their enthusiasm and energy to get others involved in their learning. They learn through give-and-take discussions and by questioning and challenging others. They are quick, verbal, and logical, preferring to use their skills in interactions with others. ENTPs look at the logical foundations in others' thinking and build on them to develop their own conceptual systems. They want to be taught concepts rather then facts. Models are important to them. They typically absorb their teacher's material and present it in a framework that ties all of the elements together.
They like to challenge their teachers and classmates and enjoy competitive learning tasks through which they can show their conceptual versatility. They may also enjoy independent study in which they can pursue and area of interest.
ENTPs contribute and innovative, versatile, and enterprising approach to work. They view limitations as challenges to be overcome and look for new ways to do things. They need to find a niche for themselves in order to be free to maneuver. They prefer the start-up phase of a project rather than the followthrough or maintenance phase. Once the project is designed, they prefer to turn it over to someone else. They take initiative and inspire others toward greater accomplishments and challenges. 
</learning>
				<working>ENTPs usually find work that involves an analytical, entrepreneurial, and creative focus. They tend to tolerate ambiguity well. They want to be in situations in which they can take intellectual risks and meet challenges. To perform in their best fashion, they prefer flexibility and versatility. While they like status and titles, they ultimately want to be judged on their innovative accomplishments. They take advantage of changing circumstances and work those circumstances into their plans. As a result, they function effectively in chaotic times.
Some occupations seem to be more appealing to ENTPs: actor, chemical engineer, computer analyst, credit investigator, journalist, marketeer, photographer, psychiatrist, public relations worker, sales agent, and other occupations that allow them to be innovative.
</working>
				<leading>ENTP's wish to exercise their ingenuity in the world of people and things. Found in about five out of every hundred people, ENTP's extravert intuition; thus they deal imaginatively with social relationships as well as physical and mechanical relations. They are very alert to what is apt to occur next, and always sensitive to possibilities. 
ENTP's are good at analysis, especially functional analysis, and have both a tolerance for and enjoyment of the complex. Usually enthusiastic, ENTP's are apt to express interest in everything, and thus are a source of inspiration to others, who find themselves caught up by the ENTP's enthusiasm. This type is delighted over many things and so is easy to please, often showing the effervescence of their NF counterpart, the ENFP. The ENTP is the most reluctant of all the types to do things in a particular manner just because that is the way things always have been done. They characteristically have an eye out for a better way, always on the lookout for new projects, new activities, new procedures. 
ENTP's are confident in the value of their pursuits and display a charming capacity to ignore the standard, the traditional, and the authoritative. As a result of this open attitude, they often bring a fresh, new approach to their work and their lives. The ENTP is a keen judge of the pragmatics of both the social and the mechanical, and may become expert at directing relationships between means and ends. 
Where the introverted NTP sees design as an end in itself, the extraverted NTP sees design as a means; the end is the invention that works, the prototype that is replicable. Ideas are valuable when and only when they make possible actions and objects. "It can't be done" is a challenge to an ENTP and elicits a reaction of "I can do it." They are not, however, the movers of mountains as are the INTJ's. Rather, the faith of the ENTP's is in their ability to improvise something, and they display an unusual talent for rising to the expediency of a situation. Superficially, ENTP's resemble ESTP's in their derringdo. But the focus of the ENTP is on the competency and the sense of power this gives, rather than on the feeling of freedom of action experienced by the ESTP. 
ENTP's can be fascinating conversationalists, able as they are to follow the complex verbalizations of others. They may deliberately employ debate tactics to the disadvantage of their opponents, even when the "opponents" are close associates and valued friends. ENTP's are the most able of all types to maintain a one-up position with others. They value adaptability and innovation and thus respond quickly and adeptly to another's shifting position. They may even be several jumps ahead. The ENTP, talkative and motivating, is often the life of an enterprise. The ENTP can be an entrepreneur and cleverly makes do with whatever or whoever is at hand, counting on ingenuity to solve problems as they arise, rather than carefully generating a detailed blueprint in advance. A rough draft is all that an ENTP needs to feel confident and ready to proceed into action, counting on the ability to improvise as a situation develops. Because of this tendency to depend on ingenuity and improvision, they may neglect very necessary preparation at times. After repeated failures in situations where improvising has met with defeat, the ENTP may develop ways of avoiding such situations as a substitute to thorough preparation. 
</leading>
				<loving>For the ENTP, falling in love occurs when they feel that there is a good fit with the other person. Often within the first meeting, ENTPs will know whether the relationship has any real potential. ENTPs may find it difficult to commit to anyone until the right person comes along. During this period, ENTPs explore the closeness until they can be certain that they have looked at all of the possibilities. Because of this, they are not likely to settle down early. When they do become involved in a relationship, they generally want to maintain as much independence and freedom as their loved one can tolerate. Their mates may need to have high self-esteem and to be independent themselves in order to accept the ENTP need for freedom and novelty.
For ENTPs, falling out of love, which may not always occur, results when their vision of the relationship does not square with reality. Sometimes they will select someone who offers stability and comfort and ENTPs later will become bored with the stability. When scorned, ENTPs use their powerful and broadreaching analysis to explain the reasons why the relationship was not good in the first place; additionally, they may become competitive with their former partner and work hard to win. ENTPs do not like to lose at anything they undertake.
</loving>
				<careerdetail>ENTP's can succeed in a variety of occupations, as long as the job does not involve too much humdrum routine. At this point, they become restless. If a project in which they are engaged is no longer challenging, they tend to lose interest in that project and fail to follow through-often to the discomfort of colleagues. 
Seldom are ENTP's conformists. ENTP's enjoy outwitting the system and use rules and regulations within the system to win the game-whatever it may be. They understand well the politics of institutions and deal with these realities very well, always aiming to understand the people within the system rather than to judge them. ENTP's are good at innovative projects and can administer them well if dull routine is not involved. They usually are outstanding teachers, continuously devising new participative ways to make learning exciting for the students. As an employee, an ENTP may work against the system just for the joy of being one-up. For ENTP's, to be taken-in, to be manipulated by another, is humiliating; this offends their joy in being masters of the art of one-upmanship. ENTP's are the natural engineers of human relationships and human systems. Their good humor and optimistic outlook tend to be contagious, and people seek out their company. 
</careerdetail>
				<home>As mates, ENTP's tend to create a lively living environment. They are gregarious, laugh easily and often, and are typically in good humor. Orderliness in the routines of daily living is not apt to inspire them; they usually solve this problem by mobilizing those around them. Tom Sawyer illustrated this talent when he solved the problem of getting Aunt Polly's fence whitewashed. Life with ENTP's is likely to be a daring adventure; they can lead families to physical and economic dangers. ENTP's improvise to remain unaware that they do not have the necessary knowledge of the situation to ward off such dangers. 
If the mate of an ENTP is not competitive, he or she is likely to find the one-up/one-down transactions somewhat wearing. If the mate is competitive, the result might be conflict. Although usually good providers of economic necessities, ENTP's at times engage in brinkmanship with their careers, placing them in jeopardy and behaving as if unaware of the consequences; they may thus offer unnecessary challenges to those who have power over their professional success. When challenges elicit negative responses from superiors, ENTP's are apt to react with delight at having an opportunity to improvise a solution to the crisis and, more often than not, they succeed in doing so. 
ENTP's are likely to have all sorts of hobbies and to be experts in unexpected areas, but they are not apt to share these hobbies with their mates or children in the sense of teaching them. In fact, ENTP's may be very inconsistent in the attention given to offspring. Usually, it is feast or famine. ENTP's have a lively circle of friends and are interested in their ideas and activities. They are usually easy-going, seldom critical or nagging. At their worst, they can show undependable, fickle characteristics and may be rather easily discouraged. 
</home>
				<midlife>At midlife ENTP's can allow their tendency to experiment recklessly to get out of hand and may destroy or discard the work of half a lifetime, both in personal relationships and in careers. Energy spent in sorting out priorities and values may be a good investment at this time. Developing an increased awareness of emotional reactions and expanding the intensity and range of these through self-development work may be something ENTP's might want to consider at midlife. An increased repertoire of introverted-type activities; for example, gardening, painting, or reading may be a source of pleasure to ENTP's. </midlife>
				<mates>The inventive ENTP finds in the ISFJ a neat complementarily for his enterprise, for in the ISFJ he finds the supreme conservator. The conservator, broadly conceived, is morally bound to ensure the material and legal welfare of his or her charge. The inventor, also broadly conceived, is bent on replacing whatever tools, operation, or enterprise now exists with a better one. Out to exercise his ingenuity in bettering things, the ENTP is of necessity iconoclastic and tends to be so seen. So he can get into a bit of trouble with the elders, who usually are not all that pleased to see their tried-and-true tools, operations, and enterprises blithely set aside for the ENTP's better mousetrap. The ISFJ, mated to this inventive rascal, takes on the task of squaring things with the establishment. 
The ENTP also may be attracted to his opposite on the N side: he approaches the INFJ. But the INFJ is humorously and preposterously different from the seemingly similar ISFJ. In the INFJ lies the soul of the "author"-the meaning-giver, the mystic, the oracle. Perhaps the INFJ is a conservator of the soul, a sort of messiah. At any rate, there is something about the "author" (very broadly conceived) which the ENTP covets. Prometheus had to pay dearly for giving fire to man. The Promethian ENTP may figure that, though his INFJ mate may not rescue his body from the vultures, at least the INFJ might rescue his soul from Hell.
</mates>
				<strengths>•	Enthusiastic, upbeat, and popular 
•	Can be very charming 
•	Excellent communication skills 
•	Extremely interested in self-improvement and growth in their relationships 
•	Laid-back and flexible, usually easy to get along with 
•	Big idea-people, always working on a grand scheme or idea 
•	Usually good at making money, although not so good at managing it 
•	Take their commitments and relationships very seriously 
•	Able to move on with their lives after leaving a relationship 
</strengths>
				<weakness>•	Always excited by anything new, they may change partners frequently 
•	Tendency to not follow through on their plans and ideas 
•	Their love of debate may cause them to provoke arguments 
•	Big risk-takers and big spenders, not usually good at managing money 
•	Although they take their commitments seriously, they tend to abandon their relationships which no longer offer opportunity for growth 
</weakness>	
			</entp>
	
	
	
	
	
		<esfj>
				<title>ESFJ - The "Supporter"</title>
				<overview>ESFJs are social butterflies that value relationships, supporting and nurturing others. Never one to shy away from social events, they are often the host. They are great encouragers of teamwork. ESFJs are responsible, dutiful, observe traditions and follow rules. ESFJs have a deep concern for others and often end up as caretakers. They are sensitive to criticism and have a need to be appreciated for the good they do for others. ESFJs are understanding, generous, have a quick wit and a knack for composition and beautification. </overview>
				<temper>SJs are observant, stable and motivated by a need to maintain security. They are realistic, routinized administrators requiring tasks be completed correctly and that people behave appropriately. SJs make thorough examinations to ensure everything is done according to plan. They make sure no more and no less credit is given than due. When a need arises, they are quick to provide a solution, provided that the need is justified. SJs are not driven by impulse, but rather by concrete fact. By virtue of their reliable, diligent, industrious, persevering nature, they make excellent leaders.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 10%
Male: 6%
Female: 14% 
</population>
				<people>
				Real ESFJ People 
•	Danny Glover - actor
•	Desi Arnaz - actor, comedian, musician
•	Dixie Carter - actress
•	Don Knotts - comedian
•	Elvis Stojko - Canadian figure skater
•	Jack Benny - comedian, actor
•	John Connally - politician
 	•	Mary Tyler Moore - actress, comedian
•	Nancy Kerrigan - Olympic figure skater
•	Sally Field - actress
•	Sally Struthers - actress
•	Steve Spurrier - football player
•	Terry Bradshaw - football player
•	William McKinley - American President


Fictional ESFJs (Characters) 
•	Donald Duck - Disney cartoon character
•	George Babbitt - Babbit (Sinclair Lewis)
•	Hoss Cartwright - Bonanza
•	Leonard "Bones" McCoy - Star Trek
 	•	Monica Gellar - Friends
•	Nurse Haleh Adams - ER
•	Rabbit - Winnie the Pooh


				</people>
				<career>
				ESFJs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Supporter/Protector personality. 
•	Accountant
•	Administrator
•	Administrative Assistant
•	Bookkeeper
•	Counselor
•	Child Care
•	Church Worker
•	Dental Assistant
•	Family Doctor
•	Human Resources
•	Homemaker	 	•	Marketer
•	Nurse
•	Office Manager
•	Organization Leader
•	Researcher
•	Radiological Technologist
•	Receptionist
•	Speech Pathologist
•	Social Worker
•	Trainer
•	Teacher

				</career>
				<brief>ESFJs are helpful people who place a high value on harmony. Paying close attention to people's needs and wants, they work well with others to complete tasks in a timely and accurate way. ESFJs follow through on their commitments. They like closure and prefer structured, organized situations in which warmth and compassion are shown. They contribute to others by anticipating their day-to-day concerns and handling them with warmth and efficiency. ESFJs are at their best in organizing people to get a job done.</brief>
				<living>ESFJ children want life to be uncomplicated, secure, harmonious and structured. They are usually responsible, reliable, and cooperative. They thrive in situations in which there is consistency and personal attention. They enjoy the acceptance of others and will work hard to gain that acceptance. ESFJ children are concerned about doing the right things and pleasing their elders.
ESFJs follow the rules and tend to accept them as fair and reasonable. They admire people and teachers who are warm, friendly, and concerned. They are concerned about the feelings of others and like to help out when possible. They begin early to assume responsibility for the welfare of others. They believe it is necessary to give as well as to receive and will often volunteer their time and talents in service organizations.
ESFJs radiate warmth and fellowship, and generally fit in well with their classmates. They value the traditional things that teenagers do and may be involved in various clubs and teams. Their friends often turn to them because of their listening ear and helpful nature.
Often the lives of ESFJs follow a traditional pattern. In adult life, ESFJs take their parent, spouse, employee, or community volunteer roles seriously and are committed to them. They are sensitive to the needs to those around them, sometimes more attuned to others' needs than their own. They gain the respect of others because of their helpfulness, pleasantness, and ability to get things done. They carry out their commitments and are often in charge of events. Mature ESFJs often structure both their work and personal lives so that they can meet the needs of others.
</living>
				<learning>ESFJs learn best in structured situations where they know what they can expect. They like to schedule their learning projects so that they can plan ahead to complete their lessons. They become uncomfortable with continuous interruptions and changes when they are trying to finish what they have started. Even more importantly, however, they want to like the person who teaches them. The teacher-student relationship is helpful to them in doing their best. When there is disharmony in the classroom, it interrupts their learning process. When their work is criticised, even constructively, ESFJs may feel demoralized until they get it right and the teacher acknowledges this. Because they tend to personalize the feedback of their teachers, it is important for them to know teachers' expectations so that they can work to meet them. 
Learning tends to be a personal experience for ESFJs. This attitue, combined with their ability to follow through and meet deadlines, results in a conscientious and effective student. ESFJs often enjoy studies about people and their well-being, and are usually less interested in theoretical and abstract subject matters. They like active learning activities such as field trips, experiments and group projects that get them personally involved with others.
</learning>
				<working>At work, ESFJs contribute their ability to cooperate with others and to complete tasks in a timely and accurate way. They respect rules and authority, and handle daily operations efficiently. They tend to be well informed and up-to-date on organizational actions that matter to people. They do what they can to make sure that personal relationships are running smoothly. Because they pay close attention to people's needs and wants, they are often involved in work activities that meet people's practical, day-to-day desires.
ESFJs prefer occupations that allow them to provide direct and personal, yet practical, help to others. Occupations that call for organization and goal direction appeal to them. They are especially careful not to waste time or resources; to do so would go against their nature.
Some occupations are particularly appealing to ESFJs: childcare worker, dental assistant, elementary school teacher, home economist, nurse, office manager, radiological technologist, receptionist and secretary, religious educator, speech pathologist, and other occupations that allow them to help others and serve their values directly.
</working>
				<leading>ESFJs, the most sociable of all types, are energized by interactions with people, tending to idealize whatever or whoever they admire. Harmony is a key to this type, which is represented in about 13 percent of the general population. 
ESFJs are the great nurturers of established institutions such as the home, the school, the church, and civic groups. Wherever they go, they promote harmony and harmonious relationships. They are outstanding hosts or hostesses, able to call people by name, usually after one introduction. At a social gathering they can be observed attending to the needs of others, trying to insure that all are comfortable and involved. 
Social ties matter to the ESFJs, and their conversations often drift to nostalgic recounting of past memories. Traditions are developed, supported, and carefully observed by the ESFJ. 
ESFJs are hurt by indifference and need to be appreciated both for themselves and for the abundance, typically in the form of services, they give to others. They are conscious of appearances and take the opinions of others regarding social standards very seriously. Values in an ESFJ may take the form of shoulds and should nots and may be freely expressed. Conscientious and orderly, ESFJs may become restless when isolated from people. 
</leading>
				<loving>For the ESFJ, love means warmth and commitment. When ESFJs first fall in love, they show this warmth and concern for their partner in many tangible ways. They will send cards, notes, flowers, special gifts, and other mementos of their affection. If the partner casually mentions a desire for a specific thing, they will try to find just that thing. Once committed in a relationship, ESFJs tend to stay with it even when there is inconvenience to them and perhaps longer than may be healthy. They are able to bring out the best in their partners, even though it may mean putting their own needs second.
Because ESFJs are caring individuals, they expect to give and receive in their relationships. Because others may not be as thoughtful as the ESFJ, it is a possible source of disappointment to them if they expect the same awareness and caring on the part of the partner. Being practical and realistic, they may not always like effusive shows of affection and prefer moderation instead. ESFJs may be more loyal to the relationship or to the institution of marriage than to the person. ESFJs may take the end of the relationship as a personal failure.
ESFJs, when scorned, hurt all over and may need to take time to get over the relationship before pursuing a new one. They may too easily and incorrectly blame themselves for the unfavourable outcome and recall instances when perhaps they were not as giving as they might have been. However, ESFJs' standards for giving in a relationship are likely to be above those of some other types. At their worst when scorned, ESFJs can become spiteful and critical of the partner. Because ESFJs are keenly sensitive to others and are tuned in to emotional needs, they really know how to hurt a person in the rare instances when they choose to do so.
</loving>
				<careerdetail>Career selection by ESFJs may lean toward service occupations. They have such outgoing personalities that they are outstanding at selling, being an invariable winner in sales contests. They are apt to have seniority in any sales group within an organization. Observation of ESFJs at work in a sales transaction will demonstrate how this type personalizes the sale: The customer is not buying the product; he or she is buying personally from the ESFJ. This same characteristic causes ESFJs to be good in teaching, preaching, supervision, administration, coaching, and, in general, people to people jobs. They seldom become a source of irritation to their superiors, for they respect and obey the rules and regulations, are duty-and service-oriented. They are loyal to their bosses. ESFJs are likely to be aware of and enjoy discussing events and problems in the lives of their colleagues; but when conversations turn to abstractions of philosophy or science, the ESFJ may become restive. Analysis of the complex-for example, an attempt to find an explanation of events through an analysis of principles-does not excite their interest, as it does the NTs'. </careerdetail>
				<home>ESFJ mates have a set of values which contain clear should and should-nots, and they expect their family to abide by these. They are conscientious about home responsibilities, are orderly about the home, and prefer that other occupants be the same. They enjoy socializing and entertaining. ESFJs want family decisions settled efficiently and quickly and want family living routinized, scheduled, and correctly executed. They do not rebel against routine operations, are devoted to the traditional values of home and hearth, respect their marriage vows, and are the most sympathetic of all types. They tend to be dependent on their mates and may marry to insure that they have a proper place in the social strata. They enjoy the rituals connected with serving of good food and beverages, thrive on festive occasions, respect and accumulate a goodly store of material possessions. They take their role in the community seriously and are sensitive to the acknowledged, official decision-makers and identify with them. They are aware of status, and often depend on higher authority as the source of opinions and attitudes. 
ESFJs wear their hearts on their sleeves and are outgoing in their emotional reactions. They need to be needed, loved, and appreciated and may spend much energy reassuring themselves that this is the case. 
ESFJs usually respect and revere their parents, and as children were responsive and obedient pupils. They seem able to express the right feeling for a given situation. They are soft hearted, sentimental, and usually observe with gusto and a flourish birthdays, anniversaries, and the like, making of the event a delightful, important occasion. At the same time, however, ESFJs can cause others undue tension by expressing anticipations of gloom and doom, exhibiting a bent toward the pessimistic that can be contagious. They need to control their fears that the worst is sure to happen and suppress their tendency toward crepe-hanging and anticipating disasters. 
The children of an ESFJ are seen as an extension of the family, and all they do reflects on the ESFJ. If things do not go well, the ESFJ may be critical, even carping toward his or her mate and children. This type may marry alcoholics or others who are particularly needy. If a female ESFJ is married to a mate who is not a good provider, she can become nagging and brood over a comparison of her possessions and status with that of others. ESFJs, male or female, live in terms of people and things rather than in terms of ideas and principles. They enjoy the process of decision-making, particularly when focus is on the usefulness of things and people. 
</home>
				<midlife>At midlife ESFJs may want to get involved in activities that spark their imagination and creativity, for example, work with art media. They should find it useful to sort out priorities in their values and force themselves to give more attention to their own wishes and needs. They could begin to practice the art of being kind to oneself and each day attempt to do at least one self-indulgent deed. Travel should be something ESFJs particularly enjoy; at midlife they should allocate time to this activity. Also, the reading of "serious" technical books in a professional field might interest and expand the horizons of ESFJs at this time of life. Planning for retirement so that a sufficient number of interpersonal activities are available is vital for the ESFJ, who would very quickly become bored and restless if cut off from contact with a variety of people. </midlife>
				<mates>There is a mutual attraction of ESFJ and INTP. The ESFJ, wanting to serve as an anchorage for the INTP's flights to the higher levels of abstraction, finds in the ISTP an even more likely target for anchorage. The ISTP's flights are often literal, not figurative: He really does fly. Look in the cockpit of almost any aircraft and you'll find an ISTP. Of course, most ISTPs do not fly in the literal sense; but the hankering for adventure and exploration symbolized by flight is there, and it is this, the hankering, that draws the ESFJ like a moth to a flame. How does this serve the giving, caring, comforting nature of ESFJ? Why, when the adventurer returns, of course; the giver of comfort is there to provide rest and recreation.</mates>
				<strengths>•	Put forth a lot of effort to fulfill their duties and obligations 
•	Warm, friendly and affirming by nature 
•	Service-oriented, they want to please others 
•	Take their commitments very seriously, and seek lifelong relationships 
•	Responsible and practical, they can be counted to take care of day-to-day necessities 
•	Generally upbeat and popular, people are drawn towards them 
•	Generally very good money managers 
•	Traditionally minded and family-oriented, they will make family celebrations and traditions special events 
</strengths>
				<weakness>•	Generally uncomfortable with change, and moving into new territories 
•	Extreme dislike of conflict and criticism 
•	Need a lot of positive affirmation to feel good about themselves 
•	May be overly status-conscious, and interested in how others see them 
•	Have very difficult time accepting the end of a relationship, and are likely to take the blame for the failure onto their own shoulders 
•	Have difficulty accepting negative things about people close to them 
•	Don't pay enough attention to their own needs, and may be self-sacrificing 
•	May tend to use guilt manipulation as a way to get what they want 
</weakness>	
			</esfj>
			
			
			<esfp>
				<title>ESFP - The "Entertainer"</title>
				<overview>ESFPs are cooperative, "here and now" people-persons that enjoy excitement and love new adventures. Because of their highly social nature, they are especially lively when they are the center of attention and hate being alone. ESFPs have a practical side that allows them to finish work efficiently and are often good problem solvers. </overview>
				<temper>SPs are observant, experiential and primarily driven by sensation. They are flexible, aesthetically-aware, "here and now" people that, with hardly a moment's notice, will go where their senses lead. SPs naturally make an effort (with a realistic approach) not to miss an opportunity that may prove to be thrilling, pleasing or otherwise valuable. SPs are are laid back, open-minded and love to feel alive. They have a tendency toward athletics and anything that involves creating or crafting.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 9.5%
Male: 8%
Female: 11% 
</population>
				<people>
				Real ESFP People 
•	Arsenio Hall - comedian
•	Bill Clinton - American President, politician
•	Bob Hope - actor
•	Cindy Gliebe - American vegan chef
•	Earvin "Magic" Johnson - basketball player
•	Elizabeth Taylor - actress
•	Elvis Presley - singer/musician, actor
•	Eva Gabor - actress
•	Gracie Allen - comedian
•	John Goodman - actor
 	•	Kathy Lee Gifford - actress, singer
•	Kyle Petty - NASCAR driver
•	Marilyn Monroe - actor, singer, model
•	Mary Lou Retton - gymnast
•	Pablo Picasso - Spanish painter, sculptor
•	Peter Kay - writer, actor, comedian
•	Ronald Reagan - American President, actor
•	Saint Mark - apostle, evangelist
•	Willard Scott - media personality


Fictional ESFPs (Characters) 
•	Clementine Kruczynski - Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless Mind
•	Cody - Step by Step
•	Frado - Godfather
•	Homer Simpson - The Simpsons
•	Kelly Bundy - Married with Children
 	•	Mrs. Pumphrey - All Creatures Great and Small
•	Peggy Bundy - Married with Children
•	Peter Griffin - Family Guy
•	Tim Taylor - Home Improvement


				</people>
				<career>
				ESFPs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Entertainer/Creator personality. 
•	Actor
•	Artist
•	Administrative Assistant
•	Coach
•	Comedian
•	Church Worker
•	Child Care
•	Entrepreneur
•	Fashion Designer
•	Human Resources
•	Interior Decorator
•	Lawyer/Attorney
•	Musician	 	•	Marketer
•	Painter
•	Psychologist/Counselor
•	Photographer
•	Recreation Worker
•	Receptionist
•	Systems Analyst 
•	Supervisor
•	Sales Represenative
•	Social Worker
•	Scientist
•	Trainer
•	Technical Specialist

				</career>
				<brief>ESFPs are friendly, outgoing, fun loving and naturally drawn to people. They are quite enthusiastic and exuberant, and are usually well liked by others. They are good at meeting people and helping them enjoy themselves. They are sympathetic toward people and generous with their time and money. At their best, they are able to realistically meet human and situational needs in a fun and lively way.</brief>
				<living>ESFP children are friendly, warm, active, and enthusiastic. They are very giving and concerned about others. They like to make others happy, believing that "it is better to give than to receive." Being on the receiving end may make them feel self-conscious. They tend to be good at comforting others, regardless of whether others are in need. ESFPs are aware of what is happening around them and notice much that escapes the eyes of others. They are tied into the present, particularly with people, they may sense what is happening with others before others know it. They may also noticewhat is going on in their environment and take delight in a spring flower, a bird's song, or a bright fabric, pointing these out in their enthusiastic way for others to enjoy. They are popular and gregarious, and are often busy in social activities with others. As teenagers, they are likely to be instigators of activities with their friends. It is difficult to catch them sitting still. They tend to be bright and sunny in disposition and enjoy laughing at themselves and others. It is hard for them to be "down," mainly because of the excitement of each upcoming event. 
As adults, ESFPs lead what might look like "a charmed existence,' even when things are not going well for them. They live with the idea that "the glass is half full" and seem to land on their feet, even when they are not sure how. They usually find a niche for themselves in any situation because of their spontaneity and flexibility. Their social skills may attract the eye of a boss. For ESFPs bring a liveliness to a groups to which they belong. Life is meant to be enjoyed and is not taken too seriously.
ESFPs often are able to interact with all ages, backgrounds, and types of people. Most individuals who connect with ESFPs feel that they are treated as equals by them, regardless of age or convention. They enjoy sharing their love of life with others, not just their mates and children. People around them benefit from this. 
In retirement, ESFPs continue their fun-filled, people-focused, actively-oriented life. They keep close friendships and continue to provide amusement to those who have been important to them in the past.
</living>
				<learning>ESFPs prefer learning through participating in groups where they can interact with others and do things, not just observe or listen about things. They want to get to know their teachers well. It is not that the teachers have to be nice, but they do need to care. ESFPs dislike and are upset by intellectual arguments and conflict. They need to experience the concept first before discussing it or receiving a didactically presented theory. Directions must be very concrete, simple and accurate. They are also plugged into the environment. Atmosphere, attitudes, physical setting --- all make a difference. If the encouragement they receive for their social life is more than the encouragement they receive for their academic life, they may err on the side of being too social. Most ESFPs learn actively and do not function as well when they must read quietly by themselves about matters that are theoretical. They find themselves easily drifting off while studying, and they are ultimately diverted by things more real to them.</learning>
				<working>ESFP like action and excitement, and are able to link together people and resources. Because they accept and deal with people as they are, they are able to understand what is necessary in order to motivate them to get jobs done. They prefer a work setting that is lively, action oriented, and harmonious. The atmosphere and overall attitude of the work setting means a great deal to them. They like adaptable people who are energetic, easygoing, and focused on the present realities. If something is not immediately useful or of intrinsic value, it may be quickly reflected by ESFPs. They notice what is going on with people and focus on these happenings intently. ESFPs are likely to adapt as the situation requires. ESFPs like occupations that allow them to be with people. They want to be direct and practical service to others and seek work that is self-fulfilling and rewarding. Being a resource to others is an important part of their work. Some occupations seem to be more attractive to ESFPs: childcare worker, clerical supervisor, coach, designer, factory supervisor, food service worker, receptionist, recreation worker, religious educator, respiratory therapist, and other occupations that allow them to be responsive to others.</working>
				<leading>The ESFP leadership style is one that promotes good will and team work. ESFPs are quickly adaptable and thus able to guide others in crisis situations, unless that crisis is one of disharmony among people. They are able to focus on immediate problems and using their ability to work with people. They are more relationship oriented but will work hard on the task part when the people part is going well.</leading>
				<loving>Love means enjoyment of one another. ESFPs want to share values with the loved one. They way people are treated is usually one value they care about. They may move in and out of relationships quickly when the situation feels uncomfortable. They are not likely to take man interpersonal risks since they fear rejection themselves. They are warm and become more generous and outgoing in the face of approval. They can become quite hampered by disapproval.
Even when a relationship ends, ESFPs tend to be very respectful of the former partner. They do not want to call undue attention to the breakup and thus move on rather quickly, surrounding themselves with their valued friends.
</loving>
				<careerdetail>ESFPs prefer active jobs and should not be given lonely, solitary assignments. Outstanding in public relations, they love working with people. Decisions are made with personal warmth, based on personal reference or reference to significant others. This type relies heavily on their personal experiences and generally show good common sense. 
The gregarious sociability and adaptability of ESFPs make them a source of warmth to others. They do not mind telephone or personal interruptions and are verbally facile in both situations. They can be counted on to have accurate data about the people around them, gaining these data through effortless and continuous observations. 
ESFPs are not deeply interested in scholastic pursuits, wanting knowledge only for immediate utility. They avoid science and engineering, gravitate toward business, and are adept at selling, particularly selling tangibles. They can be effective in education, especially elementary school teaching, and can enjoy nursing for its drama. They are good at working with people in crisis, a facility which often leads ESFPs into social work. They also enjoy entertaining people and are thus drawn to the performing arts, thriving on the excitement of being in the limelight. 
</careerdetail>
				<home>ESFPs make exciting, if somewhat unpredictable mates, which may give quieter type mates some anxiety and tension from living on the edge of adventure. The home of an ESFP is likely to be filled with people all having a good time. Problems will not be allowed to make their appearance. The ESFP accomplishes this by taking an attitude of "walking by the graveyard whistling," refusing to recognize doom and gloom. 
ESFPs can be generous to a fault. What is theirs is yours, and what is yours is yours still. They give assistance to one and all without expectation of a return, just as they love freely without expecting something in return. ESFPs seem to view life as an eternal cornucopia from which flows an endless supply of pleasures that require no effort on their part to insure. 
ESFPs' talent for enjoying life can make them more subject to temptations than are other types. They are inclined to be impulsive, and thus both male and female ESFPs are vulnerable to psychological seduction, if not physical seduction, with an ESFP giving in easily and agreeably to the demands of others. As a parent, the ESFP will be entertaining, a friend, and a source of fun and excitement. When there is sickness, or trouble, however, ESFPs may become impatient and may want to absent themselves. 
ESFPs' tolerance for anxiety is the lowest of all the types. Anxiety is avoided by ignoring the dark side of a situation as long as possible. They are inclined to be somewhat self-indulgent, but, rather than make an outward show of resistance or make waves, ESFPs will give apparent compliance-and then go their own way to what they enjoy. 
</home>
				<midlife>At midlife ESFPs might want to look to building deeper commitments to fewer people and begin setting stable, long-term goals. ESFPs may, by midlife, begin to feel that they are used as a source of fun to others, but are not cared for themselves. This can build resentments. They may want to work at building one or two deep relationships where they are able to show their fears, their sadness, and their anxieties about the future-and still find that they are accepted and loved. They may want to increase their enjoyment of solitude and their repertoire of solitary activities. Extending their reading in "serious" literature or technical works might be one way of doing this. </midlife>
				<mates>There is an affinity of the INTJ "scientist" for the ESFP exciting entertainer. This type of mating, however, is so infrequent as to be a mere academic interest (the INTJ is a mere 1 percent of the population and, furthermore, rarely comes in contact with ESFP). More frequently the ESFP is drawn to the ISTJ "trustor." Here is the entertaining ESFP, bursting with energy and hankering to put on a show of some kind. More than others the ESFP yearns for the bright lights, the party, the excitement of gatherings. In a sense, the ESFP is the life of the party. How many times have novelist and screenwriter told the story of "the showgirl and the banker" or "the playboy and the owner"? The ESFP wants to liven up this Rock of Gibraltar at the same time he or she wants to be settled down by this very stable and responsible person.</mates>
				<strengths>•	Enthusiastic and fun-loving, they make everything enjoyable 
•	Clever, witty, direct, and popular, people are drawn towards them 
•	Earthy and sensual 
•	Down to earth and practical, able to take care of daily needs 
•	Artistic and creative, they're likely to have attractive homes 
•	Flexible and diverse, they "go with the flow" extremely well 
•	They can leave bad relationships, although it's not easy 
•	Try to make the most of every moment 
•	Generous and warm-hearted 
</strengths>
				<weakness>•	May be frivolous and risky with money 
•	Tend to be materialistic 
•	Extreme dislike of criticism, likely to take things extremely personally 
•	Likely to ignore or escape conflict situations rather than face them 
•	Lifelong commitments may be a struggle for them - they take things one day at a time 
•	Don't pay enough attention to their own needs 
•	Tendency to neglect their health, or even abuse their bodies 
•	Always excited by something new, they may change partners frequently 
</weakness>	
			</esfp>
		

		
		
		<estj>
				<title>ESTJ - The "Overseer"</title>
				<overview>ESTJs are responsible, logical, norm-following hard workers. Their efforts are carried out in a practical, structured manner. ESTJs trust facts and experiences more than theories. They are decisive, loyal, tradition observing individuals. They enjoy being the person in charge and often make good supervisors. </overview>
				<temper>SJs are observant, stable and motivated by a need to maintain security. They are realistic, routinized administrators requiring tasks be completed correctly and that people behave appropriately. SJs make thorough examinations to ensure everything is done according to plan. They make sure no more and no less credit is given than due. When a need arises, they are quick to provide a solution, provided that the need is justified. SJs are not driven by impulse, but rather by concrete fact. By virtue of their reliable, diligent, industrious, persevering nature, they make excellent leaders.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 11%
Male: 13.5%
Female: 8.5% 
</population>
				<people>
				
Real ESTJ People 
•	Andrew Jackson - American President
•	Bette Davis - actress
•	Carrie Nation - advocate
•	Elliot Ness - prohibition agent
•	George W. Bush - American President
•	Grover Cleveland - American President
•	James Monroe - American President
 	•	John D. Rockefeller - industrialist, philanthropist
•	Lyndon B. Johnson - American President
•	Pat Summit - basketball coach
•	Rev. Billy Graham - evangelist, writer
•	Robert A. Taft - Governor of Ohio
•	Sam Walton - founder of Wal-Mart
•	William Henry Harrison - American President

Fictional ESTJs (Characters) 
•	Lucy van Pelt - Peanuts (Charlie Brown)
•	Mrs. Harbottle - All Creatures Great and Small
•	Mrs. Rachel Lynde - Anne of Green Gables	 	•	Princess Leia Organa - Star Wars
•	The Mayor - The Music Man
•	Tony Soprano - The Sopranos


				</people>
				<career>
				ESTJs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Overseer/Protector personality. 
•	Accountant
•	Auditor
•	Business Analyst 
•	Business Administrator
•	Banker
•	Computer Specialist
•	Detective
•	Engineer
•	Economist
•	Editor
•	Financial Officer
•	Government Worker
•	Insurance Agent
•	Judge
•	Librarian	 	•	Lecturer
•	Military Leader
•	Marketer
•	Manager
•	Nursing Administrator
•	Police
•	Researcher
•	Senior Manager
•	Sales Representative
•	Scientist
•	Technical Specialist
•	Teacher/Professor
•	Teacher
•	Underwriter
•	Writer

				</career>
				<brief>ESTJs are doers who roll up their sleeves, dig in, and proceed directly to get the job done. They use logic and analysis as guiding principles for their lives. They are quick to decide and set a plan of action. They marshall resources in an organized fashion, implement, and follow through. They like closure. They focus directly on tasks to accomplish and are able to anticipate the steps needed to complete an assignment. In doing so, they see what might go wrong and take the necessary preventive action. They monitor events continually and make sure that commitments, both their won and those of others, are honored and the job gets done. They are at their best in situations that have some structure to them and involve activity, not contemplation, and in which an end product is desired.</brief>
				<living>ESTJ children want life to be logical, practical, organized, and fair. They are often responsible, reliable, and obedient - if the rules make sense. They may be upset by a change in rules or routine, particularly if the rationale for the change is not given. They like others to be clear about their decisions. ESTJs learn early on how to use set formulas to make their own firm decisions.
ESTJ children like results-oriented activities and are often busy in some type of sporting or organized group, such as scouts. They want to learn how to do things correctly and may take lessons that help accomplish this. 
ESTJ teenagers may value the traditional things that teenagers do, such as team sports, band and class offices. They begin early to assume responsibility for themselves. They believe it is necessary to earn their keep and as teenagers they often have part-time jobs. Those jobs usually are for specific purposes, such as saving money for college or buying useful things such as cars or clothes.
As young adults, they focus on their goals, both personal and professional. They build on education and career goals set earlier in life and do all that they can to make these goals become reality. They seem to have less confusion or difficulty than some types in choosing a career or selecting a mate because they like focusing and making decisions.
In adult life, ESTJs are likely to take seriously their roles - such as parent, employer, employee, or church member - and to be committed to them and the responsibilities they represent. They are able to compartmentalize their lives and recognize discrete areas of responsibility, such as parenting, working and playing. ESTJs often gain the respect of others because of their dependability, follow-through, and task completion. They may be pillars of the family, community, church, or business world.
</living>
				<learning>ESTJs learn best in structured situations in which the objectives are clearly established. They like schedules or agendas so that they can plan ahead. It is important for them to know the time frames, the course content, the requirements, and when papers or projects are due. It is not sufficient to know that a short paper is a class requirement. The ESTJ wants to know things like an appropriate topic or two, the number of pages, and the due date. ESTJs like plenty of advance notice and dislike changes in class schedules. However, when the teacher's authority is established, these changes may be tolerated> Their idea of a good teacher is one who is consistent, fair, and applications oriented.
ESTJs may be good students when they put in the necessary time and effort. One of their main strengths is their ability to follow through and meet deadlines. They like learning activities such as field trips, experiments, and anything that gets them actively involved in the learning process. They sometimes get stuck when they concentrated only on the facts without putting them together into some kind of coherent whole. 
</learning>
				<working>When an organization wants a job done - on time, according to schedule, with strict specifications - ESTJs can deliver. They contribute their logical and orderly way of evaluating and monitoring programs. They are direct and decisive, especially when they see a flaw. They are especially adept at organizing the steps and the resources needed to get the job done. They follow through with a thoroughness focused on the actual, practical facts of the situation.
ESTJs prefer occupations that require an organized, logical, and practical bent that incorporates an effective use of time and resources. They pay attention to the organization's hierarchy and use policies and procedures to help them to move the tasks along. They like making decisions and dealing with concrete, specific facts.
Some occupations seem to be more attractive to ESTJs: government worker, insurance agent and underwriter, judge, manager, military personnel, nursing administrator, police officer, sales representative, supervisor, trade and technical teacher, and other occupations that allow ESTJs to see tasks accomplished.
</working>
				<leading>ESTJ'S are very much in touch with the external environment. They know their community and usually are pillars of strength. The best adjective to describe ESTJs would be responsible. They represent about 13 percent of the general population. 
ESTJs are outstanding at organizing orderly procedures and in detailing rules and regulations. They like to see things done correctly. They tend to be impatient with those who do not carry out procedures with sufficient attention to those details, prescribed by those with the most experience, that will get the job done right. 
ESTJs are comfortable in evaluating others and tend to judge how a person is doing in terms of standard operating procedures. They may, at times, be abrupt with those who do not follow rules correctly. ESTJs are realistic, matter-of-fact, and more curious about new devices and processes than about new principles and theories. 
</leading>
				<loving>For ESTJs, love means stability and steadfastness. However, when they first fall in love, they are much more likely to be spontaneous and open to the moment. They typically enjoy active pursuits, such as going to parties and sporting events, and taking walks together. ESTJs give and expect security and loyalty in relationships. When commitments are broken, ESTJs become upset because they hold others to the same standards of steadfastness to which they hold themselves.
Because they are logical, they expect logically that relationships will have ups and downs. They firmly believe that with a proper foundation, their relationships will survive expected down times. Because they expect this, they may ignore helping their partner or examining their relationship during those down times. In some cases, this inaction can be detrimental to their relationship, and in some cases, not.
When scorned, they may not quickly acknowledge their feelings of hurt. They are, however, supersensitive to being reflected, but they may not readily share that hurt with others. They continue to go about their tasks acting as if nothing had happened when, in fact, much has changed. 
</loving>
				<careerdetail>ESTJ's generally are loyal to their institutions, work, and community and make excellent, faithful mates and parents. They see where their duty lies and are not likely to shirk the doing of that duty, even when this requires considerable sacrifice on their part. They frequently rise to positions of responsibility in their jobs, in the community, and in their religious affiliations. They very often belong to several civic clubs, and support them both through steady attendance and through their spoken attitudes. ESTJs themselves are punctual and expect others to be also. 
ESTJs may not always be responsive to points of view and emotions of others and may have a tendency to jump to conclusions too quickly at times. They may not always be willing to listen patiently to opposing views; they are especially vulnerable to this tendency when in positions of authority. They may need to make special effort to remain open to input from others who are dependent on them-their children, spouses, and employees. 
ESTJs are so in tune with the established, time-honored institutions and ways of behaving within those institutions that they cannot understand those who might wish to abandon or radically change those institutions. They follow routines well at home and at work, tending to have a place for everything and wanting everything in its place. They are usually neat and orderly at work and at play. 
</careerdetail>
				<home>They approach human relations through traditions and rituals, promoting harmony and contentment in their relationships through creating well worked out routines and procedures. Family traditions have meaning for ISFJs, and they willingly participate in observing these. They enjoy opportunities to see friends, former colleagues, and relatives at functions such as retirement dinners, annual picnics, Thanksgiving gatherings, and weddings. ISFJs are relatively easy to get to know; they do not tend to confuse people by sending double messages. They are dependable and consistent, and what they seem to be is what they are. </home>
				<midlife>At midlife ESTJs may find new challenge in concentrating on better understanding the emotional reaction of others. If they do not develop this sensitivity, they can become bad-tempered and highly impatient with others as the years pass. They probably have been holding a tight rein over their emotions in the service of their careers and family; now a freer expression of these emotions, especially the positive ones, might be exercised. Travel to new places should have particular appeal if the ESTJs make special effort to absorb different cultures and lifestyles. 
 
</midlife>
				<mates>To preserve the establishment, to keep it healthy, steady, balanced, well insured, that's what is enjoyable and satisfying to the ESTJ. Yet the ESTJ is attracted to the disestablishmentarian, the ISFP! Does he hope to redo this bucolic spirit in his own image? Seemingly not. Perhaps he sees in this person's extreme laissez-faire a respite from the great responsibilities he manages to accumulate. 
He can and sometimes does find another sort of complementary opposite, the INFP "monastic." This is very infrequent, there being 15 ESTJs for every INFP. It is doubtful if the ESTJ finds any rest in the INFP, because underneath the monastic is a fierce crusader-hardly what he bargained for. He may soon find himself asked to increase the "depth" and the "meaningfulness" of the relationship without being given even the slightest clue on how to proceed. His renewed efforts to "stabilize" and "solidify" the relationship will only be taken as signs of superficiality and/or meaninglessness.
</mates>
				<strengths>•	Generally enthusiastic, upbeat and friendly 
•	Stable and dependable, they can be counted on to promote security for their families 
•	Put forth a lot of effort to fulfill their duties and obligations 
•	Responsible about taking care of day-to-day practical concerns around the house 
•	Usually good (albeit conservative) with money 
•	Not personally threatened by conflict or criticism 
•	Interested in resolving conflict, rather than ignoring it 
•	Take their commitments very seriously, and seek lifelong relationships 
•	Able to move on after a relationship breaks up 
•	Able to administer discipline when necessary 
</strengths>
				<weakness>•	Tendency to believe that they are always right 
•	Tendency to need to always be in charge 
•	Impatient with inefficiency and sloppiness 
•	Not naturally in tune with what others are feeling 
•	Not naturally good at expressing their feelings and emotions 
•	May inadvertantly hurt others with insensitive language 
•	Tendency to be materialistic and status-conscious 
•	Generally uncomfortable with change, and moving into new territories 
</weakness>	
			</estj>
			
			
		
		
		
		<estp>
				<title>ESTP - The "Persuader"</title>
				<overview>ESTPs are action-loving, "here and now" realists with excellent people skills. Informal, risk-taking, fast-paced and adaptable, they are not always in agreeance with rules and regulations. They are tactical problem solvers that desire quick results. ESTPs, who present a friendly and enthusiastic face, are straightshooters that are able to handle criticism. </overview>
				<temper>SPs are observant, experiential and primarily driven by sensation. They are flexible, aesthetically-aware, "here and now" people that, with hardly a moment's notice, will go where their senses lead. SPs naturally make an effort (with a realistic approach) not to miss an opportunity that may prove to be thrilling, pleasing or otherwise valuable. SPs are are laid back, open-minded and love to feel alive. They have a tendency toward athletics and anything that involves creating or crafting.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 8%
Male: 9%
Female: 7% 
</population>
				<people>
				Real ESTP People 
•	Ann Jillian - actress
•	Bruce Willis - actor (Die Hard)
•	Cybil Shepherd - actress
•	Donald Trump - businessman, TV personality
•	Eddie Murphy - actor, comedian
•	Ernest Hemingway - American novelist
•	Jack Nicholson - actor
•	Jacob (Israel) - Isaac's son, Abraham's grandson
•	James Buchanan - American President
 	•	Jimmy Conners - tennis player
•	Joan Cusack - actress, comedian
•	Lucille Ball - actress (I Love Lucy)
•	Madonna - singer
•	Mae West - actress
•	Michael J. Fox - actor (Back to the Future)
•	Roy Rogers - singer, actor
•	Simon Peter - Disciple of Jesus


Fictional ESTPs (Characters) 
•	Bart Simpson - The Simpsons
•	Bernie Bernbaum - Miller's Crossing
•	Elle Driver - Kill Bill Vol. 1
•	Jake "J.J" Gittes - Chinatown
•	James Bond - James Bond Series
•	John Parker - Alien
•	Krusty the Klown - The Simpsons
 	•	Louie DePalma - Taxi
•	Sidney Falco - Sweet Smell of Success
•	Sonny Corleone - Godfather
•	Spike Spiegel - Cowboy Bebop
•	Tuco - The Good, the Bad and the Ugly
•	Vincent Vega - Pulp Fiction


				</people>
				<career>
				ESTPs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Persuader/Creator personality. 
•	Agent
•	Auditor
•	Computer Technician
•	Craftsman
•	Computer Tech Support
•	Comedian
•	Carpenter
•	Driver
•	Detective
•	Entrepreneur
•	Engineer	 	•	Firefighter
•	Farmer
•	Laborer
•	Military
•	Marketer
•	Network Specialist
•	Project Manager
•	Paramedic/EMT
•	Police
•	Sales Representative

				</career>
				<brief>ESTPs are action oriented, pragmatic, outgoing and realistic people. They use their quickness and flexibility to find the most efficient route to accomplishing whatever needs to be done. They are lively, entertaining, and fun. They like to be where the action is and participate fully in what is happening. Characteristically, they are direct with their comments and mince no words. They are at their best in situations that require an orientation to the present and a direct, no-nonsense, pragmatic approach.</brief>
				<living>ESTP children are rambunctious, energetic, and freedom-loving individuals. They do what they want to do when they want to do it. ESTP children like life to be action packed and fun. They stir things up when they find life too boring. They do not like to sit still and are often involved in energy-intensive sports and other activities with their many friends. They seem unfazed by whatever comes along and prefer to hold a challenge or two. They usually enjoy lively activities in which they can use their motor and observation skills to respond quickly to the moment. 
ESTP children experience and do things in order to learn about life. They are particularly inquisitive about inanimate things. They like having nice toys, games, and equipment, and take care of these material possessions willingly.
School is important to ESTPs as a place to meet their friends and to be involved in activities, and is less important to them as an educational or academic experience. ESTPs can exasperate their parents and teachers, who appreciate their abilities and want them to apply themselves so as to excel academically. However, ESTPs have different needs and wants. Pleasing themselves is their aim, not necessarily achieving top grades for others. Generally, they want to do things their own way and in their own time, and they are rather direct in telling others what is on their minds.
As teenagers, ESTPs continue to be action oriented. They are likely to be on sports teams or involved in other after-school activities. If they have a part-time job, they use the money to purchase or save for the things they want, such as sporting equipment, clothes, stereos, cars, and college education.
As young adults, ESTPs tend to fall into their careers. If they are mechanically oriented, they may find a career in mechanics; if their friends are going to college, they are likely to go to college; If their friends are joining and armed forces, the ESTP may go along as well. 
ESTPs look forward to their independence and are likely to leave home as soon as they can afford to. Being pragmatic types, however, they may find that home, if less restrictions can be negotiated, is a practical and good place to be, because it is cheaper and allows them more money for other important things.
In adult life, ESTPs often focus on work, where they can directly or vicariously experience high risk and high reward. These risks may be physical, intellectual, personal, or financial. They are likely to look for loopholes, special niches, or other unusual opportunities for finding high rewards for the investment of their time. They are willing to play by the rules but only the point of using the rules to help them be or do what they want. They often fill their lives with many activities besides work. They are busy primarily with their families and with friends when they have time.
If and when life becomes too routine for ESTPs, they find ways to jazz it up, either through their own actions or those of others. They may take unusual trips or add to their lives some excitement or big-game hunting. They like life filled with zest. They may choose to retire early so that they can have more time for activities that they consider fun. They enjoy being around others in pursuit of a good time.
</living>
				<learning>ESTPs learn best in situations in which the subject matter applies directly to one of their interests, where the expectations are realistic, and where the explanations are clear. They like observation and hands-on experience, and have little tolerance for theory and material that could be, but that is not currently, useful. Teachers' comments that knowing certain ideas or theories will someday pay off leave most ESTP's cold. They want few constraints put on them. They prefer teachers who are entertaining and make learning active and fun. 
One of the ESTP's main strengths is using the five senses to notice what is happening, to find any flaws and inaccuracies that may exist, and to act quickly on them.
</learning>
				<working>At work, ESTPs contribute a straightforward attitude that calls on people to make things happen quickly. They keep things lively and are willing to take personal and organizational risks. They enjoy crises and like to dive right in and skillfully negotiate through them. Because ESTPs notice and remember factual information, they often contribute a realistic assessment of what is actually happening.
ESTPs value a quick response, they operate under the organizational principle that it is easier to beg for forgiveness after committing the act than to ask for permission in advance. The parts of their work environment or homes that are well-organized tend to relate to their interests. 
The ESTPs' final product, event, paper, or other accomplishment may be excellent, but it belies the ESTP process. ESTP's tend to leave a trail of papers, piles of resources, and messy files and closets, but usually their work is well put together in the end. One ESTP said, "I hate a clean desk. My desk is workable and is organized and categorized as needed."
ESTPs prefer occupations that allow flash and dash, ones in which they can respond dramatically with speed to the present needs. If they choose an occupation in which this is not the case, they bring these characteristics to their work. They do not like to be constrained in their activities and generally seek work that gives them a great deal of latitude.
Some occupations seems to be especially attractive to ESTPs: auditor, carpenter, craft worker, farmer, laborer, marketeer, law enforcement officer, sales representative, service worker, transportation operative, and other occupations that allow ESTPs to use their action-oriented sense of expediency.
</working>
				<leading>ESTP leadership style is one that charge readily, especially in crisis. They have a direct and assertive style, and they move ahead without necessarily paying attention to all of the rules. They find the immediate cause of problems and seek immediate solutions. They can react to any given situation, expedite it, and make it work. They hear different sides of the problem, make decisions and keep things moving. </leading>
				<loving>For the ESTP, love means finding someone to have fun with, sharing life's ups and avoiding life's downs. When an ESTP sees and intended partner as one with whom many exciting experiences can be shared, the ESTP will use persuasiveness and his or her outward, fun-loving orientation to impress and win the chosen partner. The ESTP may view this as a challenge and may use whatever expedient means are available. ESTPs enjoy falling in love but do so quite practically by finding common ground with their loved one. This companionship aspect, in which activities can be jointly pursued, is important to them. 
Generally, ESTPs can be fairly straightforward about the more sensual side of love, regarding it as a major part of life's enjoyment. They may like parties, and entertainment that has an earthy undertone, seeing these activities as a part of life not to be taken too seriously. For ESTPs in relationships, too much daily routine can feel confining and boring. When this happens, they are likely to"liven" things up by surprising their partners with a second honeymoon, a large or extravagant gift, or some other tangible expression of their love.
When scorned, ESTPs may wallow in their grief for some time, then decide that such behaviour is impractical and therefore cut their losses and move on. ESTPs usually approach the breakup of a relationship with a fairly straightforward and realistic orientation. After they have dealt with the emotional part, it is as if fate has taken its course. It is as though they might say, "The relationship is over. Life dealt me a blow, and it's time to move on."
</loving>
				<careerdetail>ESTP's are outstanding as initiators of enterprises that bring people together to negotiate. They make invaluable itinerant administrators who can pull troubled companies or institutions out of the red very quickly, and with style! They can sell an idea or project in a way no other type can, but won't follow through on the tedious administrative details of a project. This characteristic often causes ESTP's to be unappreciated for the extraordinary talents they have, for people lose sight of the idea contributed and focus on the details left undone, becoming critical of ESTPs' weaknesses rather than appreciating their strength. Few enterprises which are institutionally based use ESTP's as they should be used. When they strike out on their own, however, they do not always succeed, for their unwillingness to bother with follow-up details may cause an otherwise excellent project to fail. ESTPs need to be sure they have someone who will take care of follow-up if at all possible. 
If the promotional, entrepreneurial capabilities of ESTPs are used to constructive ends, an institution is fortunate for their presence. If their desire for excitement is not met constructively, however, these energies may be channeled into destructive, antisocial activities such as those of the confidence rackets-counterfeiting, bad-check artistry, safe-cracking, and swindling. A movie of the early 1970's which caught this use of the ESTP's talents was 'The Sting'. 
</careerdetail>
				<home>ESTPs live in the immediate moment and as mates lend excitement-and unpredictability-to the relationship. The ESTP mate is usually extremely attentive in public and smooth in social rituals. They carry on amusing repartee, and laughter surrounds them as they recount from their endless supply of clever jokes and stories. Charm radiates from ESTPs. Nothing is too good for their friends, although family responsibilities may, at times, be given second priority. The ESTP's mate may in time come to feel like an object-the female a chattel and the male a negotiable commodity. Deep commitments do not always occur in the lives of ESTPs, although they are always popular and know many, many people by name. Relationships usually are conditional, and the condition is the consideration of what the ESTP has to gain from the relationship. Anything gained, however, is shared freely and generously with the mate. The unexpected gift, the impulsive trip to Paris, the extravagant surprise at Christmas-all these an ESTP brings to a mate. Fun, excitement, laughter, and that element of unpredictability are characteristic of their relationship. The ESTPs have a low tolerance for anxiety and are apt to avoid or leave situations that are consistently filled with interpersonal tensions. ESTPs are usually somewhat of a mystery to their mates and to others. Few people comprehend this unique personality. ESTPs themselves understand well the maxim, "He who travels fastest, travels alone." Still, ESTPs are not likely to be lonely for long. ESTPs meet life with a hearty appetite for the good things of the world, searching out excitement, perhaps as a warrior, an athlete, an adventurer, or as a professional gambler, but always seeking the thrill of courting Lady Luck in one fashion or another. A theme of seeking excitement through taking of risks runs through the lives of ESTPs. </home>
				<midlife>At midlife ESTPs may want to work at consolidation of resources-emotional and economic. Long-term planning on the part of ESTPs may well destroy the essence of their strength-the impulse-but ESTPs may want rationally and logically to seek out a partner who will follow through on details, who will stabilize projects undertaken, and who will conserve the ESTP energies. ESTPs may want to work at developing a few, deep relationships even though these cause an ESTP entrepreneurial restrictions. </midlife>
				<mates>The relative rarity of the ESTP's opposite on the intuitive side, INFJ (about 1 percent compared to the ESTP's 15 percent), means that such matings will be quite infrequent, as they should be. Imagine an oracle married to a wheeler-dealer! We should, however, be mindful that, whatever our own political beliefs, our more spectacular Presidents (J.F. Kennedy, L.B. Johnson, T. Roosevelt, F.D. Roosevelt) were ESTP "promoters" without peer. It would be a fascinating study to check on the temperament of their wives to see if any married their oracular INFJ opposites. 
The seemingly correct-and, we can assume, attractive-choice is the ISFJ "conservator." Such complementarily should work out rather nicely, especially if the promoter is male and the conservator is female.
</mates>
				<strengths>•	Can be quite charming 
•	Witty, clever, and popular 
•	Earthy and sensual 
•	Not personally threatened by conflict or criticism 
•	Excellent and clear-headed dealing with emergency situations 
•	Enthusiastic and fun-loving, they try to make everything enjoyable 
•	As "big kids" themselves, they're eager, willing and able to spend time with their kids 
•	Likely to enjoy lavishing their loved ones with big gifts (both a strength and a weakness) 
</strengths>
				<weakness>•	Not naturally in tune with what others are feeling 
•	Not naturally good at expressing feelings and emotions 
•	May inadvertantly hurt others with insensitive language 
•	May be very good with money, but highly risky with it as well 
•	Living in the present, they're not usually good long-range planners 
•	May fall into the habit of ignoring conflict, rather than solving it 
•	Don't naturally make lifelong commitments - they take things one day at a time 
•	Prone to get bored easily 
•	More likely than other type to leave relationships quickly when they get bored 
•	Likely to enjoy lavishing their loved ones with big gifts (both a strength and a weakness) 

</weakness>	
			</estp>
			
			
			
			<infj>
				<title>INFJ - The "Confidant"</title>
				<overview>INFJs, making up an estimated 1% of all people, are the most rare type (males even more so). They are introspective, caring, sensitive, gentle and complex people that strive for peace and derive satisfaction from helping others. INFJs are highly intuitive, empathetic and dedicated listeners. These traits tend to act as a "tell me what's wrong" sign on their forehead, hence the nicknames Confidant, Counselor or Empath. INFJs are intensely private and deeply committed to their beliefs. </overview>
				<temper>NFs are introspective, intuitive and highly idealistic. They are subjective, compassionate "feeler" people that desire to contribute goodness and meaning to the lives of others. They are effective at doing this through their nurturing, insightful and encouraging nature. NFs despise conflict. They will do everything they can to make sure their loved ones get along with each other and are happy. NFs are imaginitive, creatively inclined and passionate about their choice causes.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 1%
Male: 0.5%
Female: 1.5% 
</population>
				<people>
				Real INFJ People 
•	Adam Sandler - actor, comedian
•	Anthony Kiedis - singer (Red Hot Chili Peppers)
•	Aristophanes - Greek dramatist
•	Billy Crystal - actor, comedian
•	Carrie Fisher - actress, screenwriter, novelist
•	Chaucer - poet
•	Fanny Crosby - hymn writer
•	Fred McMurray - actor
•	Garry Trudeau - cartoonist (Doonesbury)
•	Gillian Anderson - actress (X-Files)
•	Goethe - poet
•	James Reston - journalist
•	Jamie Foxx - actor, musician, comedian
•	Martin Van Buren - American President
 	•	Mel Gibson - actor, filmmaker
•	Michael Landon - actor (Little House on the Prairie)
•	Nathan - Prophet of Israel
•	Nathaniel Hawthorne - novelist
•	Nelson Mandela - President of South Africa
•	Nicole Kidman - actress
•	Oprah Winfrey - TV show host
•	Paul Stookey - singer-songwriter
•	Piers Anthony - sci-fi/fantasy writer
•	Robert Burns - poet
•	Shirley Temple Black - actress
•	Sudi-Kate - American dramatist, evangelist
•	Tom Selleck - actor


Fictional INFJs (Characters) 
•	Amelie Poulain - Amelie
•	Dr. Yuri Zhivago - Doctor Zhivago
•	Joe Hackett - Wings
 	•	Luke Skywalker - Star Wars
•	Tinman - The Wizard of Oz


				</people>
				<career>
				INFJs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Confidant/Visionary personality. 
•	Actor
•	Artist
•	Alternative Medicine
•	Clergy
•	Consultant
•	Church Worker
•	Chiropractor
•	Child Development
•	Child Care Worker
•	Doctor
•	Dentist
•	Designer
•	Entrepreneur
•	Educational Consultant	 	•	Human Resources
•	Librarian
•	Musician
•	Marketer
•	Missionary
•	Psychologist/Counselor
•	Photographer
•	Psychiatrist
•	Systems Analyst 
•	Social Worker
•	Trainer
•	Teacher/Professor
•	Writer

				</career>
				<brief>INFJs are future oriented, and direct their insight and inspiration toward the understanding of themselves and thereby human nature. Their work mirrors their integrity, and it needs to reflect their inner ideals. Solitude and an opportunity to concentrate thoroughly on what counts most is important to them. INFJs prefer to quietly exert their influence. They have deeply felt compassion, and they desire harmony with others. INFJs understand the complexities existing within people and among them. They are at their best concentrating on their ideas, ideals, and inspirations.</brief>
				<living>INFJ children have two sides. They can be very much involved in the world of people, as well as quiet, imaginative, and in their own world. They are usually gentle and abhor violence. As teenager, INFJs look for a small group of people who understand and appreciate them. Without this support, they can feel isolated from others. INFJs who do not find a supportive social group may find the teen years to be somewhat difficult for them because of peer pressure to be popular and activity oriented. They are not likely to enjoy large parties, but prefer intimate groups of close and long-standing friends. 
Many INFJs who have the opportunity to gravitate toward higher education where they often find their niche. With their intellectual bent, they are led to endeavors that allow them to deal with theory and complexity. Professors often spot their intellectual inclination and encourage it. 
INFJs often settle early into a career choice and diligently apply themselves to the career's requirements. This same diligent pattern applies when selecting other important things in their lives, such as where to live, who to marry, and what activities are worthy of their dedication.
INFJs have an internal picture of how they would like their work to contribute to the general good. If they are in an appropriate career area, INFJs may reap the rewards of their insight and hard work. Because of their future-focus, their people orientation, and their push toward task completion, they may rise to positions of responsibility
</living>
				<learning>INFJs have a strong love of learning, and they tend to do well academically. Through persistence, diligence, and conscientiousness, they complete their assignments on time. They are likely to enjoy research and will go great lengths to find answers. 
INFJs enjoy investigating the possibilities and meanings beyond the actual facts and realities. Reading holds a particular fascination for them because it allows them to have quiet reflection time and engages their imagination. They also like the written word (and rely on it more than the spoken word) since it is usually better structured and more coherent with a ready-made framework.
INFJs write and communicate well because they want to formulate their ideas clearly. They place high regard on their reader and audience. They seek to communicate their ideals to others. When their ideals need to be championed, they speak up in an enthusiastic and impassioned way.
As students, INFJs prefer learning from teachers whom they both like and admire, and who give them personal attention. INFJs are often 'model' students. They are quiet and orderly, reflective and thoughtful, and sincerely want to please their teachers and learn the right thing. They learn best from others but want time to assimilate material by themselves.
INFJs will go beyond what has been presented and often mull material over in their minds. Occasionally they will discuss ruminations with others in order to learn even more. They particularly like the more conceptual and theoretical classes, therefore, higher education is comfortable to them.
</learning>
				<working>INFJs tend to be devoted to what they believe in and seek work where their needs, values, and ideals can be deeply engaged. They move on the wave of their inspirations and are determined to see that their values are worked out in their lives. They will work toward their goals individually and, when needed, will put together a team of other highly dedicated people like themselves. They are personal be with others, working with integrity and consistency, and they follow through on their commitments. INFJs, while concentrating on what is important to them, may ignore the political ramifications of their actions. They can be surprised by the necessity of being political and usually resent that aspect of organizational life. Being able to talk honestly and comfortably to people at work is much more important to them than 'playing games.'
INFJs orient themselves toward their goals using a personal, values-based framework. They do not 'advertise' their values and priorities because they believe in harmony and positive relationships. However, one would do well not to underestimate the amount of perseverance, energy, and time INFJs give to their priorities. What they do, they do with an almost religious intensity.
The INFJ external environment may be only partially organised. Their internal environment, by contrast, is anything but haphazard. Their ideas need to fit into a coherent whole that has the pieces in place. Organization of the internal world takes precedence over organization of external world.
INFJs prefer occupations that focus on the big picture, involve conceptual awareness, and lead to a better understanding of the spiritual, emotional, or future needs of people. They want their work to have impact and meaning and for it to bring them admiration and respect.
While INFJs can and do enter all occupations, some are more appealing to them than others. These include clergy, education consultant, English teacher, fine arts teacher, librarian, psychiatrist, psychologist, scientist, social worker, and other occupations that allow INFJs an opportunity to make their own creative contribution. 
</working>
				<leading>INFJs lead through their quiet yet persistent and determined effort toward long-range goals for themselves, others and their organizations. In working toward their vision, they win cooperation rather than demand it. INFJs work to make their insights real and are able to inspire others with their ideals. They use a low-key, soft, yet intense and determined course of action. When they do not directly lead others, they may still act as facilitators between people. In meetings, they focus on both people and new ideas.</leading>
				<loving>For INFJs, 'still waters run deep.' They tend to become attracted to someone special and prefer this one deep relationship over many superficial ones. The depth of involvement and feeling that the INFJ has toward loved ones is only partially communicated outward. At times, when alone, INFJs become truly in touch with the depth of the love they have for their partner. They may not openly demonstrate or even verbalize their intense feelings. INFJs often have an ideal standard of what love is. They hold to their ideal and are disappointed when, inevitably, their relationship and/or mate reveals flaws. INFJs enjoy sharing activities like a regular 'date,' revisiting the place where they first met their mates, or doing other symbolic things that help to continue and confirm the existence of the bond that they feel for their partner.
INFJs want to give love and to be loved. They enter into relationships just to be cared for, even when the person is not right for them and they suspect it. However, when they meet that special person, they are quick to get into the relationship and make it a serious one. They will end their other relationships in order to pursue their loved one. They become very focused, intense, and direct in that pursuit.
INFJs, when scorned, take it personally and retreat inward. They may obsess about the relationship and their role in its failure. One INFJ explained, 'people can do the most outrageous things, yet I blame myself for triggering their behaviour or not recognizing it. I see myself as responsible for relationships. Other people can dismiss them --- I'm not able to.' INFJs may blame themselves and experience a period of mourning. If they do not marshall their resources, externalized their feelings, and take risks to move on, they may experience a long periods of self-examination.
</loving>
				<careerdetail>INFJs often select liberal arts as a college major and opt for occupations which involve interacting with people, but on a one-to-one basis. For example, the general practitioner in medicine might be an INFJ, or the psychiatrist or psychologist. As with all NF's, the ministry holds attraction, although the INFJ must develop an extraverted role here which requires a great deal of energy. INFJs may be attracted to writing as a profession, and often they use language which contains an unusual degree of imagery. They are masters of the metaphor, and both their verbal and written communications tend to be elegant and complex. Their great talent for language usually is directed toward people, describing people and writing to communicate with people in a personalized way. INFJs who write comment often that they write with a particular person in mind; writing to a faceless, abstract audience leaves them uninspired. 
INFJs make outstanding individual therapists who have the ability to get in touch with the archetypes of their patients in a way some other types do not. The INFJs are also the most vulnerable of all the types to the eruption of their own archetypal material. As therapists, INFJs may choose counseling, clinical psychology, or psychiatry, or may choose to teach in these fields. Writing about these professions often intrigues an INFJ. Whatever their choice, they generally are successful in these fields because their great personal warmth, their enthusiasm, their insight, their depth of concentrations, their originality, and their organizational skills can all be brought into play. 
At work as well as socially, INFJs are highly sensitive in their handling of others and tend to work well in an organizational structure. They have a capacity for working at jobs which require solitude and concentration, but also do well when in contact with people, providing the human interaction is not superficial. INFJs enjoy problem-solving and can understand and use human systems creatively and humanistically. As employees or employers, INFJs are concerned with people's feelings and are able to provide in themselves a barometer of the feelings of individuals and groups within the organizations. INFJs listen well and are willing and able to consult and cooperate with others. Once a decision is made, they work to implement it. 
INFJs are generally good at public relations and themselves have good interpersonal relations. They value staff harmony and want an organization to run smoothly and pleasantly, themselves making every effort to contribute to that end. They are crushed by too much criticism and can have their feelings hurt rather easily. They respond to praise and use approval as a means of motivating others, just as they, the INFJs, are motivated by approval. If they are subject to a hostile, unfriendly working condition or to constant criticism, they tend to lose confidence, become unhappy and immobilized, and finally become physically ill. 
</careerdetail>
				<home>As mates, INFJs are usually devoted to their spouses, but may not always be open to physical approaches. They tend to be physically demonstrative at times, but wish to choose when, which is when they are in the mood. This maybe quite confusing to an extraverted mate. Often an INFJ's expressions of affection will be subtle, taking a humorous, unexpected turn. INFJs need and want harmony in their homes and find constant conflict, overt or covert, extremely destructive to their psyches. Their friendship circle is likely to be small, deep, and longstanding. As parents, INFJs usually are fiercely devoted. A female INFJ, particularly, is linked to her children in a way different from the other types: with almost a psychic symbiosis. This deep bond can create an over-dependency that can be unhealthy for both mother and child. At the same time, INFJs tend to be good friends with their children, while firm in discipline. They usually are concerned about the comfort of a home and most especially the comfort, physical health, and emotional well-being of both mates and children. </home>
				<midlife>At midlife an INFJ can best continue developing the thinking function in the form of logic and the pursuit of theory. The pleasure of taking a theoretical model and applying it to a situation may be a source of interest which an INFJ may have been neglecting. While continuing to pursue the person-to-person in feeling-type relationships, at midlife INFJs may want to get more involved in working with NT's, who offer a dimension not dominant in NF's and vice versa. Carefully providing for rest and taking care of physical health is vital to the INFJ at all times, and mandatory from midlife on. </midlife>
				<mates>The oracular INFJ may opt for the inventive ENTP, but also may go for a different kind of contrary, namely the ESTP. The ESTP and ENTP, to the casual observer, look pretty much alike. Charming, suave, urbane, humorous, witty, fantastically easy to approach, venturesome, even reckless. But one is out to invent, the other to promote; this is no small difference. It takes an inventor to make a mousetrap, it takes a promoter to make an enterprise. To succeed, the promoter has to be, in the best sense of the word, a con artist. He must be able to get people's confidence. Now why would a meaning-giver INFJ be intrigued by an entrepreneur ESTP? Because he wants to help the entrepreneur find his soul and his significance in the scheme of things. Similarly, why is the INFJ attracted to ENTP? Because he wishes to rescue this iconoclast from his seeming folly (and let's face it, most inventions are abortive, or still-born).</mates>
				<strengths>•	Warm and affirming by nature 
•	Dedicated to achieving the ultimate relationship 
•	Sensitive and concerned for others' feelings 
•	Usually have good communication skills, especially written 
•	Take their commitments very seriously, and seek lifelong relationships 
•	Have very high expectations for themselves and others (both a strength and weakness) 
•	Good listeners 
•	Are able to move on after a relationship has ended (once they're sure it's over) 
</strengths>
				<weakness>•	Tendency to hold back part of themselves 
•	Not good with money or practical day-to-day life necessities 
•	Extreme dislike of conflict and criticism 
•	Have very high expectations for themselves and others (both a strength and weakness) 
•	Have difficulty leaving a bad relationship 

</weakness>	
			</infj>
			
		
		
		<infp>
				<title>INFP - The "Dreamer"</title>
				<overview>INFPs are introspective, private, creative and highly idealistic individuals that have a constant desire to be on a meaningful path. They are driven by their values and seek peace. Empathetic and compassionate, they want to help others and humanity as a whole. INFPs are imaginitive, artistic and often have a talent for language and writing. They can also be described as easygoing, selfless, guarded, adaptable, patient and loyal. </overview>
				<temper>NFs are introspective, intuitive and highly idealistic. They are subjective, compassionate "feeler" people that desire to contribute goodness and meaning to the lives of others. They are effective at doing this through their nurturing, insightful and encouraging nature. NFs despise conflict. They will do everything they can to make sure their loved ones get along with each other and are happy. NFs are imaginitive, creatively inclined and passionate about their choice causes.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 2%
Male: 1.5%
Female: 2.5% 
</population>
				<people>
				Real INFP People 
•	A. A. Milne - author (Winnie the Pooh)
•	Albert Schweitzer - theologian, musician, physician
•	Aldous Huxley - English author
•	Amy Tan - author (The Joy-Luck Club)
•	Annie Dillard - author (Pilgrim at Tinker Creek)
•	Audrey Hepburn - actress (Breakfast at Tiffany's)
•	Dick Clark - television personality
•	Donna Reed - acress
•	Fred Rogers - Mister Rogers' Neighborhood
•	Fred Savage - actor (The Wonder Years)
•	George Orwell - author, journalist
•	Helen Keller - deaf/blind author, activist, lecturer
•	Henry Wadsworth Longfellow - American poet
•	Isabel Briggs Myers - psychological theorist
•	J. R. R. Tolkien - writer (Lord of the Rings)
•	James Herriot - veterinary surgeon, writer	 	•	James Taylor - singer-songwriter, guitarist
•	John - Disciple of Jesus
•	John F. Kennedy, Jr. - lawyer, journalist, publisher
•	Laura Ingalls Wilder - author (Little House on the Prairie)
•	Lisa Kudrow - actress ("Phoebe" on Friends)
•	Luke - physician, author
•	Mary - Mother of Jesus
•	Mia Farrow - actress
•	Neil Diamond - musician
•	Peter Jackson - filmmaker (Lord of the Rings
•	Princess Diana - Princess of Wales
•	Scott Bakula - actor (Start Trek Enterprise)
•	Tom Brokaw - television journalist
•	Virgil - ancient Roman poet
•	William Shakespeare - English poet and playwright

Fictional INFPs (Characters) 
•	Anne - Anne of Green Gables
•	Bastian Balthazar Bux - The Neverending Story
•	Calvin - Calvin and Hobbes
•	Deanna Troi - Star Trek: The Next Generation
•	Doctor Julian Bashir - Star Trek: Deep Space 9
•	Doug Funnie - Doug cartoon
 	•	E.T. - E.T. the Extra-Terrestrial
•	Fox Mulder - X-Files
•	Rocko - Rocko's Modern Life
•	Tommy Pickles - Rugrats
•	Wesley Crusher - Star Trek: The Next Generation

				</people>
				<career>
				INFPs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Dreamer/Visionary personality. 
•	Activist
•	Architect
•	Artist
•	Actor
•	Counselor
•	Church Worker
•	Employee Development Specialist
•	Educational Consultant
•	Editor
•	Filmmaker
•	Fashion Designer
•	Graphic/Web Designer
•	Holistic Health Practitioner
•	Human Resources
•	Journalist
•	Librarian	 	•	Legal Mediator
•	Massage Therapist
•	Missionary
•	Musician
•	Minister
•	Psychologist/Counselor
•	Photographer
•	Physical Therapist
•	Researcher
•	Social Scientist
•	Speech Pathologist
•	Social Worker
•	Translator/Interpreter
•	Teacher/Professor
•	Video Editor
•	Writer

				</career>
				<brief>INFPs focus deeply on their values, and they devote their lives to pursuing the ideal. They often draw people together around a common purpose and work to find a place for each person within the group. They are creative, and they seek new ideas and possibilities. They quietly push for what is important to them, and they rarely give up. While they have a gentleness about them and a delightful sense of humor, they may be somewhat difficult to get to know and may be overlooked by others. They are at their best making their world more in line with their internal vision of perfection.</brief>
				<living>INFP children often create their own fantasy world and live very much within it. They may daydream about what is important to them, and sometimes others wonder if they are in touch with reality. They often get lost in their thoughts and books, and may develop a special ability in communicating, such as writing. They are somewhat reserved, especially in new situations.
INFPs decide early on what is important for them, what is of value. They tend to rely on themselves for direction and are reticent to ask others for help. They would rather do things themselves, to make sure they are done properly. INFPs have found this to be both a strength and a curse. Depending only on themselves and being careful not to show mistakes to others is important. As teens, INFPs may have a bit of a rebellious streak. They may argue with those who hold different values than they do. They are also likely to have a small, close set of friends with whom they share good times. In the comfort of those close relationships, they can relax and are often quite entertaining, since they see the world in a different and special way. Their sense of humour is readily apparent. However, unless an INFP finds an appreciation for his or her uniqueness and personal values, he or she may feel like an odd person out.
When they set their minds on things, INFPs are not likely to give up easily, yet because of their outward gentleness, they do not show their determination. They may not take a direct path, but somehow they reach their dreams. 
As young adults, INFPs may have some difficulty finding the ideal career and the ideal mate, in part because of that very word 'ideal'. They have a vision in mind of what they want, yet reality may not follow suit. They may make several starts and stops in their career until they find a comfortable place for themselves. 
INFPs have a need for perfection in connection with their personal values. They become frustrated with those who dwell on trivialities. 
INFPs need a purpose beyond the paycheck. They become burned out easily if their job does not fit their value system; they may not feel good enough about what they have achieved and, as a result, may undervalue themselves and their contributions. 
In retirement, INFPs need to look back and feel that they have led a worthwhile life that has made a difference. They want time for a variety of activities, including travel. They may also be very attached to their family and enjoy special visits with them. 
</living>
				<learning>INFPs learn best in flexible situations where they know the teacher takes a personal interest in them. They like to be able to interact with their peers, but not too much so. They want to feel free to dig into subjects that are of interest to them. Having both flexibility and creativity rewarded is encouraging to them. While they may not enjoy deadlines, if they value the assignment, they will meet those deadlines. Deadlines may force INFPs to decide that their work is 'good enough' to turn in.
Subjects that hold a great deal of interest for them are learned readily. They will often do extra work in their attempt to learn as much as possible about something of interest. And they often read assignments carefully and them work their creativity into the given framework of the assignment. Thus it may appear that they did not pay careful attention to the details of the assignment in their reinterpretation. It is best if they have teachers who appreciate their unique approach and who do not hold them to the letter of the law.
</learning>
				<working>At work, INFPs contribute their creativity, their value system, and their ability to work with others. They are able to see the larger picture and how specific programs fit in. They do not dwell on the trivialities or the details. Their job must be fun, although not racous, and it must be meaningful to them. They need a strong purpose in their work. They want to be recognized and valued, without undue attention given to them. They may become embarrassed when make the center of attention. As a result, they may undersell their strengths in order to avoid being singled out and made to feel conspicuous. They would rather have their worth be noticed gradually over time.
INFPs like to work with cooperative people committed to the same values that they are. They can become bothered when they see others working at cross purposes, especially when conflict is overt. They do not like competition or bureaucracy. They need privacy. Calm and quiet appeal to them, as does time and space for reflection. People usually like working with INFPs even though they may not know them well.
INFPs are quite disorganized. But when tasks at hand are important and best done in an organized way, INFPs strive to do so. Practicality is not a driving force for INFPs. Things that traditionally belong together may not be placed together because the INFP does not see it as necessary. They have trouble finishing what they start because of their perfectionistic nature. When they do finish a project, they may not consider it done 'for good.' Projects can always be improved upon, revised, and reworked, and therefore INFPs find it hard to bring tasks to closure. Because they are able to visualize the finished product long before it is done, the actual completion is of less importance.
INFPs prefer occupations in which they can be involved in making the world better. Having their heart in their work is important to them. These occupations also allow for an element of creativity and flexibility. INFPs are particularly interested to be counselor, editor, education consultant, English teacher, fine arts teacher, journalist, psychologist, religious educator, social scientist, social worker, teacher, writer, and other occupations that engage their values.
</working>
				<leading>The INFP leadership style is subtle, gentle, indirect, and inclusive of others. INFPs do not confront people head-on, but rather work with them and through them to get the job done. Their style is not an aggressive one but is highly persistent; only reluctantly do INFPs assume leadership roles.
They lead with their values in mind, and these guide them. They prefer not to take a hands-on approach with others but to allow them to achieve in independent ways. They are facilitative rather than directive. They encourage others by appreciation and praise. Critiquing others does not come easily to them.
INFPs seldom confront situations directly, in part because they do not like conflict. Whenever possible, they would rather wait for a situation to work itself out, since they trust that people will work things through. They do not like following all the rules and regulations, but they are not overtly rebellious. They seek to get things done in their own style.
</leading>
				<loving>For the INFP, love is a very deep commitment, and one that is not easily attained. They have ideals, and therefore reality may be carefully scrutinized.
With their ideal firmly envisioned, the first date with that special person is carefully planned and prepared for, and often every aesthetic thing is taken care of. The flowers are in place, the right wine is ordered, and the proper meal is prepared. 
INFPs may have difficulty sharing their feelings about others. They keep so many of those feelings inside that they may forget to tell their partner how much they love and appreciate them. They also need reminders of their partner's love.
When things go wrong in a relationship, the INFP takes it to heart but does not readily discuss it with others. They may not be willing to communicate to let others know how they are feeling. When scorned, they are very hurt and may overreact in an almost maudlin way.
</loving>
				<careerdetail>At work, INFPs are adaptable, welcome new ideas and new information, are well aware of people and their feelings, and relate well to most, albeit with some psychological distance. INFPs dislike telephone interruptions and work well alone, as well as with others. They are patient with complicated situations, but impatient with routine details. They can make errors of fact, but seldom of values. Their career choices may be toward the ministry, missionary work, college teaching, psychiatry, architecture, psychology-and away from business. They seem willing and usually are able to apply themselves scholastically to gain the necessary training for professional work, often doing better in college than in high school. They have a natural interest in scholarly activities and demonstrate, as do the other NF's, a remarkable facility for languages. Often they hear a calling to go forth into the world to help others; they seem willing to make the necessary personal sacrifices involved in responding to that call, even if it means asking others to do likewise. INFPs can make outstanding novelists and character actors, for they are able to efface their own personalities in their portrayal of a character in a way other types cannot. </careerdetail>
				<home>As mates, INFPs have a deep commitment to their pledges. They like to live in harmony and may go to great lengths to avoid constant conflict. They are sensitive to the feelings of others and enjoy pleasing those they care for. They may find it difficult to reconcile a romantic, idealized concept of conjugal life with the realities of everyday living with another person. At times, in fact, INFPs may seem fearful of exuberant attainment, afraid that current advances may have to be paid for with later sacrifices. The devil is sure to get his due if the INFP experiences too freely of success, or beauty, or health, or wealth, or knowledge. And thus, INFPs guard against giving way to relaxing in the happiness of mating. They may have difficulty in expressing affection directly, but communicate interest and affection indirectly. 
For INFPs, their home is their castle. As parents, they are fierce in protection of home and family and are devoted to the welfare of family members. They have a strong capacity for devotion, sympathy, and adaptability in their relationships, and thus are easy to live with. They are loyal to their family and, although they may dream of greener pastures, if they stray into those pastures they soon locate the nettles. The almost preconscious conviction that pleasure must be paid for with pain can cause a sense of uneasiness in the family system of an INFP, who may transmit an air of being ever-vigilant against invasion. In the routine rituals of daily living, INFPs tend to be compliant and may even prefer having decisions made on their behalf, until their value system is violated! Then INFPs dig in their heels and will not budge from ideals. Life with an INFP will go gently along for long periods, until an ideal is struck and violated. Then an INFP will resist and insist. 
</home>
				<midlife>At midlife INFPs may want to increase mastery of intellectual interests, perhaps taking advanced degrees in a chosen profession. They also may want to explore the sensual side of their natures, expanding their aesthetic appreciations to include physical sensory appreciations. Extending social activities and contacts may offer new horizons for INFPs, but they will have to guard against overextension psychologically, for before, during, and after midlife the vulnerability and sensitivity of the INFP will continue, and he or she can easily become emotionally drained. </midlife>
				<mates>The INFP questor probably has more problems in mating than any other type. Let us be mindful of the relative infrequency: about 1 1/4 percent, say two and a half million people in the USA. Their problem lies in their primary outlook on life. "Life," says the INFP, "is a very serious matter." Now when a person makes his life a kind of crusade or a series of crusades, then there's bound to be some taxing of the spouse. If the INFP takes the other tack, the "monastic" (and the same person can tack back and forth-now a crusader, now a monastic), the spouse will find himself again taxed, trying to draw the monastic out of his dark meditative cave. 
The opposites of our crusading monastic seem well equipped for this alternating-phase taxation: ENTJ and ESTJ. Both are anchored in the real world with a vengeance. The ENTJ marshaling his or her forces toward distant objectives, the ESTJ administrating in a solid, dependable, and traditional way whatever is his or hers to administer. Both provide anchorage to a person who might otherwise get lost in meditation or in crusade. Selection of a mate of irrelevant form (e.g., an ISTP artisan or an ESTP promoter) would not be the wisest of tactics in so serious a business as life.
</mates>
				<strengths>Most INFPs will exhibit the following strengths with regards to relationship issues: 
•	Warmly concerned and caring towards others 
•	Sensitive and perceptive about what others are feeling 
•	Loyal and committed - they want lifelong relationships 
•	Deep capacity for love and caring 
•	Driven to meet other's needs 
•	Strive for "win-win" situations 
•	Nurturing, supportive and encouraging 
•	Likely to recognize and appreciate other's need for space 
•	Able to express themselves well 
•	Flexible and diverse 
</strengths>
				<weakness>Most INFPs will exhibit the following weaknesses with regards to relationship issues: 
•	May tend to be shy and reserved 
•	Don't like to have their "space" invaded 
•	Extreme dislike of conflict 
•	Extreme dislike of criticism 
•	Strong need to receive praise and positive affirmation 
•	May react very emotionally to stressful situations 
•	Have difficulty leaving a bad relationship 
•	Have difficulty scolding or punishing others 
•	Tend to be reserved about expressing their feelings 
•	Perfectionistic tendancies may cause them to not give themselves enough credit 
•	Tendency to blame themselves for problems, and hold everything on their own shoulders
</weakness>	
			</infp>
		
	
	
	
		<intj>
				<title>INTJ - The "Strategist"</title>
				<overview>INTJs are introspective, analytical, determined persons with natural leadership ability. Being reserved, they prefer to stay in the background while leading. Strategic, knowledgable and adaptable, INTJs are talented in bringing ideas from conception to reality. They expect perfection from themselves as well as others and are comfortable with the leadership of another so long as they are competent. INTJs can also be described as decisive, open-minded, self-confident, attentive, theoretical and pragmatic. </overview>
				<temper>NTs are introspective, logical and on a constant quest for knowledge. They are practical and unsentimental in their approach to problem solving. The actions of an NT are precise and follow a systematic course. Abstract, theoretical and technically adept, NTs are naturally inventive. They can also be described as being analytical, intellectual, inquisitive, independent and complex.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 1.5%
Male: 2.5%
Female: 0.5%
</population>
				<people>
				Real INTJ People 
•	Angela Lansbury - actress (Murder, She Wrote)
•	Arnold Schwarzenegger - actor, Governor of California
•	Arthur Ashe - tennis champion
•	Augustus Caesar - Roman Emperor
•	C. Everett Koop - former U.S. Surgeon General
•	C. S. Lewis - apologist, author (The Chronicles of Narnia)
•	Calvin Coolidge - American President
•	Charles Rangel - politician, decorated war veteran
•	Chester A. Arthur - lawyer, American President
•	Chevy Chase - actor, comedian
•	Dan Akroyd - actor, comedian, musician
•	Donald Rumsfeld - former U.S. Secretary of Defense
•	Dwight D. Eisenhower - American President
•	Edwin Moses - olympic gold medalist
•	General Colin Powell - former U.S. Secretary of State
•	Greg Gumbel - TV sportscaster
•	Hannibal Barca - Military Commander
•	Ivan Lendl - tennis champion
•	James K. Polk - American President
•	Jane Austen - author (Pride and Prejudice)	 	•	Joan Lunden - Journalist
•	Josephine Tey - English author
•	Katie Couric - journalist
•	Lance Armstrong - cyclist (seven Tour De France wins)
•	Maria Shriver - journalist, wife to Arnold Schwarzenegger
•	Martina Navratilova - tennis champion
•	Michael Dukakis - former Governor of Massachusetts
•	Orel Hershiser - baseball player (pitcher)
•	Pernell Roberts - actor, activist
•	Peter Jennings - journalist
•	Raymond Burr - actor (Perry Mason), vintner
•	Rudy Giuliani - former New York City mayor
•	Sir Isaac Newton - Astronomer
•	Susan B. Anthony - civil rights leader
•	Thomas Jefferson - American President
•	Veronica Hamel - actress
•	William F. Buckley, Jr. - journalist
•	William J. Bennett - politician
•	Woodrow Wilson - American President


Fictional INTJs (Characters) 
•	Clarice Starling - Silence of the Lambs
•	Dr. Jonathan Crane - Batman Begins
•	Ellen Ripley - Alien
•	Ensign Ro Laren - Star Trek: The Next Generation
•	Ernst Stavro Blofeld - James Bond
•	Gandalf - Lord of The Rings, The Hobbit
•	George Smiley - John Le Carr� character
•	Hannibal Lecter - Silence of the Lambs
•	Marsellus Wallace - Pulp Fiction
•	Michael Corleone - Godfather
 	•	Mr. Burns - The Simpsons
•	Mr. Darcy - Pride and Prejudice
•	O-Ren Ishii - Kill Bill Vol. 1
•	Professor Moriarty - Sherlock Holmes antagonist
•	Rosencrantz and Guildenstern - Hamlet
•	Stewie Griffin - Family Guy
•	Tom Hagen - Godfather
•	Vicious - Cowboy Bebop
•	Vito Corleone - Godfather


				</people>
				<career>
				INTJs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Strategist/Intellectual personality. 
•	Business Administrator
•	Corporate Strategist
•	Computer Programmer
•	Computer Specialist
•	Dentist
•	Entrepreneur
•	Engineer
•	Judge
•	Lawyer/Attorney	 	•	Military Officer
•	Manager
•	Medical Doctor
•	Organization Founder
•	Psychologist
•	Researcher
•	Scientist
•	Systems Analyst 
•	Teacher/Professor

				</career>
				<brief>INTJs are strong individualists who seek new angles or novel ways of looking at things. They enjoy coming to new understandings. They are insightful and mentally quick; however, this mental quickness may not always be outwardly apparent to others since they keep a great deal to themselves. They are very determined people who trust their vision of the possibilities, regardless of what others think. They may even be considered the most independent of all of the sixteen personality types. INTJs are at their best in quietly and firmly developing their ideas, theories, and principles.</brief>
				<living>The independent and individualistic INTJ manner appears early in life. As children, INTJs are often inwardly focused on their thoughts of the way the world is or ought to be; they enjoy day dreaming. They can be quite stubborn when information relayed to them by authorities, such as parents and teachers, contradicts what they believe. They are sure of their own belief system. INTJs are compelled to establish their own rules, boundaries, standards, and style. 
Often at an early age, INTJs make a commitment to furthering their education. The life of the mind is very important to them. Examples abound of INTJs from economically or intellectually impoverished circumstances setting goals for themselves to continue in education, often earning the highest degree possible.
INTJ teenagers may be seen as serious and reserved young people who are labeled as bookworms by others. They set internal standards of achievement for themselves and often do well academically. Being sociable is a standard that they rarely think is worth their time and energy. 
As adults, INTJs are focused on attaining their inner goals and standards. They set a particular course based on their theory of what ought to be. They work extremely diligently to accomplish what they feel is important. They enjoy what they do and see it as a challenge. They are not easily dissuaded and may regard others' needs and wants as an impediment to attaining their objectives. 
</living>
				<learning>INTJs learn best when they can design their won approach and when they are able to absorb themselves in an area that interests them. They tend to focus on systems, theories, and constructs relating to universal truths and principles. They prefer challenging teachers, ones who meet their standards. High grade-point averages and test scores tend to characterize INTJs, who like rigorous academic work. Learning needs to be a creative process. Rote memory can be dull and boring for the INTJ.
INTJs are diligent in pursuing new ideas and thoughts, and they exert effort to master a given subject. This makes INTJs particularly adept in most school situations. Because of their resourcefulness, thirst for knowledge, and inner needs, INTJs tend to find ways of acquiring knowledge. They gravitate toward libraries, public lectures, courses, and other learners and teachers - sources that offer them information and direction.
</learning>
				<working>At work, INTJs use their conceptual strengths to analyze situations and then develop models to understand and anticipate through relentlessly to reach their goals. They will continue on with their plans, even in the face of adversity and data that might suggest to other more practical types that their goals are no longer feasible. By nature, INTJs are independent individualists. They see their visions so clearly that they are often surprised when others do not see things the same way. INTJs are strong at critiquing and as a result tend to notice the negatives. To them, a job well done should be reward enough in itself. They may neglect to comment favorably on others' contributions.
INTJs tend to seek occupations that allow them to change the status quo and to design models to express their vision creatively. They desire autonomy and room for growth. They prefer to work in a place in which the future can be planned and where they can work for change in an organized manner.
Some occupations seem to be especially attractive to INTJs: computer systems analyst, electrical engineer, judge, lawyer, photographer, psychologist, research department manager, researcher, scientist, university instructor, and other occupations in which long-range vision is essential.
</working>
				<leading>INTJs are the most self-confident of all types, having "self-power" awareness. Found in about 1 percent of the general population, the INTJs live in an introspective reality, focusing on possibilities, using thinking in the form of empirical logic, and preferring that events and people serve some positive use. Decisions come naturally to INTJs' once a decision is made, INTJs are at rest. INTJs look to the future rather than the past, and a word which captures the essence of INTJs is builder-a builder of systems and the applier of theoretical models. 
To INTJs authority based on position, rank, title, or publication has absolutely no force. This type is not likely to succumb to the magic of slogans, watchwords, or shibboleths. If an idea or position makes sense to an INTJ, it will be adopted, if it doesn't, it won't, regardless of who took the position or generated the idea. As with the INTP, authority per se does not impress the INTJ. 
INTJs do, however, tend to conform to rules if they are useful, not because they believe in them, or because they make sense, but because of their unique view of reality. They are the supreme pragmatists, who see reality as something which is quite arbitrary and made up. Thus it can be used as a tool-or ignored. Reality is quite malleable and can be changed, conquered, or brought to heel. Reality is a crucible for the refining of ideas, and in this sense, INTJs are the most theoretical of all the types. Where an ESTP sees ideas as the pawn of reality, an INTJ sees reality as the pawn of ideas: No idea is too far-fetched to be entertained. INTJs are natural brainstormers, always open to new concepts and, in fact, aggressively seeking them. 
INTJs manipulate the world of theory as if on a gigantic chess board, always seeking strategies and tactics that have high payoff. In their penchant for logic, the INTJs resemble the INTPs. The logic of an INTJ, however, is not confined to the expressible logical. Unlike INTPs, INTJs need only to have a vague, intuitive impression of the unexpressed logic of a system to continue surely on their way. Things need only seem logical; this is entirely sufficient. Moreover, they always have a keen eye for the consequence of the application of new ideas or positions. They can be quite ruthless in the implementation of systems, seldom counting personal cost in terms of time and energy. Theories which cannot be made to work are quickly discarded by the INTJs. 
To understand INTJs, their way of dealing with ideas should be observed closely. Their conscious thought is extraverted and empirical. Hence, they are better at generalizing, classifying, summarizing, adducing evidence, proving, and demonstrating than are the INTPs. The INTJs are somewhat less at home with pure reason, that is, systemic logic, where principles are explicit. In this respect they resemble the ENTJs. The INTJs, rather than using deductive logic, use their intuition to grasp coherence. 
</leading>
				<loving>For INTJs, love means including someone in their vision of the world. INTJ men tend to be attracted to partners who enjoy living their lives with and outward vitality and zest. Perhaps it is to compensate for their internal, visionary focus that they often find partners who are more outgoing and may even run interference to help the INTJ deal with the day-to-day world. INTJ women, however, may seek someone more like themselves.
INTJs tend to have a model in mind of how their relationship ought to be. This is less a romantic vision than it is and idea that relates to how the relationship functions in a unique or special way. They tend to withhold their deep feelings and affections from the public and sometimes even from the object of their affections. They can be intensely loyal and caring, even though this is not always expressed in words. INTJs can be generous with their gifts if the gift fits their vision of what ought to be appreciated by their partner. 
When scorned, INTJs retreat to their own world and may share none of their feelings with others. They may assume that there is a right way for a relationship to end and look for that. They act on the outside as if nothing has happened to them when indeed much has. They may lash out with criticisms of their former loved ones. It may take them a while to recover.
</loving>
				<careerdetail>INTJs can be very single-minded at times; this can be either a weakness or a strength in their careers, for they can ignore the points of view and wishes of others. INTJs usually rise to positions of responsibility, for they work long and hard and are steady in their pursuit of goals, sparing neither time nor effort on their part or that of their colleagues and employees. 
INTJs live to see systems translated into substance; an INTP, by way of contrast, is content to design the system. In both these types, however, coherence is the master. Both internal and external consistency are important, and if an INTJ finds that he or she is in a working situation where overlapping functions, duplication of effort, inefficient paper flow, and waste of human and material resources abound, the INTJ cannot rest until an effort is made to correct the situation. Cost-effectiveness is a concept which has a strong imperative for INTJs, who frequently select occupations in engineering, particularly human engineering. They also can be found in the physical sciences, in roles which require development, such as curriculum building, and, in general, any job which requires the creation and application of technology to complex areas. 
Fellow workers of INTJs often feel as if the INTJ can see right through them, and often believe that the INTJ finds them wanting. This tendency of people to feel transparent in the presence of the INTJ often result in relationships which have psychological distance. Thus colleagues find the INTJ apparently unemotional and, at times, cold and dispassionate. Because of their tendency to drive others as hard as they do themselves, INTJs often seem demanding and difficult to satisfy. INTJs are high achievers in school and on the job. On the job, they take the goals of an institution seriously and continually strive to respond to these goals. They make dedicated, loyal employees whose loyalties are directed toward the system, rather than toward individuals within the system. So as the people of an institution come and go, the INTJs have little difficulty-unlike the NFs, who have their loyalties involved more with persons than offices. INTJs tend, ordinarily, to verbalize the positive and eschew comments of a negative nature; they are more interested in moving an institution forward than commiserating about mistakes of the past. 
</careerdetail>
				<home>Home 
As mates, INTJs want harmony and order in the home and in relationships. They are the most independent of all types. They will trust their intuitions about others when making choices of friends and mates, even in the face of contradictory evidence and pressures applied by others. The emotions of an INTJ are hard to read, and neither male nor female INTJ is apt to express emotional reactions. At times, both will seem cold, reserved, and unresponsive, while in fact INTJs are almost hypersensitive to signals of rejection from those for whom they care. In social situations, INTJs may also be unresponsive and may neglect to observe small rituals designed to put others at their ease. For example, INTJs may communicate that time is wasted if used for idle dialogue, and thus people receive a sense of hurry from an INTJ which is not always intended. In their interpersonal relationships, INTJs are usually better in a working situation than in recreational situations. They do not enjoy physical contact except with a chosen few. 
As parents, INTJs are dedicated and single minded in their devotion: Their children are a major focus in life. They are supportive of their children and tend to allow them to develop in directions of their own choosing. INTJs usually are firm and consistent in their discipline and rarely care to repeat directions given to children...or others. Being the most independent of all the types, they have a strong need for autonomy; indifference or criticism from people in general does not particularly bother INTJs, if they believe that they are right. They also have a strong need for privacy. 
The most important preference of an INTJ is intuition, but this is seldom seen. Rather, the function of thinking is used to deal with the world and with people. INTJs are vulnerable in the emotional area and may make serious mistakes here
</home>
				<midlife>At midlife the feeling side of personality should be given much attention by the INTJ, who can work at expanding his or her abilities to respond to wishes and feelings of others. They may also do well to turn more attention to the sensory side of their natures, attempting to get in touch with the joys of good food, good beverages, social rituals, kinesthetic experiences...and play. The "wasting" of time in play is an appropriate target as a midlife task for INTJs who can take lessons from an SP, especially an ESP, in the art of enjoying the pleasures of life. </midlife>
				<mates>Wishing to control nature, the INTJ "scientist" probably has more difficulty than all other types in making up his or her mind in mate selection. Even mate selection must be done in a scientific way. It may well be that the narratives, plays, and films impugning the "rational and objective" approach to mating have as their target our thorough-going scientist INTJ. Nevertheless, when young, the INTJ is attracted to the free-wheeling, spontaneous, fun-loving "entertainer" ESFP. But the INTJ requires that mating meet certain criteria, else it is not undertaken. So the INTJ doesn't often go through with what is begun by natural attraction. Since he or she proceeds in a rational and methodical way, the selection of a similar temperament is more likely than selection of opposite, following the assumption that those who are similar ought to do well together. The INTJ "scientist" is also attracted to the ENFP "journalist," probably because of the enthusiastic, effervescent, and apparently spontaneous enjoyment and wonderment this type exudes-the very antitheses of the careful, thoughtful exactitude of the INTJ.</mates>
				<strengths>•	Not threatened by conflict or criticism 
•	Usually self-confident 
•	Take their relationships and commitments seriously 
•	Generally extremely intelligent and capable 
•	Able to leave a relationship which should be ended, although they may dwell on it in their minds for awhile afterwards 
•	Interested in "optimizing" their relationships 
•	Good listeners 
</strengths>
				<weakness>•	Not naturally in tune with others feelings; may be insensitive at times 
•	May tend to respond to conflict with logic and reason, rather than the desired emotional support 
•	Not naturally good at expressing feelings and affections 
•	Tendency to believe that they're always right 
•	Tendency to be unwilling or unable to accept blame 
•	Their constant quest to improve everything may be taxing on relationships 
•	Tend to hold back part of themselves 

</weakness>	
			</intj>
		
		
		
		<intp>
				<title>INTP - The "Engineer"</title>
				<overview>INTPs are logical, individualistic, reserved, and very curious individuals. They focus on ideas, theories and the explanation of how things work. They are especially adept at discussions and debate. They have the ability to focus intently on a subject. They appreciate and respect intelligence in others.</overview>
				<temper>NTs are introspective, logical and on a constant quest for knowledge. They are practical and unsentimental in their approach to problem solving. The actions of an NT are precise and follow a systematic course. Abstract, theoretical and technically adept, NTs are naturally inventive. They can also be described as being analytical, intellectual, inquisitive, independent and complex.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 2.5%
Male: 4%
Female: 1% 
</population>
				<people>
				Real INTP People 
•	Abraham Lincoln - American President
•	Albert Einstein - German physicist
•	Ashley Olsen - actress (Full House)
•	Blaise Pascal - French mathematician
•	Bob Newhart - comedian, actor
•	Brent Spiner - actor ("Data" on Star Trek)
•	Carl Jung - Swiss psychiatrist
•	Charles Darwin - English naturalist
•	Gerald Ford - American President
•	James Madison - American President
•	Jeff Bingaman - U.S. Senator
 	•	John Quincy Adams - American President
•	John Tyler - American President
•	Mary-Kate Olsen - actress (Full House)
•	Meryl Streep - actress
•	Midori Ito - Japanese figure skater
•	Rene Descartes - French philosopher
•	Rick Moranis - actor (Honey, I Shrunk the Kids)
•	Socrates - Greek philosopher
•	William Harvey - medical doctor
•	William James - American psychologist


Fictional INTPs (Characters) 
•	Ash - Alien
•	Avon - Blake's 7
•	Brian Griffin - Family Guy
•	Data - Start Trek: The Next Generation
 	•	Dr. Susan Lewis - E.R. TV show
•	Filburt - Rocko's Modern Life
•	Seven of Nine - Star Trek: Voyager


				</people>
				<career>
				INTPs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Engineer/Intellectual personality. 
•	Artist
•	Actor
•	Architect
•	Archaeologist
•	Agent
•	Consultant
•	Computer Specialist
•	Computer Animator
•	Computer Programmer
•	Engineer
•	Economist
•	Forestry/Park Ranger
•	Financial Planner
•	Historian
•	Human Resources Manager
•	Investigator
•	Investment Banker
•	Inventor
•	Interpreter/Translator	 	•	Judge
•	Legal Mediator
•	Logician
•	Lawyer/Attorney
•	Mathematician
•	Musician
•	Marketer
•	Network Specialist
•	Psychologist
•	Psychiatrist
•	Philosopher
•	Project Manager
•	Photographer
•	Researcher
•	Systems Analyst 
•	Scientist
•	Strategic Planner
•	Technical Writer
•	Teacher/Professor

				</career>
				<brief>INTPs are known for their quest for logical purity, which motivates them to examine universal truths and principles. They are constantly asking themselves and others the questions 'Why?' and 'Why not?' Clear and quick thinkers, they are able to focus with great intensity on their interests. They appreciate elegance and efficiency in thought processes and require them, even more so, in their own communications. They may be seen as unwilling to accept what everyone else regards as truth. While often low key in outward appearance and approach, the INTP is 'hard as nails' when challenging a truth. INTPs do not like to deal with the obvious. They are at their best in building conceptual models and developing unusual and complex ideas.</brief>
				<living>As children, INTPs are inwardly focused, often enjoying their won thoughts more than the company of others. They are full of questions, sometimes voiced, most often not. INTP children often challenge and even stump their elders. They enjoy fantasy, mysteries, inventing, thinking and doing things that may be somewhat atypical for other children of their age, and they sense their uniqueness early on. If INTPs are fond of books or games, it is likely that their choices will be the current rage. If and INTP is fond of music, it is likely to be of and unusual sort. 
INTPs tend to either respect and go along with society's rules, or to question and rebel against them. Their response to these rules depends on how the rules might affect them. When INTPs do not like the rules, they are quick to find the flaws in the rule makers' thinking, regardless of their status, position in the hierarchy, or renown.
As young adults choosing careers, INTPs either set a course and work toward it quietly yet forcefully or continue to resist and rebel against society's expectations and irrational rules. They may either focus in depth on a major interest or move from one interest to another without showing others - friends, colleagues, and bosses - their reasons why. It is the process, the quest, that has been most interesting to them. Once they have found the answer, they do not often share it because the answer is obvious, and documenting the obvious is redundant. This attitude includes a tendency not to response or speak up in groups, because the INTP feels that what he or she was going to say seems so obvious that no one would want to hear it. As INTPs mature, they continue their quest for logical purity, but now it includes more balance in their activities
</living>
				<learning>The INTP is a relentless learner in areas that hold his or her interest. They often seem 'lost in thought,' and this characteristic appears very early. INTPs enjoy the life of the mind and the learning process, regardless of whether that process takes place in a formal sense. They are often characterized as life-long learners. 
In school, well-rounded INTPs work on their assignments with a great deal of inward energy and interest that is usually not apparent to others. They tend to connect unrelated thoughts. As learners, they are able to find logical flaws in the thinking of others. They analyze these flaws and find ideas for further study. They go to great depths in their analysis.
In taking exams, they prefer theorectical questions. When INTPs view a test, teachers, or subjects as irrelevant, they may respond as follows: 'I know what I need to know about this topic; I may even know more than my teacher. The teacher made this test, and this test is dumb. Therefore, my teacher is dumb, and I will not do the test.' Because of such reactions, the INTP's academic record may include successes or may be filled with failures.
INTPs contribute a logical, system-building approach to their work. They like being the architect of a plan, because of the scheming and thinking involved, far more than being the implementer of that plan. Implementation tends to be drudgery. They are content to sit back and think about what might work, given their view of the situation. INTPs may ignore standard operating procedures. The hours that they spend are not what is important to them, but rather the completion of their thought process. When their projects are of interest to them, they can become mesmerized and may even work through the night. when their projects are not intriguing, their work is considered drudgrery, and the INTP finds it difficult to stay motivated.
</learning>
				<working>INTPs usually find a place in their work for using their logical and structured thinking. They enjoy work that allows them to abstract, to generalize beyond the data, and to build models. Flexibility is desired because INTPs like to 'do the job when they want to do it and as they want to do it.' They also prefer occupations in which the hierarchy is minimal and not important. This attitude seems from their firm belief that, to be legitimate, a hierarchy should be built on the competency of individuals who are logically placed according to their talents.
Some occupations seem to be more attractive to INTPs: biologist, chemist, computer programmer, computer system analyst, lawyer, photographer, psychologist, researcher, surveyor, writer and other occupations that allow them to use their logical thinking in appropriate ways.
</working>
				<leading>INTPs exhibit the greatest precision in thought and language of all the types; they tend to see distinctions and inconsistencies in thought and language instantaneously. The one word which captures the unique style of INTPs is architect-the architect of ideas and systems as well as the architect of edifices. This type is found in only 1 percent of the population and therefore is not encountered as frequently as some of the other types. 
INTPs detect contradictions in statements no matter how distant in space or time the contradictory statements were produced. The intellectual scanning of INTPs has a principled quality; that is, INTPs search for whatever is relevant and pertinent to the issue at hand. Consequently, INTPs can concentrate better than any other type. 
Authority derived from office, position, or wide acceptance does not impress INTPs. Only statements that are logical and coherent carry weight. External authority per se is irrelevant. INTPs abhor redundancy and incoherence. Possessing a desire to understand the universe, an INTP is constantly looking for natural law. Curiosity concerning these keys to the universe is a driving force in this type. 
INTPs prize intelligence in themselves and in others, but can become intellectual dilettantes as a result of their need to amass ideas, principles, or understanding of behavior. And once they know something, it is remembered. INTPs can become obsessed with analysis. Once caught up in a thought process, that thought process seems to have a will of its own for INTPs, and they persevere until the issue is comprehended in all its complexity. They can be intellectual snobs and may show impatience at times with others less endowed intellectually. This quality, INTPs find, generates hostility and defensive behavior on the part of others, who may describe an INTP as arrogant. 
For INTPs, the world exists primarily to be understood. Reality is trivial, a mere arena for proving ideas. It is essential that the universe is understood and that whatever is stated about the universe is stated correctly, with coherence and without redundancy. This is the INTPs final purpose. It matters not whether others understand or accept his or her truths. 
</leading>
				<loving>For the INTP, love has three distinct phases: falling in, staying in, and getting out. These phases relate to their thinking preference and its need for order and sequence.
An INTP characterized falling in love as a stage of complete loss of rationality that may last a year or less. When an INTP falls in love, he or she falls hard - an all or nothing phenomenon. At this stage, INTPs are likely to be very lively, almost giddy, in their new love. The experience rushes over them and carries them along. They do not structure or control it but simply enjoy and experience it. They do many loving things and they are curious about their loved one and are able to overlook his or her flaws. They may bravely ignore the realities of distance, weather, and time to be with the loved one. 
As relationships progress to the staying-in-love phase, INTPs begin to evaluate their structure and form. They may withdraw at this point because they are moving toward their more customary inward style. Outward demonstrations of affection lessen, and the giddy state changes. Interactions are more matter of fact, perhaps even impersonal. INTPs take their commitments to their partner seriously; however, they may not discuss these commitments at any length with their partner or with other people, because their commitments seem so obvious to them.
Falling out of love, which may not always occur, results from an analysis of the real expectations and needs of the relationship. Often an undefined line is crossed that neither partner knows about ahead of time. However, the INTP knows after the line has been crossed, and then the relationship deteriorates or ends. If INTPs recognize their emotions and needs as valid, they are able to sever relationship ties fairly cleanly. However, if they misjudge their own needs and those of their partner, the breakup can be messy, perhaps affecting other aspects of their lives for a long time. If the INTP shares some common interests with the former loved one, the relationship continues but on a different level. When INTPs have a reason to continue relationships, they do.
</loving>
				<careerdetail>The INTP is the logician, the mathematician, the philosopher, the scientist; any pursuit requiring architecture of ideas intrigues this type. INTP's should not, however, be asked to work out the implementation or application of their models to the real world. 
The INTP is the architect of a system and leaves it to others to be the builder and the applicator. Very often therefore, the INTP's work is not credited to him or her. The builder and the applier gains fame and fortune, while the INTP's name remains obscure. Appreciation of an INTP's theoretical work frequently comes posthumously-or the work may never be removed from library shelves at all and thus lost. 
INTP's tend not to be writers or to go into sales work. They are, however, often excellent teachers, particularly for advanced students, although INTP's do not always enjoy much popularity, for they can be hard taskmasters. They are not good at clerical tasks and are impatient with routine details. They prefer to work quietly, without interruption, and often alone. If an organization is to use the talents of an INTP appropriately, the INTP must be given an efficient support staff who can capture ideas as they emerge and before the INTP loses interest and turns to another idea. 
Our "architect" is not merely a designer of buildings. There is the architect of ideas (the philosopher), the architect of number systems (the mathematician), the architect of computer languages (the programmer), and on and on. In short, abstract design is the forte of the architect and coherence is the primary issue. 
</careerdetail>
				<home>INTP's take their mating relationship seriously and usually are faithful and devoted-albeit preoccupied at times. They are not likely to welcome constant social activity or disorganization in the home. In all probability, the mate of an INTP will initiate and manage the social life. If left to his or her own devices the INTP mate will retreat into the world of books and emerge only when physical needs become imperative. INTP's are, however, willing, compliant, and easy to live with, although somewhat forgetful of appointments, anniversaries, and rituals of daily living unless reminded. They may have difficulty expressing their emotions verbally, and the mate of an INTP may believe that he/she is somewhat taken for granted. As a parent, the INTP is devoted; they enjoy children, and are serious about their upbringing. The home of an INTP parent is usually calm, low-key in discipline, but well run and ordered. 
INTP's deal with the environment primarily through intuition, and their strongest quality, the thinking function, remains relatively hidden except in close associations. Therefore, INTP's are often misunderstood, seen as difficult to know, and seldom perceived at their true level of competency. They are inclined to be shy except when with close friends, and their reserve is difficult to penetrate. They are very adaptable until one of their principles is violated. Then INTP's are not adaptable at all! They may have difficulty in being understood by others because they tend to think in a complicated fashion and want to be precise, never redundant in their communications. Because their feeling qualities may be underdeveloped, they may be insensitive to the wants and wishes of others, often unaware of the existence of these wants and wishes. 
</home>
				<midlife>At midlife the INTP might do well to work on increasing awareness of emotional responses, responding to the value preferences of others, and verbalizing to others the INTP's awareness of these values. At midlife one of the tasks of the INTP is to develop an ability to play for play's sake; not to learn something or to somehow improve a skill. Working on the sensual side of his or her nature may provide a source of new pleasure and excitement. </midlife>
				<mates>Why would this abstractionist find the ESFJ "seller" attractive? Think broadly of selling. This amounts to persuading another to receive something of value to the receiver. The seller is essentially caring for the receiver (quite apart from the fact that the receiver pays). This is the essential attitude of the ESFJ seller, and this attitude is perceptible to the receiver (buyer); he feels this nourishing approach. That is what is attractive to the INTP architect-philosopher-the nourishment which anchors him to the real world. 
What attracts the ESFJ "seller"? Here is a person who, like a balloon filled with hydrogen, is likely to escape the earth (in his abstract attitude). He needs to have a string attached so that he can be hauled down to earth now and then. In a sense, he needs to be "sold on reality," so indifferent is he to it. 
The INTP also has a second likely target to attract him: the ENFJ "pedagogue." What is a pedagogue? A catalyst of the growth process, someone who has that uncanny ability to "bring out" the other, to activate the differentiation or "unfolding" process in the learner. All NFs seem to have this capability in some degree and the accompanying desire to exercise it, but the ENFJ seems to have it in abundance. This relationship-the ENFJ-INTP-can be "deep and meaningful" for the former and anchoring in a charismatic way for the latter.
</mates>
				<strengths>•	They feel love and affection for those close to them which is almost childlike in its purity 
•	Generally laid-back and easy-going, willing to defer to their mates 
•	Approach things which interest them very enthusiastically 
•	Richly imaginative and creative 
•	Do not feel personally threatened by conflict or criticism 
•	Usually are not demanding, with simple daily needs 
</strengths>
				<weakness>•	Not naturally in tune with others' feelings; slow to respond to emotional needs 
•	Not naturally good at expressing their own feelings and emotions 
•	Tend to be suspicious and distrusting of others 
•	Not usually good at practical matters, such as money management, unless their work involves these concerns 
•	They have difficulty leaving bad relationships 
•	Tend to "blow off" conflict situations by ignoring them, or else they "blow up" in heated anger 
</weakness>	
			</intp>
		
		<isfj>
				<title>ISFJ - The "Defender"</title>
				<overview>ISFJs are traditional, loyal, quiet and kind. They are very sensitive to other people's needs because they are very observant. They have rich inner thoughts and emotions. They value stability and cultural norms. They are very adept at giving attention to detail. They do not seek positions of authority.</overview>
				<temper>SJs are observant, stable and motivated by a need to maintain security. They are realistic, routinized administrators requiring tasks be completed correctly and that people behave appropriately. SJs make thorough examinations to ensure everything is done according to plan. They make sure no more and no less credit is given than due. When a need arises, they are quick to provide a solution, provided that the need is justified. SJs are not driven by impulse, but rather by concrete fact. By virtue of their reliable, diligent, industrious, persevering nature, they make excellent leaders.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 10%
Male: 5%
Female: 15% 
</population>
				<people>
				Real ISFJ People 
•	Alfred, Lord Tennyson - poet
•	Barbara Bush - American First Lady
•	Jimmy Stewart - actor
•	Kristi Yamaguchi - figure skater
•	Louisa May Alcott - novelist
 	•	Michael Caine - actor
•	Mother Theresa - missionary nun
•	Queen Mary I - Queen of England
•	Robert E. Lee - Army Officer


Fictional ISFJs (Characters) 
•	Bianca - Taming of the Shrew
•	David Copperfield - Charles Dickens character
•	Dr. John H. Watson - Sherlock Holmes
•	Hero - Much Ado About Nothing
•	Joel Barish - Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless Mind	 	•	Melanie Hamilton - Gone With The Wind
•	Navigator Lambert - Alien
•	Ophelia - Hamlet
•	Tonya - Doctor Zhivago

				</people>
				<career>
				ISFJs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Defender/Protector personality. 
•	Artist
•	Accountant
•	Administrator
•	Auditor
•	Administrative Assistant
•	Actor
•	Business Analyst 
•	Bookkeeper
•	Banker
•	Counselor
•	Clerical Supervisor
•	Career Counselor
•	Child Care
•	Church Worker
•	Doctor
•	Designer
•	Entrepreneur
•	Editor
•	Economist
•	Early Childhood Development
•	Gardener	 	•	Health Service
•	Human Resources
•	Homemaker
•	Interior Decorator
•	Librarian
•	Military
•	Marketer
•	Medical Technologist
•	Nurse
•	Office Manager
•	Psychologist/Counselor
•	Paralegal
•	Police
•	Researcher
•	Social Worker
•	Shopkeeper
•	Senior Manager
•	Scientist
•	Typist
•	Trainer
•	Writer

				</career>
				<brief>ISFJs are sympathetic, loyal, considerate and conscientious. They will go to any amount of trouble, when it makes sense to them, to help those in need. ISFJs operate most comfortably in situations where the rules are well defined and where traditions are to be upheld. They focus on providing practical help and services for others and for the organizations they serve. They are often self-effacing in getting the job done, and they are willing to make necessary sacrifices, especially for their families> They are at their best quietly providing assistance and making sure things are in proper order.
 
</brief>
				<living>ISFJ children are conscientious, diligent, and rarely a behaviours problem to their parents or teachers. They like to know what is expected, and then they will dutifully and quietly follow through. In some respects, ISFJs behave like 'perfect children' because they try to please their parents, teachers, and those in authority. They work to meet others' requirements if they are in keeping with the ISFJs' value system, even if this involves a sacrifice on their part. 
Security and routine are very important to ISFJ children. For some ISFJs, this means knowing exactly who is going to be there after school to take charge or who will be invited to play games with them. This need for security and order also applies in school. ISFJ children like to know exactly what they are supposed to do in school and like to feel certain that they have the skills before being called upon. ISFJs need gentle nudging to move beyond their comfort level. They may worry a lot about any number of things. This is apparent even in young children. 
ISFJ children are particularly introspective in the face of adversity. Because of their inward focus, it simply does not occur to them to share their problems with others. They usually have a few close friends whom they are likely to deep as close friends for a lifetime. They often belong to at least one social group. They avoid center stage and contribute willingly in quiet, practical, behind-the-scenes ways. When comfortable, they can radiate their feelings and thoughtful values outward to others. They are often accepted for their kindness and quiet friendliness. They typically select a few special friends and nurture these friendships over long periods of time.
ISFJs shy away from disharmony and try to maintain cooperation at all costs. They may be more cautious and conservative than many of their peers. As young adults, ISFJs set goals with a variety of time frames, ranging from daily goals to long-range ones. If ISFJs have goals of summer vacation trips, they begin to save their money months in advance, gather accurate information on costs, and make lists of what to take. They try to have things in order each day so they will not have to worry too much about tomorrow.
In their careers, ISFJs are often likely to take what comes along; for example, they may accept the first job offer, rather than continue to look for something else and remain in a state of flux. Once in a job, they generally try to make the most of it, since the known is preferable to the unknown. They are loyal employees who diligently work at whatever tasks are given to them.
</living>
				<learning>ISFJs tend to be good students, because they diligently follow through in their work to please their teachers. One aspect of pleasing their teachers is wanting to know their teachers' basic requirements so that they can meet them to the letter of the law. They like having assignments that are clear and that tangibly demonstrate that they have worked hard. They are not likely to feel comfortable with an independent study project, because independent study leaves them too much on their own without a set of definite procedures. 
ISFJs learn best by doing. They like to be involved in their work, perhaps having a work sheet to follow along as the teacher speaks. They may feel comfortable in group activities as long as they are working with a cooperative and task-focused group. They learn well from lectures that are well organized, not too fast paced, and properly sequenced. Lectures that activate their senses or connect to sensory impressions are very rich for ISFJs. They find arguing to be nonproductive and even uncomfortable. They like clear conclusions to their learning. They want to know the right answer. They may need to accept that situations do not always have one answer and learn to feel comfortable with that.
</learning>
				<working>At work, ISFJs contribute loyal, sympathetic, consistent, and considerate service to others. They are know for their kindness and for their willingness to go to any length to help those in need. They take the practical needs of people into account when they do their work, and their strong follow-through skills allow them to carry out organizational goals. They do at least what is expected to them and oftentimes more, without attracting attention to themselves. They are painstaking and responsible with detail and routine, and feel it is important to have the right things in the right places at the right times. 
ISFJs are attracted to occupations that require dedication to others, service, attentiveness to details, and thoroughness. They would rather work with things that they can see - the tangibles that result in something worthwhile for people.
Some occupations are more appealing to ISFJs: bookkeeper, clerical supervisor, curator, family practice physician, health service worker, librarian, medical technologist, nurse, preschool and elementary teacher, typist, and other occupations that provide opportunities for them to meet their need to be of service to others. 
</working>
				<leading>Six out of every one hundred people are ISFJs. Here the primary desire is to be of service and to minister to individual needs. ISFJs carry a sense of history, a sense of continuity with past events and relationships. Traditions and the conservation of resources are valued highly. The least hedonistic of all types, ISFJs believe work is good, play must be earned. ISFJs are willing to work long, long hours. When they undertake a task, it will be completed if at all humanly possible. Adhering to an established way of doing things and doing them well is valued and respected. The efficiency and effectiveness of an established procedure is not often questioned. Procedures dictated by handbooks are law. If others violate or ignore these standard operating procedures, ISFJs are annoyed and irritated, although they may not always display this reaction. Usually, such irritation is turned inward and may be experienced as fatigue and muscle tension. </leading>
				<loving>For the ISFJ, love means security and commitment. Again, like other types, ISFJs tend to fall hard when they fall in love. Because they place a high value on marriage and family, they seek out a partner and feel unfulfilled without one. Marriage and family give ISFJs appropriate outlets for their love. In addition, they provide opportunities for them to meet their need to be of service to others. Because they are willing to give so much, they tend to expect the same sort of response from their mates and may be disappointed when their partners do not comply. However, they are realistic enough to know that they may not get exactly what they want and sometimes must accept their fate quietly.
ISFJs tend to stay in relationships that may not be in their best interests. Because ISFJs are responsible and dutiful, unless they are careful, their partners may take advantage of them. ISFJs are likely to stay in such relationships, because their values of commitment and stability are more important than their individual needs and wants. They may be taken for granted by the very people whom they care and do so much.
In love, ISFJs tend to epitomize people who radiate warmth and good feeling. While ISFJs may not verbalize deep love or the underlying sense of security and commitment that they feel, their contented facial expressions and demeanors illustrate their inner thoughts. They will do whatever is necessary to maintain this state. When the spouse or family of the ISFJ does not meet his or her expectations, the opposite facial expression or demeanor may occur. They are unlikely to talk with others about their disappointments.
When ISFJs are scorned, they are likely to be disappointed, angry, and bitter. However, they keep their feelings inside and often focus on themselves. After her spouse had left her to marry another, one ISFJ commented, 'It wouldn't mean anything if I let the anger out.' Even though she was in pain, she held back her feelings and tears, responding to a strong need to appear composed and stoic to others.
</loving>
				<careerdetail>ISFJs are super-dependable and seldom are happy working in situations where rules are constantly changing. Their major need to be of service to others leads them into occupations such as nursing, teaching, secretarial work, medical practice (especially general practice), librarian work, and middle management administrative jobs. They relate well to people who need them, for example, the sick, the ignorant, students, and the "boss." Much satisfaction comes to them when they are taking care of the needs of another and they render the service gently and helpfully. When the recipient is no longer in need, the relationship may change its character, the ISFJ becoming disinterested. They enjoy assisting the downtrodden and can handle better than other types servility in others. If a situation calls for such behavior on their part, they will show "due respect." ISFJs have an extraordinary sense of responsibility and an outstanding talent for executing routines which call for repeated, sequential procedures; for example, ISFJs make extraordinary secretaries, highly efficient nurses, and dedicated teachers. Speculation and theory do not intrigue ISFJs, who would rather leave the less practical matters to others while remaining themselves practical and down-to-earth. 
ISFJs tend to be devoted and loyal to a boss and tend to identify personally rather than institutionally. They expect others, including the boss, to follow procedures and are distressed and embarrassed when people do not behave as they are supposed to behave. ISFJs often seem to feel personally responsible for seeing to it that people in an institution or business carry out established rules and routines. They often are aware of status given by titles, environment, offices, and the like and can use this to advantage. They are aware of the value of material resources and abhor the squandering or misuse of these resources. To save, to put something aside against an unpredictable future, to prepare for emergencies-these are important actions. 
ISFJs may experience some discomfort when placed in positions of authority over others and may tend to try to do everything themselves rather than insist that others do their jobs. As a result, ISFJs are frequently overworked. 
</careerdetail>
				<home>ISFJs are devoted to mate and family and usually are excellent homemakers. The home of an ISFJ is likely to be well kept inside and out. Interior and exterior are meticulously maintained and appointed in the traditional manner. As a parent, the ISFJ expects the children to conform to the rules of society and has a feeling of personal responsibility to see to it that these rules are honored. An ISFJ is apt to find the putting on of airs as offensive and tends to prefer modest, quiet friends rather than more boisterous ones. For the ISFJ, people should behave according to their position in life, and the ISFJ may be annoyed by others who act either above or below their social or economic station. 
The ISFJ female often displays a flair for making the interior of the home attractive in a time-honored style, provides attractive, nourishing meals, and maintains the environment in a neat and orderly state. To the ISFJ male and female, the home territory is important to own and to preserve. 
While ISFJs are super-dependable, they may be fascinated by and attracted to the irresponsible, the lush, the glutton. Many ISFJs marry alcoholics and then proceed to conduct a rescue-rejection game without end, with the rescuing phase taking the guise of an attempt to reform. Occasionally an ISFJ mother may reveal a tendency to find humor in the "waywardness" of a son, while raising her daughters to respect traditions and to do the Right Thing at the Right Time; always. 
ISFJs are frequently misunderstood and undervalued. Their contributions often are taken for granted, and the ISFJ as well is too often taken for granted. This can cause an ISFJ to harbor feelings of resentment, and this bottled up emotion can gnaw inwardly, causing the ISFJ much undeserved suffering. 
</home>
				<midlife>At midlife ISFJs might want to develop the thinking function more fully. For example, a study of human behavior might be one avenue that ISFJs can find fascinating at this time. They also might practice being in the limelight occasionally, more aggressively claiming recognition for the many contributions they have been making so quietly for so long. They could even practice the art of accepting service from others, allowing themselves to be pampered a bit, and cutting down on the services they provide to others, no matter who those others may be. </midlife>
				<mates>The conserving nature of the ISFJ nicely complemented the iconoclasm of the ENTP "inventor." There would seem to be an even greater affinity in the mating of ISFJ with the ESTP "promoter." The dashing, glittering, wheel-and-deal capers of the ESTP calls for anchorage. The ESTP tends to have "high" periods during which there is a whirlwind of euphoric activity. The ISFJ provides, and likes to provide, a place to "crash" for our high-rolling entrepreneur. Usually the ISFJ finds employment that requires this ministering, nursing, helping sort of activity. Even so, he or she doesn't seem to mind doing the same thing at home, and so tends to get burdened with a bit more duty than others. If the spouse does not show appreciation now and then for this overtime work, he may be in for an increase in physical complaints and "worries" on the part of the unappreciated ISFJ.</mates>
				<strengths>•	Warm, friendly and affirming by nature 
•	Service-oriented, wanting to please others 
•	Good listeners 
•	Will put forth lots of effort to fulfill their duties and obligations 
•	Excellent organizational capabilities 
•	Good at taking care of practical matters and daily needs 
•	Usually good (albeit conservative) at handling money 
•	Take their commitments seriously, and seek lifelong relationships 
</strengths>
				<weakness>•	Don't pay enough attention to their own needs 
•	May have difficulty branching out into new territory 
•	Extreme dislike of conflict and criticism 
•	Unlikely to express their needs, which may cause pent-up frustrations to build inside 
•	Have difficulty leaving a bad relationship 
•	Have difficulty moving on after the end of a relationship 
</weakness>	
			</isfj>
		
		
		
		<isfp>
				<title>ISFP - The "Artist"</title>
				<overview>ISFPs are artistic, creative, loyal and sensitive. They have a keen appreciation for beauty because of their highly developed senses. They are easy to get along with and live in the "here and now". ISFPs are adaptable, caring, independent and like to contribute to the well-being of others. They are typically hard to get to know.</overview>
				<temper>SPs are observant, experiential and primarily driven by sensation. They are flexible, aesthetically-aware, "here and now" people that, with hardly a moment's notice, will go where their senses lead. SPs naturally make an effort (with a realistic approach) not to miss an opportunity that may prove to be thrilling, pleasing or otherwise valuable. SPs are are laid back, open-minded and love to feel alive. They have a tendency toward athletics and anything that involves creating or crafting.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 9%
Male: 8%
Female: 10% 
</population>
				<people>
				Real ISFP People 
•	Auguste Rodin - French sculptor
•	Barbara Streisand - singer
•	Brooke Shields - actress
•	Dan Quayle - American Vice President
•	Doris Day - actress, singer
•	Fred Astaire - actor, dancer
•	Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis - First Lady (Wife of J.F.K.)
•	John Travolta - actor
 	•	Kevin Costner - actor
•	Liberace - entertainer
•	Marie Antoinette - Archduchess of Austria, Queen of France
•	Millard Fillmore - American President
•	Paul Gauguin - artist
•	Steven Spielberg - filmmaker
•	Ulysses S. Grant - American President
•	Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart - composer


Fictional ISFPs (Characters) 
•	Gina Montana
•	Manny Ribera - Scarface
 	•	Susan Hunsecker - Sweet Smell of Success

				</people>
				<career>
				
ISFPs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Artist/Creator personality. 
•	Artist
•	Administrative Assistant
•	Clerical Supervisor
•	Composer
•	Church Worker
•	Counselor
•	Child Care
•	Carpenter
•	Chef
•	Designer
•	Dental Staff
•	Editor
•	Early Childhood Development
•	Forest Ranger
•	Homemaker
•	Librarian
•	Musician	 	•	Mechanic
•	Medical Staff
•	Nurse
•	Naturalist
•	Psychologist
•	Physical Therapist
•	Pediatrician
•	Personal Service Worker
•	Social Worker
•	Trainer
•	Technical Specialist
•	Teacher
•	Veterinarian
•	Waiter/Waitress
•	Writer
•	X-Ray Technician

				</career>
				<brief>ISFPs are gentle and compassionate, open and flexible. They are considerate of others and do not force their views and opinions on them. They often focus on meeting others' needs, especially those who are less fortunate. Having a quite, modest, self-effacing style, ISFPs avoid disagreements and seek harmony with people as well as with nature. They enjoy life's precious moments and often add a touch of beauty to the environments where they spend their time. They are at their best ensuing others' well-being.</brief>
				<living>ISFP children are pleasant, quiet, and kind. Their talents may be easy to overlook because they shun the spotlight and do not have a strong need to demonstrate their strengths to others. They may be particularly drawn to people, animals, and plants who need the gentle care that ISFPs provide. 
ISFP children generally relate well with others and tend to have friends because they are easy to like. They are interested in others's feelings and notice particularly when disharmony exists. It is quite difficult for ISFPs to see their friends in conflict with one another. When this occurs, they will try to help ease the disagreements by playing the role of peacemaker.
ISFP children notice and attend to the delights of the senses. Often they will make special gifts for people whom they particularly like. These gifts are usually unique and original, with much attention paid to color, line, texture, and form. They are often very conscious of the internal sensations in their bodies. They tend to be aware of what their body will and will not do. 
As teenagers, ISFPs may blend into the woodwork because they are quiet and unassuming. They are oriented toward deeply felt personal values, and they may find themselves on the outside of social groups if the groups do not share the same values.
In adult life, ISFPs work quietly, often behind the scenes, helping individuals meet their goals and dreams. They like a life of action and interaction, and often choose careers that allow them to exercise their ability to see the needs of the moment and respond quickly. They have little desire to impress others or to impose their will. However, they can be gently and persistently persuasive if they believe some action is in another's best interest.
ISFPs enjoy their friends and their families, and spend time nurturing their relationships. They bring an air of spontaneity and easy acceptance to all they meet and are rarely quickly judgmental. Only when people do something grossly out of line will the anger of ISFPs surface. They will then stand firmly against the infraction to support the victim.
</living>
				<learning>ISFPs learn best through hands-on experience. They may not be as interested in traditional academic subjects as some other types. They prefer application and practicality rather than studying the theoretical and only potentially useful. Making drawings, constructing miniature models, or using other direct representations to master the subject matter are appealing activities for them. They dislike structure and institutional settings that take away their spontaneity and freedom. They want their learning to be relevant to what is going on in their world. They have less patience with conceptual and abstract learning.
ISFPs enjoy learning subjects that relate to helping and knowing about people. They may be easily overlooked in the classroom unless the teacher has recognized their special ways of learning and their unique contributions. Encouragement helps draw out ISFPs.
</learning>
				<working>At work, ISFPs contribute by attending to the practical facts relating to the needs of people and all living things in their environments. They can infuse a particular knod of joy into cooperative nature. Because they pay attention to the humanistic aspects of the organization, they act in ways that ensure others' well-being. People enjoy ISFPs because they bring understanding yet adaptability to the realities of their work.
ISFPs enjoy occupations that allow them to be flexible and adaptable and to meet the here-and-now needs of others. They enjoy responding to the moment and choose work where they can offer practical, specific help in times of difficulty.
Some occupations are more appealing to ISFPs: Bookkeeper, carpenter, personal service worker, clerical supervisor and secretary, dental and medical staffers, food service worker, nurse, mechanic, physical therapist, X-ray technician, and other occupations that allow them to provide gentle help to all living things.
</working>
				<leading>ISFPs are found in about 6 percent of the general population. The best name for this type is free spirit, for they have an intense need for freedom. The simple rural life, life in the wilderness, the tribal/communal life-all these may call them. Their need for social interaction, however, is not as great as that of the type they most resemble, the ESFP. So an ISFP may forgo all social ties of any duration to preserve the freedom to wander. The lyric, "I was born under a wandering star...", might capture the spirit of the ISFP in this respect. The flower children of the 1960's may have been largely ISFPs, though the ESFPs also seem attracted to communing with others. 
ISFPs also resemble INFPs in needing to achieve intensity of feeling. The focus, however, with the ISFPs seems to be more on the sensuous side than the meaningful side. The ISFP is orgastic, in the sense, demanding of life that it provide the excitement and pleasure of drinking deeply at the Dionysian well. Not revelry (that is the forte of the ESFP) but experience is what attracts the ISFP to these kinds of activities. Music, like wine, is incorporated and internalized, and the introverted nature of the ISFP requires this internalization. There is a reason why the flower became the symbol for what the flower children wanted: Flowers are warm, alive, sweet, colorful, rhythmic, natural, absolute, needing no statement, no interpretation-a pure being-in-self. 
ISFPs are not articulate. They communicate through action. They do not verbalize their meanings, but, for example, offer a lovely flower and a smile. Their actions speak of the pastoral and the bucolic. 
</leading>
				<loving>For the ISFP, love means devotion, loyalty, care, humor, and consideration for the needs and wants of the loved one. When ISFPs first fall in love, they may feel consumed by it. They may become naive and focus entirely on the romance of it - 'falling in love with love.' Future worries are cast aside in favor of the present realities. ISFPs may ignore all else in order to experience their love life most fully. Doing this can leave them vulnerable to the whims of others.
Because being loved and cared for is important to ISFPs, they make sure that relationships are nourished so that they can continue to grow. When They are in love, they find a multitude of ways to show their affection and their appreciation for the other person. Often ISFPs will go so far as to rearrange their careers, start or stop working, move geographically, or make other changes to maintain their relationships. 
The friends, family members, and even pets of the ISFPs' partners become important to them as well. ISFPs take it upon themselves to make their environments places where there is the potential to have a harmonious existence for all. 
In their desire to please others, some ISFPs may not be confident enough to speak up for themselves about what they need. If the relationship turns sour, the ISFP may believe that it was caused by something that they personally did. They may assume more of the blame than is necessary. When they are scorned, they may retreat and repeatedly analyse the situation internally. When they do face reality and finally let go, they can become more assertive and self-directed in the resumption of their lives.
</loving>
				<careerdetail>They do not seek philosophy or science or literature. These are too distant from life for the ISFPs. They seek, rather, the pounding surf, the river, the forest, the ship, the truck, the racing car, the horse, the potter's wheel, the hoist, the bulldozer-some kind of action where they can keep their fingers on the pulse of life. </careerdetail>
				<home>It is not that people are unimportant to the ISFP-indeed they are-but people are more the framework for the activities of the ISFP, providing a shadowy background. Perhaps this type is the least understood of all the types-and yet often the most envied. They are so fiercely independent and insistent that they live in and for the moment, in action, fully savoring the urges they feel and discharge, that others often find them difficult to comprehend or understand. Gaugin, perhaps, provides a prototype of the ISFP as he walked away from his affluent position in society, off to Tahiti to an unknown future, and without a backward glance! </home>
				<midlife>At midlife ISFPs may be subject to strong temptation to follow Gaugin's lead, to abandon their current style of life, and sacrifice home, children, and mate for the lure of the unknown bucolic life. The cost of following this impulse must, of course, be reckoned. If the ISFP has not found in work a source of pleasure which continues past midlife, he or she may want to opt for an early retirement and enter into a new career where their need to be close to nature can be satisfied. </midlife>
				<mates>Pursuit of two themes-closeness to nature and artistic activity-places the ISFP quite a distance from the utilitarian outlook. Yet it is precisely that outlook that seems to attract the bucolic spirit. The opposite on the N side is the ENTJ "fieldmarshal," the most militant of all types in his desire to run things. ISFP is most likely to become a pacifist or environmentalist, and yet also is likely to seek out the person who is temperamentally suited to tactical leadership, military or otherwise. ISFP is likewise attracted to the ESTJ "administrator," the person temperamentally suited to be "in charge" of establishments. Note that the person most likely to deprecate the establishment is attracted to the head of an establishment. It is rather doubtful, should an ISFP actually marry an ENTJ or ESTJ, that there is any intent or desire to change the spouse into a pastoral. Of all types, ISFP is most likely to "let be" whoever or whatever. It seems more likely that the latter provides a kind of anchorage to enterprise and to civilization.</mates>
				<strengths>•	Warm, friendly and affirming by nature 
•	Usually optimistic 
•	Good listeners 
•	Good at dealing with practical day-to-day concerns 
•	Flexible and laid-back, usually willing to defer to their mates 
•	Their love of aesthetic beauty and appreciation for function makes them likely to have attractive, functional homes 
•	Take their commitments seriously, and seek lifelong relationships 
•	Likely to value and respect other's personal space 
•	Likely to enjoy showing their affection through acts and deeds 
•	Sensuous and earthy 
</strengths>
				<weakness>•	Not good at long-range financial (or other) planning 
•	Extreme dislike of conflict and criticism 
•	Focused on enjoying the present moment, they may appear lazy or slow-moving at times 
•	Need to have their own space, and dislike having it invaded 
•	May be slow to show their affection with words 
•	Tendency to hold back their thoughts and feelings, unless drawn out 
•	May become overly cynical and practical 
</weakness>	
			</isfp>
		
		
		
		
		<istj>
				<title>ISTJ - The "Examiner"</title>
				<overview>ISTJs are responsible, loyal and hard working. They have an acute sense of right and wrong and work hard at preserving established norms and traditions. Because of their deep sense of duty they are dedicated to everything they do and are very dependable. ISTJs care deeply for those closest to them.</overview>
				<temper>SJs are observant, stable and motivated by a need to maintain security. They are realistic, routinized administrators requiring tasks be completed correctly and that people behave appropriately. SJs make thorough examinations to ensure everything is done according to plan. They make sure no more and no less credit is given than due. When a need arises, they are quick to provide a solution, provided that the need is justified. SJs are not driven by impulse, but rather by concrete fact. By virtue of their reliable, diligent, industrious, persevering nature, they make excellent leaders.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 12%
Male: 15.5%
Female: 8.5% 
</population>
				<people>
				Real ISTJ People 
•	Andrew Johnson - American President
•	Benjamin Harrison - American President
•	Evander Holyfield - boxer
•	George H. W. Bush - American President
•	George Washington - American President
•	Harry Truman - American President	 	•	Herbert Hoover - American President
•	Jack Webb - actor, producer
•	Jackie Joyner-Kersee - athlete (heptathlon)
•	Queen Elizabeth II - Queen of England
•	Thomas - Christ's Apostle
•	Warren Buffet - investor, businessman


Fictional ISTJs (Characters) 
•	Angel Eyes - The Good, the Bad and the Ugly
•	Bruce Wayne - Batman Begins
•	Cliff Clavin - Cheers
•	Dallas - Alien
•	Darth Vader - Star Wars
•	Eeyore - Winnie the Pooh
•	Evelyn Cross Mulwray - Chinatown
•	Frankie Dunn - Eastwood in Million Dollar Baby
•	Fred Mertz - I Love Lucy

				</people>
				<career>
				ISTJs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Examiner/Protector personality. 
•	Accountant
•	Auditor
•	Administrator
•	Computer Specialist
•	Computer Programmer
•	Doctor
•	Detective
•	Dentist
•	Executive
•	Electrician
•	Financial Officer
•	Judge
•	Librarian	 	•	Lawyer/Attorney
•	Military Leader
•	Mechanical Engineer
•	Math Teacher
•	Marketer
•	Manager
•	Police
•	Scientist
•	Systems Analyst 
•	Steelworker
•	Technician
•	Technical Specialist

				</career>
				<brief>ISTJs are systematic, painstaking, thorough, and hardworking. They get the job done and complete it on schedule. They are serious and sincere in whatever they do. They work well within a structure, follow the hierarchy, and are particularly strong and careful in keeping track of facts and details. They are cautious, generally seeking to maintain the status quo. They are at their best getting things to the right place at the right time. They honor their commitments.</brief>
				<living>ISTJ children are serious, dutiful and reserved. They like a great deal of order and structure. In new situations or with new people, they are quite cautious and perhaps uncomfortable. They prefer familiar friends to new ones and select friends carefully. When they know what is expected, they act more at ease with others. They tend to enjoy traditional childhood activities. When they feel comfortable, they also enjoy group activities such as scouting, with doing their duty and serving their country fitting their world view of what is right. They like to be read to and appreciate hearing stories as well as the pictures that accompany them. They particularly like stories in which good triumphs over the forces of evil.
ISTJ children, perhaps more than others, enjoy having a schedule to follow and, even as kids, show a propensity for getting work-related responsibilities out of the way before they play. 
ISTJ teenagers are down-to-earth types who seek to do the appropriate thing at the appropriate time. If they date, they tend to single out one person and date steadily. ISTJs may be chosen to lead school activities. They generally believe that one should earn one's keep. Even as children, they may request chores that help the family. As teenagers, they tend to have part-time jobs. They money they earn tends to be used for the important practical things in their lives. They do not like to ask their parents for money.
As young adults, ISTJs begin their career training early and find it hard to understand people who start and education but do not complete it. They believe that dropping out is irresponsible. They complete what they start. They may choose large and stable organizations in which they hope to find security and an opportunity to prove their worth. They are particularly realistic about their skills and needs, and prefer to learn the basics before risking something beyond their capabilities. Slow and steady on an unambiguous course is the way ISTJs prefer to navigate through life. As a result, they may select undergraduate programs in college that lead directly to employment.
ISTJs have a need to 'do right' with what they've been given, safeguarding traditions of the family and of the community. They often will take on extra personal responsibilities in order to maintain what they believe is important. 
ISTJs may stay with a job or company they do not particularly like because they tend to regard financial well-being as very important and are willing to do without things, including emotional gratification, so that they can provide for their retirement. They worry particularly about being dependent on others for their needs and work hard to avoid that state.
</living>
				<learning>ISTJs learn best and apply themselves most carefully in subject areas that are practical and useful. They are diligent and persevering in their studies. As learners, ISTJs tend to need materials, directions, and teachers to be precise and accurate if they are to trust the information that is presented. They prefer concrete and useful applications and will tolerate theory only if it leads to these ends.
ISTJs like learning activities that allow them time to reflect and to think. If the material is too easy or appears to be too enjoyable, the ISTJ may be skeptical of its merit. Because of their practical bent, they believe that work is work and play is play. Therefore, their preferred learning environment is task oriented, starts and stops on time, and has clear and precise assignment.
</learning>
				<working>At work, ISTJs get things done on a timely basis. They honor deadlines, and they believe in thoroughness. A half-finished joy is not a joy well done. They established procedures and schedules, and are uncomfortable with those who do not do the same. ISTJs put duty before pleasure. As long as they can fulfil their responsibilities, they feel useful and thereby satisfied. Their work does not have to be fun, but it has to count toward something productive. ISTJs believe that vacations are something that one takes only when work has been accomplished; thus, at times they do not take vacations even when they could and should. 
ISTJs prefer work settings that contain hard-working people who are focused on facts, details and results. They want structure, order, and some privacy for concentration without interruptions. They like tangible products and concrete accomplishments. They want to be secure and to be rewarded for their solid accomplishments at a steady pace.
They pride themselves on their organization, yet often think it is still not quite good enough. They usually have a great deal of factual information to deal with, and they take pains to properly label and file it. They put emphasis on cross-referencing and easy retrievals. A hands-on approach is important to ISTJs, because they make use of the actual or the visual memory of the concrete data in their hands. 
ISTJs prefer occupations that require thoroughness, accuracy, perseverance, and follow-through. They would rather work in situations in which they can see concrete, tangible results. Accountant, auditor, dentist, electrician, first-line supervisor, math teacher, mechanical engineer, police supervisor, steelworker, technician, and other occupations are particularly attractive to ISTJs.
</working>
				<leading>While not directly seeking leadership positions, ISTJs are often placed in such roles. They build a reputation for reliable, stable, and consistent performance that causes others to select them to lead. ISTJs use their past experience and their factual knowledge in their decision making. They respect traditional, hierarchical approaches and seek to reward those who get the job done by following the rules and standard operating procedures. In their view, rewards should go to outstanding contributors who do not violate the rules while completing their work. ISTJs are more task oriented than relationship oriented in their style. </leading>
				<loving>For the ISTJ, love means commitment, steadiness, and consistency. ISTJs expect themselves and their mates to be responsible, practical, and dependable. When in a relationship, they behave appropriately for what the situation or their role demands. For example, if the relationship is in the courting stage, the ISTJ will exhibit courting behaviors, such as giving boxes of candy, red roses and presents. These are worthwhile and important traditions to uphold and observe because they give direct evidence of commitment.
When ISTJs give their word and are ready to settle down, they follow through. Because they are dutiful, they expect their partners to behave in a similar fashion. They offer their partners stability and security. They do sensible things for the relationship, such as paying the bill and making household repairs.
ISTJs may stay in poor relationships out of their sense of duty, even when it is to their benefit to leave. They prefer the certainty of the current relationship to any future unknowns. When feeling scorned, ISTJs may not let their partners or others know it. Because they focus internally and because the facts all support the conclusion that the relationship is over, ISTJs may feel it redundant to express to their partners or others what is going on. When it seems clear to the partners that the relationship really is over, ending it is the practical thing to do. However, when a decision to part is not so clear to ISTJs, they may continue to rehash the past rather than look to the future and other relationships.
</loving>
				<careerdetail>ISTJ's interest in thoroughness, details, justice, practical procedures, and smooth flow of personnel and materiel leads this type to occupations where these preferences are useful. For example, ISTJs make excellent bank examiners, auditors, accountants, or tax examiners. Investments in securities are likely to interest this type, particularly investments in blue-chip securities. ISTJs are not likely to take chances either with their own or others' money. 
ISTJs can handle difficult, detailed figures and make sense of them. They communicate a message of reliability and stability, which often makes them excellent supervisors of, for example, a ward in a hospital, a library, or a business operation. They would be capable of handling the duties of a mortician, a legal secretary, or a law researcher. High-school teachers of business, home economics, physical education, and the physical sciences are ISTJs, as are top-ranking officers of the Women's Army Corps. Often this type seem to have ice in their veins, for people fail to see an ISTJ's vulnerability to criticism. 
ISTJs are patient with their work and with procedures within an institution, although not always patient with the individual goals of people in that institution. ISTJs will see to it that resources are delivered when and where they are supposed to be; materiel will be in the right place at the right time. And ISTJs would prefer that this be the case with people too. 
</careerdetail>
				<home>As a husband or wife, the ISTJ is a pillar of strength. Just as this type honors business contracts, so do they honor the marriage contract. Loyal and faithful mates, they take responsibilities to children and mate seriously, giving lifelong commitment to these. Duty is a word the ISTJ understands. The male ISTJ sees himself as the breadwinner of the family, although he can accept a working wife-as long as responsibilities to children are not shirked. The male ISTJ's concept of masculinity is patriarchal, and both female and male ISTJs make steady, dependable partners. The female ISTJ may abandon the frivolous for the sensible and may not always deepen her sensuality. 
As parents, ISTJs are consistent in handling children, and the rules of the family are made clear. A rebellious, nonconforming child may have a difficult time, however, with an ISTJ parent-and vice versa. As a child, the ISTJ is apt to be obedient and a source of pleasure to parents and teachers. 
Although ISTJs are outstandingly practical and sensible, they can marry people who are thoroughly irresponsible, with the marriage developing into a relationship more parent to child that adult to adult. The ISTJ fluctuates from being rescuer to reformer of the wayward mate. The marriage then becomes a lifelong game: On one side, there is Irresponsibility, Promise of Reform, Brief Period of Reform, and Irresponsibility again; on the ISTJ's part, the cycle is Disapproval, Rescue, Scolding, Forgiveness, Acceptance of Promise To Do Better, and on and on. This pattern often is seen when an ISTJ marries an alcoholic and enters a life of caretaking punctuated by periods of anger and rejection. Somehow, although ISTJs can accept periodic fickleness and selfishness in significant others, they do not see this kind of behavior as acceptable in themselves. 
ISTJs have a distaste for and distrust of fanciness in speech, dress, or home. The ostentacious is abhorred, and a neat, orderly, and functional home and work environment is preferred. Durability of furnishings are of primary concern, aesthetics given slim consideration. The clothes of an ISTJ tend to be practical and durable rather than in the latest style or luxurious. "No nonsense" in both food and clothes seems characteristic of this type who tend not to be attracted by exotic food and beverages, or places. 
The male ISTJ may enjoy stag, men only parties and use a different sort of language when only men are present. The yearly hunting or fishing trip as a male ritual is often a part of recreation for an ISTJ. More than the female, the ISTJ male is apt to be involved in community service organizations that transmit traditional values to the young, such as Boy Scouting. They understand and appreciate the contributions these groups make in preserving the national heritage. Along with the SJ's, the ISTJ takes particular delight in festive occasions held in the context of rituals, for example, weddings, holiday feasts, and birthdays. At work, the ISTJ is apt to see the holiday office party as a necessary nuisance and would be likely to participate and enjoy these events. 
</home>
				<midlife>At midlife ISTJs might develop an interest in collecting art objects and indulge themselves in using time to craft objects which have utilitarian purpose. ISTJs might enjoy relaxing physically and psychologically from a decision-making role, perhaps even schooling themselves to allow others to wait on them. They might want to increase their capacity to engage in frivolity and, for a change, let someone else worry about the future. Continuing to put off vacations, wanted luxuries, rest periods, and other long-overdue activities could well be abandoned in favor of some self-indulgence. </midlife>
				<mates>Here is the paragon of insurance, preparation, and consolidation-a person with a strong desire to be trusted. Small wonder that he looks upon accounting, banking, and securities with a benevolent eye. Try to imagine him married to one of his own kind: Two Rocks of Gibraltar, each steadfastly tempering the other's steadfast tempering! We can safely guess that this sort of relationship wouldn'ts work very well. 
The attraction, rather, is for the "entertainer," for the vivacity and sparkle of ESFP, the opposite of ISTJ. ISTJ is the ultimate saver who is fascinated by, and frequently marries, the ultimate spender! Here is complementarily to the nth degree! Just as often, ISTJ finds his or her opposite on the intuitive side: the ENFP. Perhaps he senses in the ENFP's desire to spread the word something similar to the ESFP's desire to put on a show. Certainly the vivacity and sparkle is apparent in both, an attribute which must be quite enchanting to the sober and careful ISTJ.
</mates>
				<strengths>•	Honor their commitments 
•	Take their relationship roles very seriously 
•	Usually able to communicate what's on their minds with precision 
•	Good listeners 
•	Extremely good (albeit conservative) with money 
•	Able to take constructive criticism well 
•	Able to tolerate conflict situations without emotional upheaval 
•	Able to dole out punishment or criticism when called for
</strengths>
				<weakness>•	Tendency to believe that they're always right 
•	Tendency to get involved in "win-lose" conversations 
•	Not naturally in-tune with what others are feeling 
•	Their value for structure may seem rigid to others 
•	Not likely to give enough praise or affirmation to their loved ones 

</weakness>	
			</istj>
		
		
		<istp>
				<title>ISTP - The "Craftsman"</title>
				<overview>ISTPs are adventurous and independent. They like to figure out how things work. They have great mechanical and technical skills. They live in the "here and now" which makes them adaptable and spontaneous. They like to keep busy and are action-oriented. ISTPs thrive on new and exciting situations.</overview>
				<temper>SPs are observant, experiential and primarily driven by sensation. They are flexible, aesthetically-aware, "here and now" people that, with hardly a moment's notice, will go where their senses lead. SPs naturally make an effort (with a realistic approach) not to miss an opportunity that may prove to be thrilling, pleasing or otherwise valuable. SPs are are laid back, open-minded and love to feel alive. They have a tendency toward athletics and anything that involves creating or crafting.  </temper>
				<population>Total: 9%
Male: 11.5%
Female: 6.5% 
</population>
				<people>
				Real ISTP People 
•	Alan Shepherd - astronaut
•	Antony Worrall Thompson - British celebrity chef
•	Bruce Lee - martial artist, actor
•	Burt Reynolds - actor
•	Charles Bronson - actor
•	Chuck Yeager - U.S. Air Force officer
•	Clint Eastwood - actor and director
•	Frank Zappa - guitarist
•	James Dean - actor
 	•	John Malkovich - actor
•	Judy Finnigan - British TV star
•	Katharine Hepburn - actress
•	Keith Richards - English guitarist/singer
•	Michael Jordan - athelete (basketball, baseball)
•	Robin Cook - British politician
•	Tom Cruise - actor
•	Zachary Taylor - American President


Fictional ISTPs (Characters) 
•	Archibald "Harry" Tuttle - Brazil movie
•	Blondie - The Good, the Bad and the Ugly
•	Boba Fett - Star Wars
•	Brett - Alien
•	Butch Coolidge - Pulp Fiction
•	Elvira Hancock - Scarface	 	•	Han Solo - Star Wars
•	Hedda Gabler - Hedda Gabler play (Ibsen)
•	John Milner - American Grafitti
•	Maggie Fitzgerald - Million Dollar Baby
•	Verna - Miller's Crossing

				</people>
				<career>
				ISTPs are often happy with the following jobs which tend to match well with the Craftsman/Creator personality. 
•	Athlete
•	Business Analyst 
•	Computer Specialist
•	Construction Worker
•	Computer Programmer
•	Carpenter
•	Driver
•	Detective
•	Dental Hygienist
•	Engineer
•	Entrepreneur
•	Electrical Engineer
•	Forensic Pathologist
•	Farmer
•	Firefighter
•	Human Resources	 	•	Marketer
•	Motorcyclist
•	Military
•	Mechanic
•	Project Manager
•	Police
•	Probation Officer
•	Pilot
•	Paramedic/EMT
•	Steelworker
•	Systems Analyst 
•	Scientist
•	Sales Representative
•	Transportation Operative
•	Technical Specialist

				</career>
				<brief>ISTPs are realists who apply expediency and reasoning as they manage and adapt to situations. They are aware of what is going on in the environment and are able to respond quickly to the actual facts, making sure the odds of success are in their favor. They do not like to be tied down and will feel hamstrung when they must operate within tight structures and schedules. They are able to anticipate immediate, practical needs in situations and to present a logical, straightforward plan for meeting those needs. They are at their best in situations that require immediate attention.</brief>
				<living>ISTP children want life to be logical, flexible and action oriented. While they like hands-on activities, they also may want to stand aside and observe what is taking place. They are especially observant of what makes things tick and may take apart a toy to see its inner workings. They are curious and are great gatherers of data and detail. They rarely forget what they have noticed about places and things. They are aware of flaws and try to correct them. ISTP children become very absorbed in their hobbies. 
ISTP teenager may have several close friends but generally are not social butterflies. They relate to others by sharing detailed information about one of their interests or sharing in physical activities that involve a measure of risk. They like sports in which they can challenge themselves and master specific techniques and strategies. 
As young adults, ISTPs tend to follow a path of least resistance when thinking about their careers. They usually don't like planning ahead because they think that things don't turn out like the plan. They relax their brain while everyone else is busy using theirs to plan. 
ISTPs are pragmatists and gamblers who play each hand as it is dealt. As a result, they are able to take advantage of opportunities as they arise. In adult life, ISTPs are fairly laid back and mellow. They do not impose much structure on themselves or others. Because they retain and use detail for logical ends, they are often recognized by their employers as people who do well with the careful and precise understanding of factual data. 
Most ISTPs, when questioned about their careers, reveal that they would love to have more time and income to pursue their interests full-time. Because retirement may allow ISTPs to further pursue their work as well as leisure interests unhampered by time demands, it is a very desirable state for them. If their work is interesting, they may resist retirement because their work is a key element in their lives. When their work does not provide them with enough enjoyment and challenge, they may try to arrange things so that they can retire early and thus obtain more time to enjoy their leisure pursuits.
</living>
				<learning>ISTPs learn best when they can observe first-hand in a one-to-one situation. They are particularly fond of subjects that have a logical basis; mastering certain rules or principles allows them to efficiently work with the subject matter. They like individual projects that require them to solve problems systematically.
ISTPs prefer to learn alone, at their own rate and in their own time frame. Because they are able to assimilate a great amount of detail in areas that interest them, they usually do well in those areas. ISTPs earn their best grades when it is necessary to accurately report facts and data. They are impatient with theorectical subjects and like their learning to be directed toward concrete and practical outcomes.
Teachers are not particularly important to ISTPs in the overall scheme, unless they can show ISTPs how to do things more easily. When the teacher obstructs or gets in the way of something ISTPs want to learn, they may ignore or go around the teacher. The formal or traditional school setting is not as important to ISTPs as is the opportunity to increase their own practical knowledge. Nontraditional programs or approaches often attract ISTPs, especially when they can learn about things that they see as vital and central to their interests.
</learning>
				<working>At work, ISTPs contribute their realistic and logical way of meeting situational requirements. They can see the easiest and most expedient route to completing a task, and they do not waste their effort on unnecessary things. They often act as trouble shooters, rising to meet the needs of the occasion. Since many ISTPs have a natural bent in technical areas, they may often function as 'walking encyclopedias' of technical information. 
ISTPs prefer a work setting that is project oriented and unconstrained by rules. They want a chance to be active, independent problem solvers. They do not like routing but want the opportunity to be somewhat inventive in meeting current needs.
The ISTP organizing style is based on expediency and quick application of information. They often organize their hobbies or collections and make a game of finding the best way to arrange things. 
ISTPs prefer flexibility and impersonal dealings with others. Because they often have a technical orientation, they prefer to work in an environment that produces a practical product. They pay attention to the organization's hierarchy only to the point of learning how to bypass or go around it if it stands in their way. ISTPs may have mastered the details of the organization but may rebel if it is too rigid.
Carpenter, construction worker, dental hygienist, electrical engineer, farmer, mechanic, military personnel, probation officer, steel worker, transportation operative, and other occupations that allow them to use their ability to act expediently are generally attractive to an ISTP.
</working>
				<leading>The ISTP leadership style is one of leading through action, by setting an example. They respond quickly when trouble is at hand. They operate logically from their internal ruling principles. They give their staff the necessary information to do their jobs, allowing them to complete their work in their own fashion. They prefer to be managed loosely and with minimal supervision, and they manage others in a similar fashion.</leading>
				<loving>For the ISTP, love means being responsive yet realistic. ISTPs seek partners who either are willing to allow them to have their necessary freedom or who will participate in these activities with them. They may introduce their partners to their interests if they are ones that they want to share. When this is the case, they will acquaint their loved one with all the facts and details of their interest.
When falling in love, ISTPs are very attentive to small things that might be enjoyed by their partners, surprising them with those particular gifts. They would rather show their feelings through their actions than verbalize them. They are not likely to discuss their feelings about their relationships with their partners because they believe that the experiences that they have had together will speak for their feelings. Feelings are discuss only when necessary.
When scorned, ISTPs are not likely to share hurt feelings with the external world. If the couple still has some interests in common, ISTPs may maintain the relationship with the loved one, but on a different plane. They do not give up easily on their relationships, however, unless the weight of the factual evidence convinces them to do so. When the relationship is actually over, they are usually not vindictive. They see the end of the relationship as a concrete fact about which it does little good to worry. They can therefore move on to new experiences.
</loving>
				<careerdetail>For ISTPs knowledge for the sake of knowledge is not as important as the use of knowledge in providing a foundation for activity. They are not particularly interested in acquiring advanced levels of education through formal channels, preferring to gain expertise through experience and action. In recreation, they are involved in sports, either as participant or spectator or both. Probably 50 percent of the surfers are ISTPs, for surfing requires a willingness to perfect a performance and a tolerance for solitude. 
ISTPs respond to the challenge of complicated equipment that provides action. For example, large trucks, earth movers, and construction machinery are apt to fascinate an ISTP. They also find their need for excitement and action met in such occupations as surgery, electronics, car racing, bicycle racing, daredevil acts, acrobatics, athletics, and the like. Surely the gunslinger of yesterday and the hit man of today draw their great virtuosos from the ISTP pool. Outstanding craftsmen are also apt to come from this type-for example, the sculptor, the wood carver, the furniture maker, the cabinet maker, the tile maker, the weaver, and the rug maker. 
</careerdetail>
				<home>ISTPs enjoy solitude: and their ties with others can be somewhat superficial because they tend to connect with others through activities where body movement is involved rather than through face-to-face dialogue. Others sometimes find ISTPs distant and detached. </home>
				<midlife>At midlife ISTPs may be at the point of developing outstanding expertise in their craft, and a shift away from this may not be productive. They may, however, want to work on expanding the extraverted, gregarious side of their personalities and may need to develop discipline in completing one project before beginning another. </midlife>
				<mates>The adventuresome artisan may seek out his opposite in the ENFJ "teacher." As noted previously, in the ENFJ he finds a catalyst to growth, certainly a complementary quality to his artisanship. There is nothing, however, in the nature of the ENFJ that is catalytic to the adventurer side of the ISTP's temperament. If this theme is dominant in the ISTP, then the ENFJ-ISTP mating is headed for trouble. 
The ISTP is at least as attracted to the soothing, hosting, giving ESFJ. It takes the ESFJ "master of ceremonies" to get the ISTP off his motorcycle (surfboard, airplane, hang-glider) long enough to relate to others in more productive and facilitative ways. The ISTP needs this anchorage, else he wanders off into the frontier (when Horace Greeley said, "Go west, young man," the ISTP took him seriously and went!).
</mates>
				<strengths>•	Good listeners 
•	Usually self-confident 
•	Generally optimistic and fun to be with 
•	Practical and realistic, they handle daily concerns 
•	Are not threatened by conflict or criticism 
•	Able to leave a relationship with relative ease once it is over 
•	Able to administer punishment, although they're not interested in doing so 
•	Likely to respect other's needs for space and privacy 
</strengths>
				<weakness>•	Living entirely in the present, they have difficulty with long-term commitments 
•	Not naturally good at expressing feelings and emotions 
•	Not tuned in to what others are feeling, they may be insensitive at times 
•	Tendency to be overly private and hold back part of themselves 
•	Need a lot of personal space, which they don't like to have invaded 
•	They thrive on action and excitement, and may stir things up to create it 

</weakness>	
			</istp>
		
		
		
	<!--
		<lala>
				<title></title>
				<overview></overview>
				<temper> </temper>
				<population></population>
				<people>
				
				</people>
				<career>
				
				</career>
				<brief></brief>
				<living></living>
				<learning></learning>
				<working></working>
				<leading></leading>
				<loving></loving>
				<careerdetail></careerdetail>
				<home></home>
				<midlife></midlife>
				<mates></mates>
				<strengths></strengths>
				<weakness></weakness>	
			</lala>
		
		-->
	



</allaboutnature>